Is it good to do that? Hello, we are live. It's midday and yes, we are doing it later at 7 p.m.
So if you have tuned in and thought, oh, I'd really like my Sunday evenings in the UK listening to these two fellas.
Well, we're still doing that as well. And we're just waiting for Mr Anthony Chaffee to arrive.
But of course, let's introduce Richard Smith in case you don't know Richard. Richard, do you want to say hello?
Hello, nobody knows who I am.
Oh, they do. You've got six and a half thousand subscribers, I think. And I did an interview the other day
I mentioned you and there's always such a lot of people in the comments saying, I've not heard of him, but I'm going to go and find his channel now.
So, I should have a little extra bump there. And of course, they're going to know you at the Easter weekend, aren't they?
By the way, you and I are going to be at the wall on health.
Spot on. Yeah, wall on health. The end of this month, 30th and 31st of March.
Two-day event, some fantastic speakers lined up. Super excited. I still haven't written my presentation yet,
but I don't dare, Richard. But I know what I'll be talking about. It's just I find that
having visual aids helps explain things. So, the talk is is down to a tea hopefully within my head, but it
yeah, I just need to put it on onto onto those slides to present. Yeah, as you've got a
fact to do. Sorry, come. You've got a fantastic talk lined up as well?
Yes, well, I've been a goody, goody two-shoes and a little girly swap. And I've done my presentation,
sent it off to film the wall on health men. And yeah, I think it's going to be good. I'm going to be
talking about bloods. That's my presentation. It's going to be talking about the context of bloods
and how it's different when you're a carnival, when you're low-carb, when you're keto, and how
you can interpret them differently. And I mean at that back-up, that's my book there,
which is doing very well. I've got to blood tests in that context. So, I mean, that's one of the
things I'm looking forward to is actually getting out and seeing some people face to face rather than
being online. And then they can see, this isn't a filter. I've just got two white lights.
And I blew light behind me. And some people seem to think that I don't want to be out in the world,
well, but I'd much prefer that for becoming rich. Well, a thousand people this way can't
be rather than how many people at the conference. And of course, we've got a lot of people tuning
in him because they would like to see Dr. Anthony Chaffey, who was just passing it.
Yeah, he's just massaged to say he is now logging in, so keep your eyes peeled.
Oh, that was a nice backstage. So, let's bring it on, shall we? Can we bring him on?
Yeah, why not?
Oh, everyone. How are you doing? How are you both doing? Yes, really well. You?
Yeah, good. Good, good. It's not like there. Yeah, good. So, it's 8 p.m. with you. I think.
Yeah, it is. So, another late one. So, well appreciate it. Thanks for coming on. I know it's a little bit
awkward with you with the time difference, but great to see you. Oh, yeah, good. You guys.
Yeah, looking forward. Looking forward. Before we kick off, Steve, should we jump on to
what we were just speaking about in regards to events? So, Dr. Chaffey's coming to the UK?
Oh, yeah. Yeah, for the PhD event. So, do you want to talk a little bit about that?
Anthony, and then we'll go from there. So, yeah. So, the PhD conference is in
London this year, and that is what we can, is that it's May,
yeah, like the 18th and 19th that we can, like 17th, 18th and 19th. So, that's a big,
that's the the biggest annual conference that the public health collaboration have.
There's will be a ton of speakers, so people from the US and from Europe and Australia,
coming over to speak at that. So, the public health collaboration is, you know, they
really just trying to be both a grassroots movement to get people healthier and get the information.
And, you know, just the, you know, the best information that they can, so that people can
can fix their health and fix the health care system from the inside out, get other doctors on
so that they can see what they, you know, different sorts of tools that they can use to get
their patient's healthy and to try to affect political change as well, although that's always
difficult with all the, with all the special interests and money involved in politics, but, you know,
you can get people interested in these sorts of things when you get enough grassroots support.
Chaffee: So, that's sort of the idea there. And, yeah, so it would be my first one, I tried to go last year,
Chaffee: but then I had some these issues and I was grounded in, in Australia. So, this year, it's not a
problem and I'll be able to, uh, be able to come. So, are we great? Fantastic. Looking forward.
Thanks. Looking forward. Yeah. We've got tons of questions, of course, and a few people have
asked a question. Can I ask questions? So, yes, because it's a lot of question and answer thing.
It's not a live answer. So, uh, yeah, I wrote your questions. Um, if you could keep them to, to
carnival, that would be really handy as well, or key to a low-car, because there are some odd
questions, but I'll throw them at you and to the anyway, because why not, you know, it's Sunday.
So, I have the first question, you ready for this? Dr. Chavy?
So, yeah, sounds good. Okay, right. Hi, guys. I'm a long-term
Crohn's sufferer. We have an angel last week, uh, asked for me. After watching you and others,
I've started to think I could be cured on carnival. What's your views on this being possible?
My doctor says no. Uh, well, you know, most of the teaching would be, you know, that they would
say that, and that's, you know, a perfect one understandable bit that is coming from that point of
view, but no, that's that's absolutely possible. Um, you know, you need to be very, very strict.
Chaffee: You need to be on just red meat and water only. This is something that people have been using since
Chaffee: the 1800s. Um, there have been, you know, gastroenterologists in 1970s, uh, named Walter,
Dr. Walter Volklin. Don't know if that's pronouncing it right, but that's how I'm guessing with
it's with the weird spelling. And, uh, he wrote a book called The Stone Age Diet where he talked
about how humans are carnivores. Here's the, here's the evidence for that. And all these diseases
were treating now, basically a product of, of eating the wrong thing. And, you know, he, as a
gastroenterologist, was was pointing out that there's different diseases that he treated basically
if you didn't eat plants, you, you wouldn't need him as a, as a specialty as a profession.
But there, there are control trials and interventional trials and humans showing that
Crohn's disease in particular is very affected by diet, massively affected by diet. There are two
studies in particular. I think it very interesting. One was an interventional trial with, uh,
what's called an elemental diet and this person might be knowledgeable of this, maybe something
that he's tried before. It was, it was, something developed for ketogenic kids, or, sorry,
kids with epilepsy, so they were genetic ketogenic, but they're just the elements, right? So the
macronutrients micronutrients that you need, uh, to survive. And nothing else, and it's generally
ketogenic. So you just take this shake, it's very processed, but it's, you know, it's just the macros
and macros and macros and nothing else. And they found that that was a better treatment for Crohn's
disease for an acute clot flare, but Crohn's disease that then prednisone, so steroids,
prednisone into UK and Australia. Um, so just not eating certain things was a better treatment than
steroids, which is the gold standard for getting someone out of, out of the bad flare up. Um, so
obviously that has, the update has a lot to do with this changing something that you, it seems to be
have a cause and effect relationship. You remove something, problem goes away. You return that
something, problem comes back directly. That's a cause and effect relationship. There was another study
that just removed carbohydrates and fiber and saw how long, you know, try to see how long
people would, would go into, stay in remission without medications. And some of the parts of
this bit in state and remission without medications up to 51 months, um, which is over four
years. So that's, uh, that's quite a long time with, with, in full, in full remission, um, with
just dietary changes. And contrast that with those who did not come out of, uh, of, um, come off
and fiber, they, they stayed in remission average zero months, right? There's a big contrast there.
So yes, of course, diet has, has everything to do with this disease, as with all other
autoimmune diseases, my opinion, but especially the cost. I mean, like you, how can you say that
that the food that you eat that passes through that organ does not affect that organ in any way
perform? I mean, you have to sort of, you have to, you have to, you have to wonder if the person's
really thinking that through, um, but of course it does. And there are, there are studies that say that.
Now, that's not what's taught in gastroenterology,
residences, because that doesn't sell pills. And so, you know, there's a product at the end of
that. So you don't have a multimillion dollar marketing firm budgeted out to, to push this out and
things get them on to a certain diet, no more crumbs. You know, there's no money. You know,
there's no, there's no money at the end of that. So no one's going to spend the money marketing
and getting reps out to gastroenterologists say, oh, who use my product? Here's this thing,
Chaffee: just tell people to buy meat. I don't know if the cattleman's association wants to get on that,
but, you know, if it's, um, but if someone has, you know, an interest in that can figure out
some way of monetize that, get in there. Because, you know, this is, this is a better treatment
than steroids. And it's a hell of a lot less expensive than the biologic agents that they
they use as well, which are quite harmful in a number of different ways. And yes, can help people
disorder lesser of two evils, but you know, you're not winning this situation. It's horribly
expensive. It has a lot of side effects. And then you still have this issue. And you're only treating
the, you know, you're only treating the symptoms. You're not actually counteracting the disease
whereas when you're just the diet, you are addressing the root cause mechanism. As can be seen,
you remove certain things from the diet, disease goes away. That's a cause and effect relationship.
So you address the root cause. Obviously, that's always going to be the best answer.
Yeah, that's great, Anthony. So this, this is where I go with the common sense.
Basically, I have clients that come to me with Crohn's, they go kind of, and they've got it anymore.
You know, that's sort of proof. And normally, they say, I've tried everything. I mean, that's
really common thing that they say. I literally, this is my last chance to do, you know, something
like that. I've tried every sort of diet and they try carnival and they can't believe that, you know,
and they've had all these problems, all these gut, you know, issues, crones in particular,
as one that always comes up, at least once a month, they get a client that's struggling with it.
And they, this way, and it goes. And some of them look a bit bitter that I've been told about this
way of eating. And the best ones, actually, are the ones that are skeptical. They come to it,
thinking, what I'm going to do here, I don't think is good for me. And they do it, and they can't
believe it. So they're sort of reluctant carnivores at first, they tend to come round to it.
Rich, I can't bear you being quiet for so long, mate. So do you want to chime in a bit?
Nobody wants to listen to me chat in when Dr. Chief is on onboard, right?
No, just to add really quickly, I mean, it makes perfect sense. We look for these magic
pedals, but as Anthony says, it's, you know, addressed the root cause and these issues go away,
these issues are caused by an inflammatory basis and intestinal permeability. And this is what
plants do. They cause a intestinal permeability and they cause lots of inflammation, remove those two
factors. And everything else just clears up and goes away. Eat meat next time. It's a simple as that.
So I'm going to put some of the comments up because, you know, they are pertinent to what we're
talking about. Coffers Carnival Kitchen Aussies meet Dr. Chief in person, regenerate regenerate
health summit and that's in Melbourne on the 21st of April. So thanks for that. It's always good to
plug these things so you can meet your heroes in person. Right, he's going to be in Austin as well.
So, right, Dr. Chief, you're all over the place. So we're going to move on to a question.
Now, really, what are your top five favorite movies?
Chaffee: Well, I don't know. I think it changes for a very long time. Number one was Ace Ventura.
Chaffee: Head replaced that. I don't think I've ever laughed harder at a movie in my entire life than
Chaffee: when I watched Ted in the theaters. And I watched it three more times that week. I think I
watched it. The Monday it came out then the Tuesday, then the Wednesday and then the Friday again.
And then I think I watched it only twice the next week. And then I went back and watched
Flash Gordon, which is a terrible, terrible movie from 1980. Because I've only seen it as a kid.
And so I was watching that just to like augment my, my, my Ted watching experience to, you know,
sort of be back in the minds that of that of that movie. And so those are definitely
going to be up there. I tend to like comedies, especially what sort of pops up in my head.
But one of my favorite moves for a long time was things like happy Gilmore as well. I'm always
cracking me up. I always thought that was Adam Sandler's best movie. And I mean, there are actual
really good movies that are not, they're not just goofy comedies that I really like. I'm just
not really thinking about them. And, um, oh my gosh, why can't I think of anything?
Chaffee: Well, and, and then maybe I'll just put series after that, like the, you know, the original
Chaffee: store was the original, uh, three Indiana Jones. Yeah, exactly. Yeah, just stop, stop after that.
Yeah, but I watched those hundreds of times as a kid or dozens anyway. But I would like watch,
like the store all the way through and then like start over the beginning and just do that.
You always had like the youngest kid in the house, just basically controlled the TV. And you're just
like, yeah, he's on there again. You know, so that was, that was me for it's high anyway. And then
it was my little brother, uh, with borrowing of all things. I did not, I did not know why the hell
you did that. But yeah, it's never into that stupid dinosaur. I know that I know the dinosaur
you mean. Right. Yeah, a proper question. A proper question. A proper question now. Could
take an iodine or iodine, depending where you live, cause weight gain in a 65 year old female.
Shouldn't, um, you know, if you have, you know, I caution people about about iodine just because
you can exacerbate hashing motos and most people, uh, who with thyroid dysfunction don't
don't ever get that checked. And or don't even necessarily know they've had, they have thyroid
dysfunction. So, you know, I just caution people, um, that, you know, if you don't have iodine
deficiency, you know, why are you taking iodine? Um, you may. Most people do, but, um, you know,
if, if they're on a like a standard sort of diet, they certainly might anyway. Most people have
a lot of vitamin and mineral deficiencies, but you may not. And so if you have, if you don't have,
I don't think there's any point in taking it. If you are a bit low and you want to supplement it,
I just, you know, I just, and especially if you're worried about your thyroid, it's like,
oh, my, my thyroid slightly underactive, or could be, could be iodine. What could be,
Chaffee: but it could be something else as well. And so, you know, check, if you have thyroid dysfunction,
Chaffee: then you check yourself for hashing motos. It is way more common than people think. You know,
Chaffee: people generally don't look for hashing motos until it's a disaster until the TSA,
Chaffee: just above 10. And then they start investigating and saying, oh, okay, well, why the hell is that happening?
And it's, it's, it's a bit, you know, the horses out of the barn at that point. You know,
I mean, you should, you missed your moment. And so, you know, the thyroid is severely damaged at that point
and may not ever recover fully. And so, you know, obviously you want to, you know, you want to
get on top of it before that. So I would check in my patient population well before we get to that
mark. If your TSA is above two, it can double your risk of developing thyroid cancers. So obviously,
that's not normal. Even though I can go up to 4, 4.5, depending on the area, I can go possibly higher
than that. But, you know, just above two is a double your risk of thyroid cancers. So that's obviously
not an acceptable range to keep your patients in. So I would check before that. And, and we actually
find quite a lot of people with Hashimoto's, you know, it just hasn't just completely destroyed them.
So no, I don't think it's going to raise, you know, make you gain weight. Unless it's sort of
around about sort of way that you exacerbated Hashimoto's rows of your antibodies damage your thyroid
you produced less thyroid hormone in that to breast your metabolism. But taking iodine shouldn't
directly cause weight gain, no. No, I don't think so. And just add a couple of people, message me,
they're listing in headphones and they can hear, I think they can hear your hands on the mic
and to me. So. Really? Okay. Yeah. I don't know. Anyway, right. Yeah, that's it. That's the noise.
Thank you. We have a lovely question here, which Richard will be able to answer as well.
Greetings to all. What does it exactly mean 24 hour live? What does that mean?
Richard that that is our 24 hour live for 24 hours.
So you knew that. And it's a spot on. Relay on on YouTube for 24 hours. Last year, Steven and I
did the world's first ever 24 hour live carnivoreathon. It was alive that we discussed. All things
carnivore, all things healthy, keep door. We touched based on a little bit also. But it's alive
in which we get fantastic guests come on each hour. Dr. Chaffey kindly joined us for three
hours. I think two or three hours last year. I was two. Yeah. All last time. I think three hours.
Yeah. And I would say this time, I was two hours this time. Two this time, I believe.
Okay. Yeah. Yeah. Are you scared? I was like, I need to go to sleep.
Chaffee: I was up until like three, third in the morning last night, and then up at seven for work today.
Chaffee: I was like, I was just like, oh, did I do that to myself again? Okay. That's all right.
And then we have you dragged on on the shows at 8 p.m.
It's time. But we're actually really appreciated. Yeah. Oh, so good.
I mean, I stood for 24 hours like this. That's it. 24 hours. I'm engaged in it. I had to
tell what I nipped to have a pee, basically. But I didn't know you didn't drink, you know,
which I don't think you could do when you're high car or you could only do it when you're
fat adapted, I think. But it's, that's it. It's really that simple. 24 hour life stream.
We start in UK, I think at 9 a.m. A.m. on the 7th of the 7th. And the idea was that you could
remember it because it's 2477, 24 hours on the 7th of the 7th, right? Not 2477, but 2477.
Right. Don't miss that. We got Dr. Anthony Chaffee, of course, top of the bill. And then we've got
another supporting people, like Robert Kiltz, you know, and Dr. Sarah Sawd and Philip Evardia.
And we got Sean Baker and tons of other great guests. So I'm already joking there.
Anyway, go into it. No, I have joke from Anthony. You know, my favourite joke or call
me joke is, who would you like to have as a guest at a dinner party, a live or dead, and I'm like,
someone alive, you know, so yeah, right. Yeah, definitely someone alive and be good.
Once a week, man, which is a great pun, why will we all agree that diet, animal based, of course,
is very important in achieving good health? What role does Anthony Chaffee think, quantum biology
plays? For example, blue, right, blue, light exposure. Yeah. Well, well, I do think that that's important.
Chaffee: I mean, we're trying to, we're trying to really cater to our own biology and our make-up.
Chaffee: And we are trust real beings. We're not trogledites. We didn't grow up in a cave or deep under the sea,
grew up in the sun and on earth. And that's, that's where our bodies are designed to be.
Now does that necessarily mean that we have to do that? No. But it's not surprised me that there's
more and more evidence coming out that there is an effect that this has and it could be extremely
positive and beneficial. Our circadian rhythm is well and truly tied up with the cycles of light.
And we started getting this light pollution in our eyes and he's blue, lights, and white lights,
and things like that in and around our house. And we're screwing that up. Our brains tell
what time it is based on a frequency of light that's coming into your eyes and in your brains.
And so, you know, you're, you're messing with that. Your brain doesn't know really what's going on.
You may disrupt your hormones. You may bounce off your circadian rhythm. You may not get
your testosterone in the morning. You may not get your cortisol or estrogen or your melatonin
night or your growth hormone. All these sorts of things. There's all these different hormones
wrapped in its tons and tons and tons of hormones. But they may not be as able to function properly
and be released properly. So I do absolutely think that this is something that is very beneficial
to our health, to try to be out in the sun in the morning, or to try to be outside whenever you
can. You know, barefoot, I don't know much about these sorts of things apart from, you know,
seeing these things peripherally. And, you know, we're not seeing any reason why I would
doubt it. I need to look more into it and speak to people like Dr. Jack Cruz and and start
and take a look at a lot of the studies that he talks about and others talk about. But, you know,
it's fairly mainstream understanding about how light affects our circadian rhythm
and our hormonal cycles. That's not, that's not fringe. You know, that's been, that's been
out there for a very long time. I'm very mainstream scientists such as Andrew Huberman and others
talk about this regularly. But, I mean, this is something that's been around for decades. So
I definitely think that that plays a major role in our life. And, I mean, I even just look at
how I feel when I go camping for two weeks, but few times I've ever done that. And I've just been,
you know, up with the sun and then busy all day and then, you know, doing things outside.
And then light goes down, sun goes down, fire goes on, hanging out. I'm just naturally like,
oh, I just want to go to sleep. I'm not on my phone. I'm not on these screens. I don't have any
artificial life besides the fire. And, and I go to sleep. I sleep like an absolute baby like a
Chaffee: well well-behaved baby. And something went on all sleep. And, and then I wake up, you know,
Chaffee: with the first crack of light, I get up and I feel great, you know. And when you get into that pattern,
you do that for, you know, a couple weeks. You just feel fantastic at the end of that. You know,
Chaffee: you really feel the charge and refresh. So I certainly like that. And something I want to look into
Chaffee: more, but no, I absolutely think that that has a big role to play in our health.
Yeah, and I think I think the people that are skeptical when I talk about that sort of stuff,
I say, have you ever worked in an office where you haven't had a window, and then you've suddenly moved,
and it's just got a window. Does that make a difference? There's a real simple thing like that.
Like, well, yeah, actually, my lounge is a bit dark, so I tend to be at the back of my house,
where there's French doors. All right, well, there you go. You are just believing that daylight is
going to help you because it does. I mean, it seems obvious to me, if you've ever been in a dark room,
right, I knew you'd say the dark sort of a pressy room because dark rooms were a pressy
for a lot of the time. So I think you're right to talk about all the science there, but sometimes
just a real-world experience, and you talk to them and you're camping and all that, and people often
sort of say, we have a lot of that person's on holiday, so yeah, but also what I just said,
you can be at work and feel better because you're near a window or you've got a better view,
or it's a sunny day, and you can see the birds, oh, you know, there's so many good things
about nature. Right, we've got somebody really thankful for your appearance here, the Paris Simon.
Super chat for Dr. Chaffey there. Thanks for all you do, Dr. Chaffey. I'm doing carnivore,
but I'm having an all-over body cramping issue. I take a good AMT of electrolytes,
amounts of things, along with trace elements, and drink almost a gallon of water per day,
Chaffee: could this be oxalate dumping or question mark? Well, cramping potentially quite often cramps
Chaffee: are to do with, they could be, they could be electrolytes such as magnesium,
and most people will be low on magnesium if not, you know, probably not outright deficient,
Chaffee: but, you know, lower than they want to be. I don't know if it would be oxalate dumping, although
Chaffee: oxalate dumping can sort of manifest as almost anything is just sort of affect things in a lot of
Chaffee: different ways, but generally cramps are dehydration, my experience, and certainly when you are
Chaffee: losing too much water and just have required more water throughout your day. And so I tend to
Chaffee: find that even when people are taking electrolytes, they're just not getting any improvement from
that, some do, but, you know, the vast majority of people that I hear about, you know,
Chaffee: so people will just take electrolytes and that does end this fine. But other times, you know,
Chaffee: when you actually hear about it, when people have been taking electrolytes, I mean, trying
Chaffee: these sorts of things and I'm like, look, this is just not helping. Do I take more electrolytes?
What do I do? And to me, it's like, you know, obviously it's not the electrolytes at that point.
You're taking electrolytes. You're covering that. It's almost always dehydration. It's almost always
that they need more water. You know, I understand that you're drinking about a gallon of
a day, and it just may not be enough for your needs at the moment. So I'll just try to ramp that up
Chaffee: and see if you can add that on. If you just feel like you're drowning, like, I just really can't
Chaffee: drink anymore than fair enough, but do try to increase it from there and see how you go
it's probably going to be a short-term thing. You might not need this for a long time, but especially
in some of the months in places like Australia and if you were active and they're outdoors,
you're going to need more water. And if you're transitioning over to a corner of where
died, sometimes you can have a higher requirement for water early on. And so most often when people
get these cramps, it's because of dehydration, my experience. It can be other things. That's the most common
part. And do you think that it's possible to drink too much water and cause dehydration because
your body is expel in the excess water and therefore taking an electrolyte out so you get this
vicious circle of overdrinking? Well, you can certainly cause hyponotremia, and so you can flush out
too much sodium, and that's not safe. Obviously, that's not that's not good. If you're taking
away, but yeah, you can definitely over consume water and then cause a hyponotremia. So we
will need to be careful of that. That affects your brain, generally. It doesn't cause cramps.
Mate, low magnesium can cause cramps. I've never seen the patient in the hospital
that had low sodium or low potassium clinically on blood reports. And we see it in the
hospital. You know, Mr. Davis has a low potassium. They don't present with cramping. They have
other symptoms. If it gets low enough, if you're showing those below 130, you have extremely
confusing, it's rubble to demon and things like that. So it's actually quite unsafe. But they're
the fargic. They're very sleepy. They're hard to browse them. Very confused and don't know what
the hell is going on. And they're just sort of basically slipping into a coma. So that's pretty obvious,
you know, when that happens and the obvious part of it is not body cramps. You know, so when
it goes, oh, I need more salt. Yeah, maybe you do, but I don't think that's it's just going to be
brilliant. I always have in the works Steve, can I just throw a spanner in the works in regards to
that one? Yeah, please do. I mean, there's never some of the screen. And that's the point of
us being here. Crump in, in my experience is usually a calcium issue, excess calcium and calcium
excites the muscle, calcium depletes magnesium. So we can combat this through two ways, either decrease
and calcium or increase in the magnesium. The thing with excess calcium is that it also depletes
sodium. A gallon seems like a lot to me. And I think it could be the opposite issue. I think
you could be drinking too much water with maybe not the right ratio of electrolytes. It'd be
interesting to find out one how much calcium you consume in. I eat if you live in a carnival
lifestyle and you did not have eggs, you'd be surprised how much calcium that is in an egg is around
20 to 25 milligrams per egg of calcium. If we look as nature intended, a piece of beef and everything
within nature comes with a set amount or set ratio of electrolytes potassium is really high.
So potassium predominates and it's about four times higher than sodium, then it drops right
down to magnesium and below that again is calcium. And a best calcium is an even level with
magnesium and this is how the cell operates. It's a one to one ratio roughly. If we increase the
calcium too much with maybe cheese or raw milk or eggs, that can throw that ratio out. And again,
that calcium also depletes potassium which can lead to further cramping issues. If you are
using electrolytes and the ratio of sodium to potassium is wrong, then that can also lead to cramping
because most of the electrolytes predominates sodium and then they drop right down with a low level of
potassium, but the potassium needs to be almost level to the sodium because excess sodium also
depletes potassium. So you've got all of these contributing factors going on in there. So first of
all I'd look at the calcium, look at the electrolytes make sure that the potassium is not so the
ratio that we see with more the electrolytes on the market is say 1,000 milligrams of sodium
and then they'll drop right down to 200 milligrams of potassium. That 200 needs to be at least
five and ready for not higher. And that's the closer to one to one ratio, the better. Once you
address those two things, then maybe look at combat in the water intake. And again, as Steven
says, drinking too much water can dehydrate because your flesh and out electrolytes especially
if that ratio is wrong in the first place. Calcium is usually the biggest contributing factor as
excitery to the muscle. So again, combat with either increase in magnesium or reduce in the calcium.
Thanks for me. Yeah, I hadn't actually heard that Hypercalcemia cause
cramping low Calcemia is certainly does because tetany and you test this, you sort of tap on the
muscle and just through your face will cramp up and things like that, you sort of kind of put
like a turning came in your arm and sort of tap these muscle and all just they'll just cramp up
like hell. But you know, you can always check these sorts of things and you're going to just
to see where you're at. And you know, if you surely don't need to take a whole bunch of calcium
or anything like that, you know, some people think that they need to take a lot of supplements.
You don't generally, well, like specifically calcium, you know, I think that you need to eat a lot of
there's a line that's get calcium to make its milk. Right, you're eating from meat, right? And so they're
getting to obviously there's calcium in meat and your body, you know, uses that and efficiently.
Chaffee: As opposed to when you're eating a bunch of plants with anti nutrients and oxidizing,
Chaffee: stripping all this calcium out, you need it over abundance in order to overwhelm that and just
Chaffee: get the little that you need. When you're all mammals are weening their, they treat their
Chaffee: milk and then they ween on to the mother's diet and they eat that diet for the rest of their life.
Chaffee: And that's when most of the long bones are growing. So that's when most of this growth is happening.
So the, the, the most, uh, calcium demand happens after their ween after they're off milk.
And again, where the hell is the mother getting that calcium to give to the baby in the first place
if the mother's diet is deficient and the child is going to be weened onto the mother's diet.
And that's when most of this, the bones are going to grow and most of the calcium is going to be
be deposited. So, um, yeah, you get onto these sorts of diets. You certainly don't need to take
a lot of calcium supplements unless you have an actual deficiency, like I just don't think
Chaffee: people need to supplement as much as, um, as some do, unless they have a deficiency. Now, there's
Chaffee: a lot of people that do have deficiencies. There are a lot of people that that come in and they've just
been on different diets, just, you know, standard diet or a plant-based diet. And they're in a
be deficient. They're going to be very deficient. Horrible diets are going to catch you up,
especially if you include some more high dense parts of the animal, like the organs.
That's that supplements for carnivores is Oregon. But if you're extremely deficient and, you know,
it's sort of at a dangerously low level, you know, sure, you know, go ahead and supplement.
Chaffee: But if you're not, you know, then I don't think that's a good idea. Especially if you're in normal
Chaffee: ranges, there's no point in supplementing if you're in a normal range. And, you know, as people know
Chaffee: from listening to me, the normal range isn't, isn't all that normal, uh, from the reference range.
Chaffee: The reference range are an average for the community that every single lab has a different one.
So, they have, when they're changing the reference range, updating the reference range is
first 2000 people that come in, that is the reference range. And so, that's going to be different
every single lab. And as we get sicker and fatter and more malnourished, those ranges just change
and they get worse and worse and worse. And I say, oh, look, you're normal. And, um, you know,
but you're comparing yourself to sick malnourished people. So, in actual good ranges, if you're actually
in those actual good ranges, then you definitely don't need to supplement. Yeah, especially with
calcium, I'm always, I'm not a big fan of calcium supplementation, either supplementation or
excess in the diet because studies have shown excessive amounts of 700 milligrams per day,
can increase risk of cardiovascular disease, where as much as 15%. So, you know, I eat eggs, but
I'm well below the 500. And I think if we eat as nature intended, then, you know, these issues tend
to go away, don't they? But not a big fan of calcium supplementation. If we look how nature
intended, you'll need two things in nature that contain high calcium as Dr. Chiefy alluded to there
is eggs, which give birth to animal and milk, mother's breast milk. That's the only
and we're not meant to drink milk past the age of infancy, um, let alone from another animal. So,
it, um, these contributing factors, I think, can, can massively impact. And our absorption of
calcium is, or, I would need for it is massively reduced as, as we, as we get older because of
vitamin D and K2 and sodium and, um, um, and protein, all of these things
build bone and send the calcium into the bone. In fact, calcium absorption to bone is directly
correlated with salt, which a lot of people don't realize. So, we need salt to send calcium to the
bone. So, a deficiency of salt could cause a problem even. Brilliant. And I'm going to plug
my book, which talks about normal ranges in the context of, uh, keto and kind of all there. So,
yeah, I've just, occasionally, that diet of blood tests. Anyway, right, um, and I talk about
all that sort of stuff. We've got a great question here, which is, um, by the way, this is not
medical advice. It's all for information and educational purposes. Uh, what would be causing me
to get nasty bruising veins in my right leg being carnival over a year? I don't lift anything
Chaffee: heavy. Um, well, it may not have anything to do with, with a carnivore diet. I don't,
I can't really think of anything that would do that. I mean, generally bruising is caused,
well, it is caused by damage to the blood vessels and capillaries. And, and you bleed out,
Chaffee: you bleed in sort of under the skin. And so, I don't know if you're on any medication that may
Chaffee: increase your risk of bleeding or something like that, but it, it really shouldn't happen unless
sort of bumping it on something or something's damaging it or some sort of trauma. Even
Chaffee: even some people have very probable tissue and very thin tissue. And, uh, and it can bruise very
Chaffee: easily, especially if they're on medications like blood thinners or aspirin, which a lot of people are
on. Um, but you just don't show up unless you at least had something touch it, push it, hit it. So
it's always happening on the right leg. I would wonder what's going on with that right leg. I can't
think of anything to do with a carnivore diet, maybe, maybe Steven and Richard may have some thoughts,
but, um, you know, if you, if you continue to have this right on and on, um, might be worth going
to your doctor and just having them take a look at it and just see what's going on because it's not,
you know, it's a bit odd that you just have continued bruising that same leg if you're not having
something hit it or bump it. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Cool. Rich. Oh, gone. You, you've gone.
Well, I was going to say, yeah, go to the doctor. Exactly what, uh, anti-JFEC sit there and just get your
cotton factors look to. Yeah. We're going to Rich. I'd, I'd question which side of of your body
you sleep on? Um, that might be a fact that you sit with your legs crossed. Uh, is it one? Is it a
store for the right, for example? Um, have you lost so much weight that now you can see things that
weren't there prior and are you in all the gristly things on your meat? Are you getting all the collagen?
Are you eating the gristler on the bone and the fatty cuts of the stringy bits on the beef
all of these are really important for building, uh, and forming collagen within the body.
Um, a couple of things to take with there, but it is a strange one. I was especially
it was on one side. Yeah. Yeah. That's moving on. I think, um, that's pretty much covered.
Uh, we have the next question here, which is, uh, I have Moia Moio. What were kind of or do for me?
Well, that's a good question. So that's, um, that's, uh, well, that's a, that's a, that's a complicated,
pathology, but that basically what that has to do with the vessels in the brain can be very
friable and so they can get a lot of bleeds. Um, and that can cause, uh, strokes. And so sometimes we do
bypass surgery to re-baskularize or, or, you know, bypass certain areas that are better damaged, um,
of people with Moia Moia. Uh, I don't know of any, any studies with ketogenic diet,
um, with Moia Moia. Um, so I can't tell you. I can't tell you what's going to happen with that.
It's a very rare disease and I just don't know, um, many people who have, I don't think I
know anybody who's tried a carnivore diet with Moia Moia. Maybe one that I spoke to a while ago,
but I don't know how they're doing with that. It's, it's one of those things that, you know,
Chaffee: we don't have a lot of data on everything. This is certainly one that we don't or that I don't know
Chaffee: about. I don't know if anyone else knows about ketogenic diets with Moia Moio. I don't know if
you guys even have come across Moia Moio. It's super rare, but it's, um, it's, uh, going to improve
Chaffee: your life in a lot of ways anyway. It's going to improve your Moia Moia. You don't know. Um,
Chaffee: you know, things like Crohn's disease where you remove the food, the food is really causing
Chaffee: your body to react and, and, and, and, and make antibodies and attack your body. So that's a
cause and effect relationship. And I can tell you what that's going to do when you, when you go on a
carnivore diet, it's, it's going to go away. But with Moia Moia, um, I, I can't say that same thing.
I don't know what the underlying cause is for Moia Moio. So I don't know how, um, a carnivore diet
is going to affect that. I would, what I would imagine is, you know, this is sort of a, uh,
you know, inflammatory sort of condition and this can cause friability of the vessels.
This is going to improve your collagen. This is going to improve your information. This is
going to improve a lot of different things that could contribute to that. But I have absolutely no
idea. The, the best thing to do is just try it. See what happens with it. You're going to feel
a thousand times better anyway. You're going to fix a lot of different sorts of things. You know,
none of us here have had Moia Moia and yet we're still doing carnivore because we feel so much
better and our bodies work so much better and our brains work so much better. And so even though
we didn't necessarily reverse something serious like Moia Moia, it's still worth it to a. So I think
Chaffee: it will still be worth it to you to do that and very well may help with that. However, it would just be
Chaffee: sort of a wait and see sort of thing. But I don't know what you guys think. Well, I think if anything
is, well, I mean, just clarify for people, it's the obstruction of the arteries, arteries at the
base of the brain and the cause is unknown. You see, so it's very difficult to answer anything where
the cause is unknown because if you don't know the cause, how can you fix that? But I think what
you're saying, Dr. Chase is, if you, if you deal with your systemic inflammation, you're giving
your body the best environment possible to make that condition less troublesome. If you've
got an obstruction in the artery, it's there. So if you're then inflamed in your arteries and
inflamed around that area, then that blockage is going to be even more restricted, isn't it?
Then the blood flow to the brain is going to be restricted. So you may find going carnivore
because you reduce inflammation. You start to feel better. I mean, I'm a great believer in
a common sense. It's not going to kill you. It's not going to make it worse. So I think, you know,
just trying it and then coming back, actually in six and weeks and saying, yeah, did and we would
like to have a case study. We don't like to have someone who has had that and it has improved because
that's how you start to learn about these things. I mean, I think everybody on the screen admits,
we probably know like 1% of what we'd like to know about the body. So, you know, I've not come across
15 years already have five years of doing carnivore coaching. Never had to climb with it. So
I think I can't see it doing anything other than improving situation. Did you want to say
to the rich? No, I think you guys have covered up. Okay, Jacqueline's next and she's a newbie,
10 weeks into carnivore, well done and I have low blood pressure and feel shaky and no energy.
Do I know you can more soaked? I take a lecture like this, but maybe not enough.
Chaffee: Yeah, well look, 10 weeks is a wow to have electric issues. But if you have low blood
Chaffee: pressures and feeling shaky, then you can add that can absolutely be from low sodium, low
electrolytes and that can drop your blood pressure. So if you're feeling that, well, you've
already checked your blood pressure. So you know, you have low blood pressure. So,
Chaffee: eat more salt, drink more water and especially when people sometimes is more subtle. So sometimes,
Chaffee: you know, when you get up, you stand up, you have a sort of a head rushing, oh, you feel a bit
sort of woozy and then that recovers. You know, how is everybody, you know, even in normal conditions.
But if that's how many you regularly, that could be because you're getting this postural
drop in blood pressure that's that's maintaining and you're not able to overcome that normally.
And so if you have those sorts of things, you should think, am I getting enough salt, am I
getting enough water, those sorts of things? Yeah, I agree. And the water, I think was a big
contributing factor there because that does help with blood pressure. But salt, yeah, it's the
Chaffee: team. So possibly too much potassium, potassium calms a heart. So we want increase the salt.
Chaffee: Yeah, and I would question if you are still feeling dizzy, are you eating enough juggling?
Are you consuming enough food? Maybe you're not eating enough fat and protein. So a couple
of things to look at there potentially. Yeah, and Jacqueline, I think is actually a member of our
school community. So you can always come to our live question and answers and get to more in depth
one. Well, obviously we're making the most of having Dr Anthony Chafew with us today. So anyway,
I hope those answers helped you. Scott is asking, I think Richard might jump in with this one as well.
What do you think about MCT oil and its data use? But Dr Chafew first, as you're the guest?
Well, I just tend to avoid it. I don't use it myself. I just try to get animal fats.
There may be advantages to MCT oils, but I just, I just like getting
natural fats from meat in what I'm eating. I tend to steer clear of some of the plant oils in any
case, just because they come along with plant stirrows. If they're out of the plant and they're unsaturated,
you know, are they stable or are they oxidized and on these up the sorts of things? I just try to eat
meat and fat in it's whole form. That's my usual go to. Yeah, Richard, as always, I completely agree.
I think we should get as many compounds from animal proteins as we can. I am a big lover of
MCT, particularly C8, C8, is the 6% of the coconut oil. Again, it does come from plants, but when
it's at 99.9% all of the other nasties within that compound have been removed. But there are
benefits. MCT is not the healthiest fat, you know, and people believe that it is because of its
microbial benefits. It's, in fact, it's the most anti microbial substance available without a
doctor's prescription. But it isn't the healthiest. Animal fats are the healthiest for us, but where
MCT comes into a league of his own is this ability to convert into key dawns incredibly quickly.
Key dawns, the production of BHB. So when we consume the C8, for example, it sends straight to
the liver through the patty portal vein, and it's almost instantly converted into beta hydroxybode
red. And it will do this, whether you are live in a ketogenic carnival or even a carb lifestyle,
it will instantly convert. And therefore, the benefits of the BHB will follow, i.e., the block
in of NLRP3 and flammers also lower in inflammation, increase the incidence sensitivity. The
key dawns will breach the blood-brain barrier and fill well the brain with energy. It will increase
the mechanical efficiency of the heart by as much as 35% and blood flow by as much as 70%. So it does
have its benefits. Again, it does come from a plant, but it's a tool for me. It doesn't make a part of
my diet, but I do find it beneficial, especially for things like public speaking events where,
you know, you may be feeling a little bit tired and you need that energy to the brain. You don't
want to drink the coffee because of the acrylicide, and we know Dr. Chief is not a fan of coffee at all,
as it causes massive neuroinflammation with him, especially in the legs, if I can remember correctly.
Bremstity, that could confer a benefit in that instance, for example, because it's going to supply
that our instant energy. But it's a tool. It's the same as everything else. Isn't it?
Electolides are a tool. All of these things are tools. Do you need them to be fit and healthy?
Or, if you eat nothing but meat, you are going to be considerably fit and healthier than any other
point in your life. But all of these things are tools that may confer a benefit as and when you
like to use them, you know? Yeah. And it's a brilliant mess out of your will.
Chaffee: I always, I always did wonder, and I'm thank you for clarifying that. I was just was a bit nervous
Chaffee: with MCT oils. It doesn't come up with a plant sterile. It doesn't come up with all the crap
that you don't want. So it does sound like there is some available that you can get pretty pure.
So if you are visiting, obviously, which we know you are in May, the PhD, I'll bring some with
me for you to try, because I produce it. So I mean, I don't, I haven't just rented that off because
it's a sales pitch. And as you know, I produce certain products to help people along their journey.
But I do these things because I believe that there is a benefit to use in them. And there is
that this is why I produce what I believe to be the world's purest form of electrolytes.
And that's something else I'd like to get you to try because we produce in a carnival version,
which is all natural ingredients and there's going to be no artificials. And it also contains a
compound called AstraZanthin, which is the world's only true and deoxidant. And again,
we can chat about that. And if it's something that comes from salmon, but we've produced one
of the carnival community specifically that doesn't contain any stevia. The only downside is
the vast majority of the market that are gravitated into a low carb, ketogenic carnival lifestyle,
don't want to drink salt water, whereas AstraZanthin would gladly do so. Many people
are one step too far, but it's all about these incremental changes. And MCT and electrolytes are,
you know, or they do make up at least part of those incremental changes. And allow people to
maintain the journey. And that's what it's all about. It's supposed to stay in the journey,
maintain in the journey. If we can't sustain or maintain everything falls apart.
Brilliant. Sorry to be like the teacher here, but I'm moving along. We have 547 people and
up that 200 questions. So I know we won't get through them all. And if you've put a question on
I think you're very much, if you've done it recently, we're trying to get through them as
quick as a possible but we want to give you a proper answer to every question as well. So
casten is asking, oh, I mean, caused by lectins, how strong is the scientific data?
Well, Richard might have a lot to say on this, but you know, there's, well, there's, it's actually
Chaffee: something that we do see. We see these lectins getting into the body and interacting with our body
and interacting with our cell. We see it in our gut. We term a gluten is that's binding
onto the surface antigens on ourselves. And in the gut, and that can cause damage, leaky gut,
and then these little suckers can get in there. So that's been demonstrated. We have demonstrated
that these can get in the body. We can see lectins tracking up the vagus nerve into the brain.
We can see them that they're binding onto the different carbohydrates and antigens on different
Chaffee: cell structures in the body. And then we all of a sudden have this specific immune response
with antibodies that are specific. So if they're just sort of attacking something,
but now they're attacking something specific, we can look for action-moderate antibodies.
We can test for these sorts of things, right? So that means there's some sort of specific
complex on the likely on the thyroid that is that the body is attacking. And then you stop
reading these things and antibodies go away. So, you know, in certainly, from a clinical standpoint,
you see this again, it causes an effect relationship. You remove these sorts of things. The
antibodies just go down and they go away. And you can measure them both in patient symptoms,
and also in the actual blood form. You're going to look for these specific antibodies
they go away. So I have patients, oh, I don't even know, I estimate over 100 patients with
Hashimoto's and a lot of other autoimmune issues, but Hashimoto's being the definitely most
prevalent in my in my patient population. And certainly if you have one autoimmune issue,
you'd likely have others. So, you know, they will also likely have other autoimmune issues as well,
but at least that many with Hashimoto's. And we measure these things. And so, you know, we
change their diet, put them on a carnivore diet, especially like a red meat moderate diet.
And you just look, their antibodies are in the thousands, and then they're in the hundreds,
and then they're in the tens, and then they're gone. They're just not registering, they're
just undetectable. And that's, and that's what we see. We see this in real time. So, it's,
you know, it's certainly enough evidence for me to, you know, do this for my patients,
Chaffee: and then regardless of if it's lecturers or if it's something else, either way, when you remove
plants, it goes away. And so that's the main thing. You know, do we have as hard of evidence as we
want to, you know, maybe maybe not, but it's enough for me to say, we'll look, this is something
that, you know, looks like it's a credible mechanism. And when we do it in practice, it works.
And so that's really all it comes down to. I mean, that that's the end of the day. What I'm worried
about is what is going to help my patient, and what is going to get them better, and what's going
to get their antibodies down, and get their thyroid functioning again. And so, removal of all
plants, including lectins, could be other things that they're reacting to too, certainly even
things like dairy, you know, that that trips off auto immunity as well. So there's likely other
things that are going on as well. But either way, you remove these things, the problem goes away,
and that's what I think is the most important part of this. Excellent. Bishop's deep learning.
Thank you for the super chat. For Richard and Anthony, what is the best way to gain muscle on the
carnival diet? Work out frequency, fat to protein ratio. Thanks.
So I'll just jump in very quickly, and just my general guide is just, you know, you work out
hard to get onto an appropriate lifting schedule. You consistently maintain that lifting schedule,
and you eat enough. So as far as frequency, sorry, fat to protein ratios, you're still in the same
thing, you're sitting, you know, high fat, it's also a high protein diet. You keep eating
till fatty meat stops tasting good. You try to do that a couple times a day, at least to make
sure your body's getting enough. And that's certainly for, you know, just the layman or, you know,
the athlete that's not trying to just perfectly sculpt their body, like, so rugby player,
sprinter or something like that. That's what worked for me. And, but, you know, Richard is definitely
the expert on this on how to actually really make a program here. So be interested to see what
he says. Yeah, look, don't overthink it. I think Anthony's hit the net on the head.
Protein, always consume protein with fat, every cell in the body is made of protein of fat,
and we need the fat with the protein. If you're looking to aim for any numbers,
aim for one gram of protein per pound of body weight, and that is a rough estimate. We need to
Chaffee: release 0.5 grams per pound, and 0.82 per pound in order to build muscle. So one gram per pound is
Chaffee: an ICZ number to remember. If you want to really get into the weeds, concentrate on eccentric
movements, train for no longer than an hour, 45 minutes to an hour, four sets ranging from
reps of 12 to 16. And again, on eccentric movements, if you are looking to benefit from the
M2 activation, consume training them all in, ideally fasted. This is one M2 activation. It takes
3.5 to 4 hours for M2 to reset. So again, it maybe 3.5 to 4 hours after that, 3.5 to
4 hours after that. And so on. And that way, you can still put in a 12 hour fast, if you wish
to do fast in, and this way, you're activated M2 four times, which is an optimal for the
building muscle. You don't have to do that every day, but that is maximal. And a lot of research
I'm doing recently in regards to building muscle and increasing bone strength and tendon strength.
It may be more beneficial to in fact train twice in one day, around 8 hours apart and
Chaffee: having the second day off. More to come on that, I'm still researching. I'm looking into this
Chaffee: injury guards to my building, my strength up in my legs, because as you guys know,
every Sunday started doing running and cycling, so I complete 180 from body building.
But there's a couple of tips there to jump on. So it should be plenty to get you started.
Brilliant. So when you're saying twice, you're working the same muscle group,
twice a day, 8 hours apart. Yeah. So one of the studies I've been looking at is, I can't remember
that the lady's name, but she is the world record holder for some 500 odd miles in the shortest
time, 100 mile. She's a scientist who's looked into muscle adaptation and bone and tendon adaptation
in regards to training frequency. So rather than training every day, which is what a lot of athletes do,
she's looked into training twice in one day, doing the same training split. So the same.
So if you were to train for one hour each day, for example, a train half an hour in the morning,
half an hour, sort of eight, six to eight hours apart and then have the second day off and this
Chaffee: seems to be building most adaptations. The science that I was looking into yesterday, as sad as
Chaffee: this sounds, this is what I was doing yesterday afternoon, when everyone else is watching TV and
Netflix and so on. I was looking at these research papers. It's incredible stuff. And it also showed
that the glycogen muscle glycogen was higher when trained low carb. So this was with athletes who
consumed in carb, but they would deplete glycogen and then they would refeed with carb
a hydropid. But it showed that the adaptations created in doing so increased their ability to store
more muscle glycogen, which goes against everything that we had told from the general standpoint of
training and glycogen storage. But yeah, it's probably a whole other podcast on that when we look
into the evidence, but it's incredible research. Yeah, and I'm going to flood my ultra-conditioning
program because I've been doing alternate day training for 15 years. And I think Anthony doesn't
know this, but I used to be an advanced person of training and I actually got somebody to the
Olympics, travelling for I. Nice. So it was better. I can answer some of these questions, but I
love to hear Richard. You know, I think it's not sad, but looking at research studies, I guess I do
a lot of time. Okay, you're not a loser. It's all right. It's okay. We love you, Mike. We love you.
Right. I was going to ask you. Okay, guys, one more thing, just in that same vein, I just saw a
excuse me. I just saw, you know, when there's old school body builders, it was like that was that
some of the NAM, some like that's like Mike and something. Anyway. Sorry. But almost certainly.
Yeah. And you just want those big ass dudes and he's in the sort of the Arnold era. And he was saying
that actually what you want to do, you wanted to just work out once. And you're saying like one set
to failure, that's all you needed to do. And then and then rest 72 hours before you do your next
Chaffee: work out session. And so you're not even, not even the same muscle group, but just the next set of
Chaffee: muscle groups. You want to give your body 72 hours to rest entirely. They want to do that. And if you
did two sets of something, then that was yes, you get more for it, but to hurt yourself on your
Chaffee: recovery and all that stuff. I don't know if he was doing carnivores or something like that,
Chaffee: a lot of them were doing steak and eggs back then and lots of steroids. But so I don't know what
combination here is that there's going to be a winner, but just what I wonder what your thoughts
are on that. Because I certainly in my own experience, I've always had better results in my strength,
physique, and my performance. If I work my muscle groups out twice a week, that's what I found
Chaffee: work best for me. And that's why I set up my workout routine around that. So I do the same
Chaffee: muscle group twice a week. And that's what I felt work best. But it's always interesting to hear
those thoughts. Yeah, I think we build when we recover. We're not building muscle when we are training.
So recovery is incredibly important. What I found was nothing worked for me on a seven day week.
So rather than training twice a week, I would train twice every eight days. So things seem to work
on an eight-day cycle. So I would never have set days for training. But I would alternate a muscle
and the reason for that is giving that rest in between. So you'd hit chest on on a
Monday, for example. And then I wouldn't train that till four days later. Legs sometimes took a
little bit longer. But again, that healing period is really important. I can imagine why
resting for 72 hours would work because you cause in a lot of damage. But then the issue with
going too heavy also is that when you're lifting too heavy, it does cause more damage.
This is why I moved away from the heavy weights. Always to failure. But eccentric movements
were really important for me because that time and attention was last in longer. And we're actually
stronger on eccentric movements rather than concentric. So that not only allowed me to build
muscle as in physique wise, but it helped build a lot of strength. And a lot of people don't know this.
But when I came away from the bodybuilding, I'm 20k like there. So I'm absolutely tiny compared to
what I was when I was bodybuilding. But when I came away from that, I was
with what I could lift, I would have been in the top 10 in the UK in powerlifting. And
that is between everyone which is the clean and dirty feds i.e. supplemented with anabolic
and not. And obviously I don't take anabolic. So I was in the top 10 or would have been in the top 10.
And that's what I was going to gravitate into. But I got pulled into the world of running and
cycling and training for duathlons and triathlons. So I complete one AD from bodybuilding. But
I do feel a lot thicker and healthier for doing so. And something you mentioned recently, Anthony,
is that, you know, you and I don't train an awful lot yet. In a vest, I'm still big for a runner.
Chaffee: I've still got the delts and the lats. I'm small, but I've still I'm still holding the muscle
Chaffee: without even training. And my brother mentioned to me recently that I still look fairly
shapely for someone that doesn't lift any weights and hasn't lifted a weight in a year and a half.
And that just adds weight to the fact that living the carnival lifestyle muscles precious,
the body doesn't want to waste it. And when you do retain and I believe it's more to do with
volume in the muscle than actually muscle size itself. Because when I've tested even though I've
lost 20k, my dry protein has only come down by 2k. So my dry, yes, I've lost muscle because I'm
not using it. But that 2k in a year and a half throughout my whole body doesn't sound like an awful
lot. And when we put that fluid back into the muscle, I eat through stimulation training.
I believe that I could get back to a physique that I was once in, incredibly quickly. Maybe
a test for a future to see how quickly we could do that. But muscles precious isn't there.
So we don't lose it as much as people think. I think a days off are under estimated because
they're not days off. They're recovery days. The recovery days are logical. Response are training
response to what you've done is really important. And it's a big hot topic at the moment in
Premier League soccer because there's teams playing you know every three days. And we're seeing
lots and lots of injuries. So even prime athletes and prime sports people need those recovery days.
So we get to this one so long after you've posted. But thank you very much for the super chat.
Someone I know was diagnosed with glioblastoma stage four about nine months ago.
Would a standard kind of a diet be fine to try or should it modified because of the cancer?
I have seen some of your videos with survivors.
Chaffee: Well, no, it doesn't need to be modified in in, you know, really an insignificant way.
Chaffee: The only modification you need to make is in respect to the GKI. So glico's ketone index.
Chaffee: I think that's your sort of your your hallmark here. So normally I don't think that you need to
fast for any periods of time, you know, apart from just what your body's telling you to do
on a carnivore diet. There's there's two schools of thoughts in the ketogenic metabolic therapy
approach to to cancer with carnivore diet. You need to keep your GKI down. There are a lot of
Chaffee: studies in animals and humans that show that restricting eating. So not eating as much as your
Chaffee: body's necessarily demanding and and having your blood sugar lower and your ketones higher.
Chaffee: And you should that ratio is it called GKI, glucose ketone index. You keep that under two.
Chaffee: That's a therapeutic range. You keep that under one. That's even better.
That that has shown to be very beneficial for cancer outcomes and survival and prolonging survival.
At least in the the studies that we have so far in GBM, which are limited. And with a lot of
studies and a lot of different cancers, but specifically GBM, it's a bit limited. There are smaller
trials anywhere from 15 to 30 people. There is a randomized control trial with about 20 patients
and they have shown efficacy and benefit certainly certainly being safe and in some of these
Chaffee: showing benefit people living far past where they would have otherwise actually showing
Chaffee: recession and receding GBM even on like fourth line treatment. But they go through the surgery,
Chaffee: chemo radiation, it recurs and they have the surgery, some more chemo, last bit of radiation.
Chaffee: Now it's not safe and they have a recurrence, they have a re-resection, a re-re-resection. And they
Chaffee: can't really, they're sort of capped out on radiation and then they have to go through like
Chaffee: you know, different sorts of end stage chemo such as a vastin, which is really hard on the
body, makes a brain very friable. It's it for surgeries after that. You can't operate on on a
patient's brain after they've been on a vastin because the tissue just falls apart and they just
bleed and bleed and bleed and bleed and you can't stop it. So that's sort of a last line approach
and then they people have a vastin and they're they're not going they're not being helped and they
say well you know you could just stop eating carbs or you could you know and then they
Chaffee: they do that. So c-design line does that in America right now and they published a large case
Chaffee: series without 15 patients. Most of them were brain tumors not all of them were GBMs but they
showed that the brain tumors and the GBMs even responded extremely well even though this was
a fourth line defense against against the GBM in that case series they survived for years and
Chaffee: years passed where where they were they were they were dying they were on their way out and then they
Chaffee: went on keep on a on a ketogenic metabolic therapy and all of a sudden they just kept going
and on MRI tumors were shrinking and there's multiple case series with your 15 16 patients
there's another case series published out of Phoenix showed the same thing you showed these
like big tumors and they're just shrinking down so you know you do a ketogenic carnivore diet
and you and you get your GKI down below two from much of the time below one if you can you do
that with a combination of ketogenic carnivore diet and fasting if you need it. If you need to have
Chaffee: periods of fasting you go for it to bring that that GKI down and then there are you have to
Chaffee: refeed on other days because you don't want to lose too much weight you know this is good you can't
let it you know make it so you're too weak to defend yourself and to maintain your body
after about eight to well so GBM in particular is a bit nasty because cancer is run on glucose
Chaffee: and glutamine and GBM's run on about 75% glutamine and so it they do much better if you get
Chaffee: an onto an agent that disrupts glutamine there are chemotherapy agents one is called Don DON I don't
have the chemical name a mind at the set at the moment but that's been used in animal models with
GBM when you put people like ketogenic diet and Don they they all the mice survived and I was
with the work of Professor Thomas C. free out of Austin College and and they showed that on imaging
Chaffee: and then on bio or on histology when they sacrificed the rats that the tumors just died they just
Chaffee: gone away and just died cells and just died because you you've taken away their energy sources
Chaffee: and they just shut down and died so that may or may not be something that your doctor can help you
Chaffee: with that may or may not be something you can get your hands on because of depending on how your
your doctor and your oncologist feels about those sorts of agents but there are chemotherapy
agents that do that like Don DON is like chemotherapy agent but it's not necessarily life
is for GBM so it would be off label and you don't know if your oncologist would be okay with that
um when you fast between eight and fourteen days you make glue to mean first of all you also make
Chaffee: glue coes but you're just keeping it down at lower levels and because these cancer cells have
Chaffee: such a high metabolic demand and they're inefficient at making energy they really require a lot of
Chaffee: this stuff and they don't have a sufficient amount the cells die off and so that's what you want to
Chaffee: just want to start these suckers out glue to mean is in meat it's also in plant proteins you're
not going to avoid it by you know going vegan or anything like that um glue to mean is denatured
by cooking so if you're really that worried about it you can cook your meat or you can limit your meat
and you can have periods of fasting now we'll get rid of incoming glucose and incoming glue to me
and um then you want to if you need to if you need to fast to get your GKI down that can be a
helpful adjunct there are people that that you know finds success in this and according to
Chaffee: Dr. C Fried when you get to about sort of eight to fourteen day fasting range this actually can
can disrupt your your own glue to mean metabolism and so that can actually have favorable results
for a long a sort of longer fast and you have to do that carefully to do that under medical
Chaffee: supervision to be careful about refeeding and how you start eating again after you have to
you do a long fast like that where else you can you can hurt yourself but those are some things
Chaffee: that people are currently trialing and and using in their in their own
cases or in their patient populations for different people that are treating this sort of thing
Chaffee: and then the other side of it is the paleo metacena side and they've been treating cancer's
Chaffee: in GBMs for 15 years with this with a pkd diet of the paleolithic ketogenic diet which is
what gave memory eating during the ice ages which is meat that's it right so there there was
absolutely nothing besides fatty meat but you limit the amount that you're eating and so you
Chaffee: have to use organs so you eat organs because they're more nutrient dense you're not getting in as
Chaffee: much food so you need more nutrient dense food and so you're limiting the amount that you're eating
all the studies show in animals and humans that restricted you know calorie restricted I hate that
but calorie restricted eating calorie restricted ketogenic diets are are the most beneficial
to survival and longevity and improved outcomes so that's something that's what they do so they don't
Chaffee: do fasting they don't want you to do fasting but they definitely do restrict so you're restricting
Chaffee: what you're taking in you're eating more high density food and nutrition and and you're a very,
Chaffee: very dull than with that so those are those are some caveats but really what you do you do
Chaffee: exactly same thing you very high fat and I mean like two grams of fat to one gram of protein and
you really get your your key tones up and you try to keep your GKI down below two and below one
as much as possible on average for the week and that's what you have different days you might be
fasting you may need to fast you may need to limit what you eat and to get your GKI down but that's
what I would do and I would adjust what your eat I would still eat the same thing fatty meat and some
organs but I would do it in such a way that you can keep your GKI down most of the time and if you
have to limit what you're eating or fast for periods of time and you're losing more weight than
than you should you're going to have to have refeed days you're going to have to you know feed the
body and make sure you're getting enough nutrition for your body so you can support yourself in this
and then you should have these periods of refeed days and then you go back to it all right
your body can do that you know we're more than capable and adapted to deal with
famines and lean times and so your body can do that you just be very careful with it make sure
you're not losing too much weight so that it affects your health negatively and you have these
refeed days but you have these these stretches in these periods where you are significantly
limiting the amount of available energy for these cancer cells and if you can hit it with
something like dawn or some of these other agents that disrupt glue to me that you can you can
look into there's a lot of you know literature on that and that's something that is
is in keeping you know safe for you to do with your current plan you know obviously you need to
talk to your doctor about these sorts of things you know then you do that that's that's
Chaffee: ketogenic diet and every now and then you hit it with like strong words like you're just going to
Chaffee: fast for a week and you're going to hit it with dawn and you're going to do these sorts of things
where you really aggressively go at it so it's constant pressure of just energy depth it's constant
energy deprivation for these cancer cells and then every now and then you hit it with you know
these periods of fasting and and you know the glue to me disruptors and then the other
you know flying the ointment there is dootarium which is this is seems to be a very interesting
line of research that's now growing but there's a guy named Dr. Gavor Somlai who's actually
Chaffee: published multiple papers on this and how having lower amounts of dootarium in the body which is
Chaffee: heavy hydrogens is hydrogen with an extra neutron on it or with a neutron added onto it that this
actually can be very damaging to the mitochondria damaging to the cells and if you have lower
levels of dootarium this can actually disrupt and damage cancer cells more and can actually help
in that treatment also which is how he came to ketogenic carnivores or diets because that's the
diet that naturally lowers your dootarium more than anything else so I have a couple of interviews
with him on my channel and I have another interview with Dr. Lazlo Boros on the subject and he's
Chaffee: you know a professor of medicine at UCLA and ran a biochemistry lab there and did a lot of research
Chaffee: on dootarium and he actually didn't believe that either side was crazy and Gavor found him they're
both from Hungary originally but hey once you do this research and he's like oh my god this is crazy
and he's just like all right well look it's $25,000 a cell line if you want to do something like that
yeah let's do three okay these guys are serious so we ran the test and he went holy shit these
guys run this something like this is this is actually real and so now he just went full on head
long into the research and now he teaches that he teaches deutonomics which is a deuterium based
biochemistry and how this affects diseases so that's another thing you can sort of look into probably
too long of a topic to get into here but you know if you look up those interviews
with Lazlo Boros and Gavor some like on my channel I just did a more recent one it has more new
published data showing the benefits of this so something to think about you know if I had something
like GBM or family member did I would just throw the kitchen sink at it and I would just be extremely
Chaffee: aggressive with this stuff because GBMs don't mess around they are likely one of the most aggressive
Chaffee: cancers that exist certainly the most aggressive primary brain tumor and so it's it's not something
you want to play around with I would be exquisitely strict if I had something like this and I would
just be borderline neurotic about my numbers and making sure that everything was just
exactly the way I wanted it at least at first until you got into a pattern you figured out how you could
Chaffee: you know how you could live with this sort of thing and and even down the road if you're seeing
Chaffee: like hey there's nothing here there's nothing here my MRIs are all clean you know it can all
it could spark back up you know it's that you have to be you have to take this very seriously this
is a they life long issue and so even while there are long-term survivors you know nine
Chaffee: years plus that have been doing this and there's others that I've been talking people I'm
Chaffee: talking to they're like oh yeah there's this random guy been 23 years doing ketogenic diet with
Chaffee: the GBM and just but just no one knows who the hell he is he's just he's just off living his life you
know and so I'm still trying to track that guy down but you know when you start slipping off of this
this can come back you know uh uh uh friend of mine Pablo Kelly is one of these long-term survivors
with GBM and he had a bit of a relapse because he started saying well I should be able to have
Chaffee: ice cream with my kids I should be able to eat this and I should be able to do that and always
Chaffee: starting to have a more symptoms and I went in and got checked out and I'll ship this things growing
again and so it just realizing no I can't think like that that's stupid I should be able to should
doesn't come into it I can't and so if I want to be here for my kids and my wife I can't and so he's
now back on back on the straight and narrow so um that's that's where you have to think of too
Chaffee: is that this isn't this GBM isn't necessarily something that's gonna go away and stay away
it's something that that if it goes away you have to keep it away by doing this so this is a
time commitment this is a a lifestyle this is just this is just how you live your life now it's
no different than any you know than any three of us here and how we're living our life as well
Chaffee: it's just you need to be just you know very switched on and you know there's less room for error
Chaffee: you know you can't have these cheat days oh well whatever I mean you can but it's going to be detrimental
and so you know that's what I would do I would just be very very dialed in and strict with it
yeah and I think that that's a download just to when people talk about type two diabetes for
instance and we talk about reversing it and I get in online arguments where they say we've not
cured it I'll say no you've reversed the symptoms if they go back to the wrong way of eating
then you you're opening the door back to those symptoms so it's sort of very similar to that obviously
more dramatic brilliant answer there I think it's Daiso Oxo Norl Lucy and if people want to
look it up when it's six at the beginning and five in the middle of that so anyway I did
hold still in the comments at earlier I was it yeah it isn't comments yeah
Norl Norl thank you very much for nine nine nine nine that's of course I think I've done
where that super chat's gone to but thank you very much very generous super chat I think this
to doctrine to the chafee for $100 is meat of the young calf not veal nutritionally okay to have
Chaffee: as a mature beef meat it's the meat of the calf what nutritionally okay yeah well so it's
Chaffee: like an Australia you know it's like they they it's basically just just the next step past the
old it'd be like yearlings you know so like in America it's usually like 18 months to to 24 months
they would get they would slaughter the steers but in Australia they do a lot of yearlings
Chaffee: which we're the bugs maybe because they're like smaller stakes and like where the hell's my big
Chaffee: ass robot like and you know it's a smaller so I look I think it's I think it's very similar
but you know it's something that that I would like to do some some test with or talk to some
some ranchers about doing some tests the thing is is that we don't I think when you when you
have an animal out just eating grass it's sort of building up you know nutrient density and you can
taste that in the meat I've had different age meat and it just tastes more beef you just more beef
flavor those flavors are the nutrients and then you have these sort of very bland sort of
am I really getting anything out of this um so you know you have these regenerally raised grass
Chaffee: fed and finished cows and it's just like there's much more flavor to it there's much more of this
Chaffee: nice rich sort of there's actually an aroma that's very different on grass fed meat and
especially older ones and and and you know it the taste is different it's just it's much more
potent it's not gaming but it's just more beef flavor if that makes sense and um and we can see
Chaffee: in regenerally raised grass fed and finished cows in any case that at least some of the ranchers
Chaffee: that I've spoken to that they've sent their meat off and got it tested and it's like four or five
times a number of micro nutrients so you know it does objectively have more nutrients in there and
I think that probably is reflected in the taste from similar age cows now I've had older
cows I've grass fed their entire life I would imagine that they have more nutrient density because
Chaffee: they have 10 times a beef flavor of even these these other younger regenerally raised grass fed
and finished cows they don't they aren't commercially viable at the moment probably that's
good for all of us who know about this because they're way better and you can generally get them
Chaffee: for cheaper and you don't have to fight for them but they're freaking delicious and so if you can
Chaffee: go to a rancher and just say hey I want your oldest cow that's only ever eaten grass generally
they they they just grind them up for hamburger because we were like oh they're too tough I think
you're sacrificing um flavor for texture and the texture is not all that different it's actually
excellent the gristle is as hard as almost like gets me tendons are like whale bone it's just like
oh god but they're usually just to pluck out and just toss them you're not chewing on them and
you know it's like meat gum for two hours you know you just do just chuck it you get rid of it
Chaffee: and so I would imagine that those are more nutrient dense the older that you get if it's eating
if it's eating a better die however I don't know anyone who sent that off because they're they're
they're not I don't know people that haven't older heard they're selling that to a bespoke market
and they're sending this off say oh look at this we have 10 times 20 times the amount of nutrients
I think if you're eating younger younger meat it's not going to be as nutrient dense it's still
going to be fantastic it's still going to be absolutely you know you know hands down better than
then the other options available certainly the other plant based options available and so
Chaffee: if that's what you have available that's what you have that's available to you I think that's fine and
you know but I would expect that if we were to test older older cows that you get more nutrient
density out of it yes great great this is a really nice question from Tom Dr. Chafi could you
clarify what you mean by carnival being a fasting mimicking diet in my opinion after you eat a
kilo of meat you're definitely not in a fasting state no I 100% agree with you and
it's it's not a fasting mimicking diet a fasting mimics a carnivore diet fasting mimics
your our our primary metabolic state the metabolic state that we are in when we eat our our
Chaffee: main source of nutrition which is meat it hasn't always been meat since the dawn of humanity
so yeah when you eat a kilo of meat you are definitely not fasting and so that's the thing these
these were this was misnamed a fasting metabolism and a fed metabolism and that goes back decades
and I think the only reason we did that was because by the time we were able to look at our
biochemistry at a molecular level everyone was eating carbohydrates and I said oh when you eat it
looks like this and when you don't eat it looks they're completely different failing to recognize
that if anything else except carbohydrates it also looks like you you aren't eating at all speaking
my niece who's now you know pre-med in America and she's taking biochemistry this year or
maybe she's even yeah she's taking it this year she was saying they don't they don't even call it
fed-say and fasting state anymore it's a carbohydrate metabolism and a non carbohydrate metabolism
which is much more accurate you know that the fed-say and the fasting state that's a you know
you know that's a value judgment you know just save it like all this is the only thing we're
Chaffee: eating over here so yeah it is just a carbohydrate metabolism versus a non carbohydrate metabolism
and I think that the non carbohydrate metabolism is our primary metabolic state and that
fasting mimics it I think that a lot of the benefit you get from fasting largely comes from just
not eating the wrong thing and from being in the correct metabolic state you know this is something
Chaffee: with insulin insulin has you know over a hundred different mechanisms in the body one of them
Chaffee: is to suppress and decrease a top of G and the turnover that organelles in the cells that are older
Chaffee: and damage so it's when people talk all you have to fast for five days every now and then
Chaffee: and all that sort of stuff to get the all top of G you only have to get 72 hours and 84 hours so
116 hours all that sort of stuff no you just don't you just need to stop eating carbohydrates you
need your insulin down that happens all the time so at the moment I believe that Steven
Richard and myself have been on the equivalent of you know six thousand four hundred and eighty
two day fast you know because we just we just our insulin has been low this whole time
Chaffee: obviously not that long but you know a long ass time it's certainly longer than 72 hours so
the top of G has been long accounted for in our in our systems so it's really just comes
down to being the correct metabolic state 70% of all animal species are carnivores they're all eating
protein if that they're all in this so-called ketogenic starvation state right and animals that eat
Chaffee: fiber break down that fiber into saturated fat and protein so they're not getting carbohydrates either
Chaffee: they're in the non-carbohydrate driven metabolism also so this isn't a shock to your system
Chaffee: this is out care what rape heat tells you in your nightmares like it's just it's not the case
Chaffee: that this is shock to the system or stress to the system this is the normal metabolic state
of human beings and nearly every animal on earth and so the idea that this is stressing us and
freaking us out and this is bad makes absolutely no sense biologically and is wrong anyway
people can look at Richard and I's I appreciate my video on the subject here is ketosis harmful
short answer no and we go through like just hours of data and literature on that and to really
sort of hammer that point home brilliant Anthony thank you so much for your time
Richard just private message me and I didn't realize we'd show over an hour but quite considerable
testing so I've been trying to sort of exaggerate with questions but I'm going to say two hours
just fine yeah you're right to hours yeah yeah yeah oh fantastic yeah if I'll keep my trap
that then I was just continue yeah well I know that's all good yeah I thought it was two hours
but then you know Richard's on who you know so it's good can I just jump if we're staying on can I just
jump into ad to that as well so that yeah I agree completely what Anthony's just said it's
just by being in a ketogenic state which is what we are in this is our metabolic state even
when we live in a carnival lifestyle the benefits that we see of fast in which are autopsy
autopsy mightophyg brown fat activation lipolysis and insulin sensitivity there are all exhibited
to live in the lifestyle regardless of whether we are in a state of a m pk or m to activation
we are benefit it it's like a sea sort of fact one predominance with both are always playing that
fact but it those benefits are there regardless of being fasted or not and this is why you
just live in the lifestyle as that benefit and we don't need to force fast in and I would also
argue that maybe potentially extended fast in doesn't benefit a lot of a lot of women
the more that I'm working with I'm seem to see that then being in more of I don't want to use
the term fed state after Anthony's just said that but maybe he did two to three meals a day
may help a little bit better in regards to but some people do thrive but it does cause
homeowner shoes who some and what I would argue is that if we look at our our evolutionary period
the men of the tribe would be out hunting in for hours and days well the females were
were there prepping food or maybe eating before the hunt has returned and therefore
their state of prolonged fasting was going to be a lot lower than that of the men and this is
seems to be a big big problem within the female community that I work with that they're pushing
for the extended fast and it leads to lethargy skin conditions hair loss and it's to do with
not eating enough and we're told by many of the influences in the community that is because of
lack of carbohydrate to create thyroid hormone but it's not to do with carbohydrates it's to do with
not eating enough and that comes down to animal proteins and fat we need animal proteins and we need
fat especially for the production of hormones so don't neglect the nutrition eat when you
hungry you know if you're not hungry don't eat but be mindful that we do need that protein
we do need that fat and the benefits are there regardless of fasting or not. Yeah I'm still struggling
to see what part of carbohydrates help us make thyroid hormone but anyway so here's a nice question
why blood pressure went down significantly going from coffee to de-caf coffee any benefits to
Chaffee: quitting the de-caf and I did worthy of quitting. Well I mean that's that's interesting your blood pressure
Chaffee: went down I wonder what type of de-caf you switch to you know there are things called
Chaffee: rancid oils in coffee that when you heat it over 160 degrees they come out and on our known to
kickoff hypertension and so generally like filters like filter coffee will actually take that out so
things like the spressos or like the bottom press coffee those are the French press coffees they
won't filter that out and you sort of see this oily sort of sheen on the surface and those
can definitely jack up your blood pressure and this is what cold brew coffee was for us will
be the the heart healthy blood pressure coffee back in the 60s and 70s and things like that
sort of had a resurgence in with Starbucks and things like that more recently but I would wonder what
what you're switching to you know caffeine can certainly affect that but it's generally the generally
things that affect your blood pressure the most or those rancid oils so I I wonder if you
went to this sort of de-caf is now filtered as opposed to more of spressos sort of things from coffee
Chaffee: I don't know but as to benefits from drop dropping decaf absolutely so caffeine is just one of
Chaffee: 150,000 or so chemicals that are in coffee and there's all sorts of these different nasty chemicals
Chaffee: that are not good for you when you when you taste something bitter your brain is warning you about
Chaffee: something saying hey why don't you not eat this you know we used out there just putting things in your
mouth and you're like oh that tastes good I'll eat it that tastes better no I'm not going to eat it
that's the natural instinct in nature until you have someone telling you no that bitter taste is good
oh that's good yes you wanted to taste horrible you want to hate your life you know like well
that doesn't make sense you know but we we convince ourselves of this so if you have that bitter taste
your brains your brains telling you there's something there that you don't want so coffee's very bitter
Chaffee: and you know it's it's a being being as a seed as he's a plant's baby that's where you
generally find the highest concentration of toxins is in the seeds which because the plant's
trying to protect that most because that's the next generation so yes I think there's absolutely
Chaffee: a lot of benefit to dropping decaf in fact I generally the rather see people like switch to caffeine
pills and and and skip the whole decaf side of the coffee that the caffeine although it's a
neurotoxin developed as an insecticide to fry the brains of insects that are trying to eat that
plant I still think that getting rid of those 150,000 other things probably even more beneficial
than just getting rid of the caffeine if you take a caffeine pill in the morning and that can
Chaffee: give you the bump that you want then you can sort of do that and then when you're so far off that
Chaffee: and come off eventually you'll have better energy anyway but you'll you'll have less you know
Chaffee: hornets and aches and muscle pains and joint pains and other sorts of problems but um you're
already off the caffeine so don't worry about that don't start the caffeine pill now because you're
already off the caffeine I would just drop it completely and just switch back switch over to water
I think you'll feel a lot better overall and have a lot less information in your body
great okay we've got Lucy here who's been kind of off for seven months but she's having
gut issues blood tests are all clear try lyandia but end up at the toilet between two to three hours
of eating any suggestions for helping my gut microbiome well the thing is is that it well it
could be your microbiome but you do you have to always consider all the other things you know are
Chaffee: are you strict lyandizers strict meat and water do you still have any sort of artificial
Chaffee: sweeteners you have even electrolytes that have stevia or or a leprethar tall things like that
Chaffee: are you having coffee are you having tea do you take magnesium supplements do you take met
Chaffee: foreman or other sorts of diabetes medications these can all cause loose stools or at least
you know have mild laxative effects and now you don't have much of fiber in your body they can move
things through more quickly and then obviously if your your body has a limited capacity to absorb
fat and so if you're eating far past your body's capacity to absorb fat it's going to go out and
has to come out just one way one direction so that is um that is something that can cause
Chaffee: loose stools as well so you know especially we're talking about the timing of your of your meals
Chaffee: there you're eating a lyandia you're just eating meat and then you're like oh nope this has to go
that could suggest that maybe you're ingesting something that's being this long if you're having
anything else if you're not as assume you're not that's about the time you'd see that this is
sort of coming through your system and digestion and the fat that didn't get digested and it was
or is now coming out and causing problems it's not necessarily a problem it's not necessarily
that your sick or there's an issue it's just inconvenient and so that could be an issue as well
so just maybe look at that and see if you can adjust your fat and if that changes anything if you can
Chaffee: if you're very very constipated and you get overflow diarrhea where you have blocked up and you
Chaffee: can get liquid stools pushing around the harder stools and get liquid diarrhea pretty much all the
Chaffee: time and then every now and then you get like this boulder that comes out this sounds more like the
other side that you're having more fat you eat that fat your body just can't absorb it all so it
Chaffee: just goes out especially people with without a gallbladder may run into that as well because
Chaffee: they're just not going to be able to absorb as much fat in one go so maybe play with that if you
try these sorts of things you've eliminated out everything else you've played around with the fat
levels and you do still think this is a microbiome issue seven months carnivore though it's
most people's microbiomes are radically different at that point but all things if you
Chaffee: exclude everything else and you need and you're thinking maybe this is a microbiome issue
fermented yogurt so fermented dairy you get that live culture yogurt small amounts no carbs
if you can some of them have a little bit but try to get like the the lowest carbs you can put
that on a piece of meat chew it up together swallow it together whole you can work those bacteria
sort of into the bowl of some food and that will hopefully get it past your stomach acid and
burn top and get it off down into your into your colon and you just do that for a week or two
but that should recede your bacteria and then just the food that you're eating will support the
bacteria but you know if you think it's a microbiome issue you can always send off for a microbiome
test seven months on a carnivore diet most people actually have pretty stellar microbiomes at that
point so I would from what you're telling me there it seems sounds more like excess fat to me but
maybe you guys have a thought on that yeah I agree yeah I think minced meat minced beef can
cause an issue again it's the fat issue it's got to be predominantly a fat problem especially
with that sort of movement time the quality of meat I would question whether you're consuming
aged meats because aged meats obviously by definition become rancid so eat you eat fresh
you know if you do buy in bulk freeze it as soon as you can and try to eat it
you know as you're taking it out of the freezer but fresh is always best but minced meat I've
I've noticed as caused a number of issues with clients of mine I'm a big fan of minced meat
this incredibly cheap incredibly new drink dense I love pan fry in it and I'll pour the fat over
and I think this incredible sometimes I'll fry an egg and check that on top as well but
it does cause issues with some people so I think honestly he's hit the nail on the head I think it's
Chaffee: predominantly a fat issue and I'm sorry oh I'm just gonna say too and that rendered fat seems
Chaffee: to be go through people quicker yeah so yeah so then when you're doing like ground beef just
Chaffee: like Richard said a lot of that will render out and and that can be it just it just goes through
quicker more quickly if you have it like the solid fat tissue and you chew it up obviously and
but then your your body has to sort of work on these things with your asses and digest events
on takes longer to extract that fat gives your body a chance to respond with life pace and
bile to get out there and actually break the stuff down and absorb it so it's more conducive
to adequate digestion and absorption and so what some people find even when they're lowering
Chaffee: down the amount of fat and they're still having issues with it or the earlier there's still
Chaffee: you a very reasonable amount of low amount of fat and none of these other issues that we touched on
Chaffee: that when they start eating solid fat as most rendered fat or they even I the most extreme
Chaffee: I've seen people have to do is they cut off the fat before cooking and eat it uncooked and then
cooked the rest of the meat separately and that that seemed to work for a number of people
one one thing that I've seen as a growing trend is that people think that they have to just
take on so much salt that they actually dump a ton of salt and rock salt in their in their
water so it's just I mean they're just drinking like you know water from the dead sea or something
like that and it's just like it's just a ton of salt that isn't osmotic that work as an osmotic
laxated that pull out water from your body and just flush your bowel so if you want to do a bowel
flush that's how you do it um I don't recommend it but um but that was that was one thing
Chaffee: I was I was talking to uh I thought you want to multiple people you're talking about what are you
Chaffee: eating what are you doing this this and this and it sounded like the only thing they were doing
was meat and water and then it was just sort of at the animals like oh well I'm also putting in a
lot lot of salt into my water and it's just like okay well that can absolutely do it so just
just try to think of all these things as well and uh but those are some some points that can help
and what fats are you cooking and also uh I don't cook in any fat anymore I just use the fat
from the meat that I cook in but I know within our community um you know we're heavily biased towards
adding uh butter, tallow, lard, or ghee but you don't need to add any fat when cooking um
possibly another lever to polarity take a fat when cooking out if you are using salt.
Cool that's great um just for those that are wondering why I'm not answering many questions
it's because later on if you want to ask questions of myself or Richard we have our live
Chaffee: in five hours times seven p.m. in the UK we do another hour and a half an hour on YouTube and then
30 minutes on another platform which rhymes with apple crumble so um yes you can check us out there
Lucy from England by the way Richard's from Wales you know so I'm in England he's he's
he's in Wales that's the United Kingdom anyway uh or if you're from England and you're looking
for beef jerky I have found this if you really go from the guy that does the mason survival
protocol because we we always get all these Americans we've all these fantastic things and uh
okay we've like behind oh sorry really it's yeah it's crazy yeah it's crazy but like we're going
to grow the kind of movement away from America and everywhere else so hello from England I have
a question if we cannot take into much fact due to our bodies only taking what we need
how does PSMF which is protein sparing modified fasting work so well for people just curious
Chaffee: that's struggling with white oh look you can starve yourself and you're smaller dress size
Chaffee: everybody knows that but it doesn't mean that it's it's the most beneficial thing for your body
Chaffee: doesn't mean it's the healthiest thing it doesn't mean it's the thing that uh is going to be conducive
Chaffee: to a a healthy strong metabolism there's the the um the Minnesota starvation trial that
doesn't in world war two they show that you put people on just basically you know um concentration
camera actions and yeah you'll lose weight to a two a point and then it'll level off and it'll
plateau and um and then and then that that slows down and just sort of is able to maintain on extremely
low intake uh that's your metabolism is slowing down and so you know that's not necessarily what
you want if it was just calories and calories out then uh some of these people would would have
ceased to exist because it would have lost they would have had to have lost more weight than they
started with so you know the modified um protein sparing uh fasting um so that's just basically eating
like a keto carnivore diet but just super high protein and like next to no fat and the idea
there is that well you have you have fat availability body can use that I don't I don't tend to
agree with that our our body is making bile for a reason I don't think your body does that by mistake
I don't think that it's just an accident your body is spending a lot of energy and resources
to make bile to absorb fat that it doesn't even want um I don't I just don't think that that
makes sense at first principle first principles and fundamental physiological paces
Chaffee: bile is expensive is an expensive resource and it costs a lot for our body to make it so you know
it doesn't just do that for no reason and since it's a limited resource I think our body is very
specific okay we need this amount right your body knows that it has fat there you know and it's saying
hey we want more that isn't just a calorie source that is a set and grouping of essential nutrients
or essential fatty acids you have to have you can get very sick or you can die there essential
fat soluble nutrients you have to have you can get sick and you can die so this is this is not
Chaffee: something that you can just say yeah yeah it's fine um do you have all the fat soluble vitamins in
Chaffee: your adipose tissue do you have all the omega 3s and dHA and EPA just stored there probably not you
know you have you have excess energy stored there it's not necessarily in the form of the fatty
essential fatty acids and fat soluble vitamins that you actually require so I don't really buy
into that and you know if people if people want to do that and they feel that that's helpful to
them and they can but I think that you run the risk of actually lowering your metabolism and just
you go into the zioo diets where you drop your metabolism and you lose weight for a while and
Chaffee: this sort of plateau is off and you sort of feel miserable and you're not really having you know enjoying
Chaffee: this you say okay I'm going to go back to what I was doing before or maybe eating more fat and then
you you balloon up and you put on weight oh my god I think it really scared of eating anyway any other
Chaffee: way because you put on weight well of course you're putting on weight because you're telling your
Chaffee: body you're in a famine and that you don't have enough nutrients and you're not able to get what
your body requires and so your metabolism has to slow down and as it slowed down it stays down
and then when you start eating more you put on weight because you're by saying nope we need to store
this now the studies with the biggest loser show where they they you know they're just the same thing
don't need anything to stick a celery a week and then just work your ass off and they just
destroy their meat they lost weight but they destroyed their metabolism and they tested them six years
Chaffee: later their metabolism had never recovered so you know that's not that's not great right so that's
Chaffee: what you want to do if you want to you want to encourage your metabolism you want to encourage your
body and say hey look we're not in a famine whatever you tell me I'm giving it to you right if you're
eating carbs you're eating lectins you're eating others sorts of things in a fear with insulin
leptin and and and growing you're going to overeat if you're eating just meat that doesn't happen
and so your body will tell you how much it wants you don't have to micromanage it you don't have to
guess your body will do it for you you just take in what your body is asking you for and I think
that includes that the other concern and it's a real concern is that if you're just on a
carnivore diet or you know a heavily animal-based ketogenic diet and it's very low that or know
that where your back was coming from it's coming from protein only and when you're only driving
energy from protein that can actually be dangerous and so you get what's called you look it out
called you know like rabbit starvation and protein poisoning and it's not good it's not good for you
you do need you do need to get your energy from other sources aside protein as well
and and that and obviously if you're not eating plants and carbs you're getting that from that
you could do it from from car but I wouldn't I would I would get it from the vet also if you're
going to lose weight why are you not eating fat you know which it was very calorie dense
oh you already have that okay what are you putting in your mouth you're putting in things and
you put it on a scale it has weight so you're eating things right so if you're going to get the
same amount of calories why wouldn't you eat the calories the 2000 calories at way less
Chaffee: right one might what do I mean by that that has nine calories per gram and so we think well
Chaffee: guys all that calories and you could store those as fat oh don't eat that right and then there's one
gram per you know of four calories per one gram of carbs and amino acids however when you're
using protein as energy it actually drops down to about 3.4 calories per gram so in real terms
if you're talking about taking in calories from from meat and you're just eating the protein
side of things and you're not eating the fat side of things you will have to take in more
grams of meat of protein in order to get the same amount of calories so you have to take in more
Chaffee: weight you will be weighing more right and you know and calories in calorie are really bad
Chaffee: model anyway because most of protein gets used as as building blocks in any case and carbohydrates
Chaffee: affect a lot of hormones and then there's a lot of fatty acids that you used as as building blocks
Chaffee: as well not all that's used as energy but in any case if you if you flip that equation around
Chaffee: the calories don't weigh anything it doesn't matter what the calories are if you have a glass of
Chaffee: ice water you have a glass of of steaming hot water the steaming hot water has a lot more calories
than the ice water they weigh the same effing thing right it's not the calories don't weigh anything
it's heat energy grams weigh something that's the only part of that equation that weighs anything
is the grams so you flip that equation around and now you're seeing one gram of fat for nine calories
but you're seeing three grams of protein per nine calories so you have to eat three times as much
protein in order to get two thousand calories if that's what your body requires that day right
Chaffee: so why would you do that you're you're putting on three times the amount of weight so you can
Chaffee: starve yourself and you can do all the other sorts of things but I think that they're not the
best way you can do it I don't think that it's you have has your long term health intentions
best in check if you just eat the way you're designed to eat your body's telling you how to do that
Chaffee: your body's going you're going to lose weight this is not a race you know you're not on a
Chaffee: game show you're not trying to you know it's not the biggest loser not trying to lose weight
Chaffee: faster than everybody else you're trying to be as healthy as you possibly can and part of that is
going to be returning to a healthy body body fat percentage it will happen but the thing is is it
you need to be healthy first that's a primary motivation objective and it all of this is being as healthy
as you possibly can and then the weight and musculature and all these other things they're all secondary
they do come right but they are of secondary importance I think you do this the right way you do this
in a as healthy a way as possible first and foremost without without you know you don't have to
rush it will happen haste makes waste the you know the slowest steady wins the race all these
sorts of things these things have been around for thousands of years for reason you know do it the right
and you will get to where you want to go faster and better shape and better form then if you
if you try to do these other sorts of shortcuts yeah and there's a phrase called leave them one
team more so doctor and me chafy we've come to the end and we're going to leave them one team more
well I thought we'd go out on a high I thought that was great Richard what did you think
did you think that was brother good your mood you're muted buddy nobody wants to listen to me chart
not fantastic well appreciate as always super informative and always a pleasure so I'm yeah look
super looking forward to the PhD conference in May and also to our 24-hour life
yeah definitely yeah awesome guys well it was great you both and yeah always a pleasure
good to see good to see you guys sorry remind ones the 24-hour life again seven seven
seventh of the seventh do I have that yeah do you have any you care you're here midday
about the same time you started this one yeah yeah so okay my my my clever ploy of 24-7-7 didn't
I thought how could we forget that anyway that was good and if there's any English
people watching from your channel and to the Richard is doing a talk the Easter weekend at the wall
on health so if you want to come along and see Richard talk because he says nobody wants to hear him
but they do they do because he's got lots to say so that's the Easter weekend and there's a link
in the description if you want to come in here Richard's talk and there's some old far talking
about blood as well there on the same day so yeah if you want to see that then book into the
wall on health it's going to be a two-day conference so yeah thanks Anthony thank you time
you guys is great to see you yeah you two won and thanks everyone for joining