Hello, good morning. Good evening for everyone who is in America. Today is the live for April 25th in America
26th in Australia another part of the world. Thank you everyone for joining
Sorry again for being late seems to be a habit. I should probably start
Organizing these four times I can actually make but thank you all for joining and
Try to answer all the questions that are available
I do have to lead for work in about an hour and a half but I'll try to get to everything as much as I can
And thank you to elf for letting people know that I'm on my way and good to see you in the live
Chaffee: Okay, let me just get going on Instagram here as well
As you run x
Instagram and
YouTube as usual so great so we'll start with some of the
Superchats
First one is from cibi thank you very much cibi
Early cue because I'm in the UK. Oh, yeah, so which is in the UK so that's the middle of the night
UK won't catch this live
Our egg whites inflammatory is there meant to protect the yolk and
They say animals don't want
Chaffee: Anything eating their eggs so there must be some level defenses in them
There is a level of defense in the in the egg whites and some people can be more sensitive to them
Some people have more of a problem especially if you don't cook them so if you cook the egg it can be or the egg white it can be
Say for your denature some of these things
Some people don't have any problem that's me. We'll drink
Eggs raw I've done that myself had
No issues that I've noticed but some people do especially with auto immunity should probably avoid
Certainly raw egg whites
If not egg whites in general
Quite often they'll have
I won't have a problem with egg yolks, but just just be mindful of their own situation
Chaffee: You know they're giving me a lot of reasons why some people will feel better or worse on different sorts of meat or eggs
The other day doesn't really matter if they if you respond
differently and negatively towards them just you know something else you'd something that that makes you feel better
Chaffee: It could be a psychosumatic sort of issue that you're just not used to eating red meat or fatty meat and your body's just
Chaffee: We're to give it oh what's this and you'll get over that with with more exposure
But you know if you're not enjoying something or it's giving you some sort of weird reaction
You know just eat eat another meat or animal product that doesn't do that to you and
You know just and eat the things that you enjoy and make you feel good
As long as it's meat
Chaffee: Now, thank you for the super chat. I doc. I've been told I need to temporarily stop working out when starting carnivore to let my body adjust is that true
And if true for how long I don't think that's necessarily true
I think that you just keep doing what you're doing most people feel better straight away
I mean, I don't know why you have to adjust to
Chaffee: Not introducing poison into your body if anything you should probably avoid working out if you're poisoning yourself because your body's being hurt
Now you're not being hurt your body's allowing you to or you're allowing your body to sort of work the way it's supposed to work
I guess the argument could be
That when you're fat adapting your body's getting you surrounding on ketones
I'm mobilizing fat stores and making your own carbohydrates
There could be a lag in your energy levels and that could you could see a bit of a dip and not feel as good
So maybe you give your body a rest to just
Get over that
But you don't have to you know you just be mindful that you might have a dip in your energy and your and your
Exercise output that usually lasts a couple weeks two three weeks at most for most people
There are the rare
Few exceptions that takes several months
You know some people have pretty wretched energy
Chaffee: For many months and then all of a sudden just something comes out of it and they they get out the other side and so
Don't necessarily know why the hell that is but it does seem to be
slower conversion for some people than others the vast majority of people will feel
Fantastic after about two weeks as far as energy levels are concerned even with their exercises
I know a lot of people that convert over and they don't have any dip in their exercise
Or their output I was one of those people and then after two weeks it just
Took off so
Chaffee: That could there will be you so I don't know I don't think you you need to avoid exercise if anything that can help
Stimulate and spur your body into adapting further and faster so I wouldn't I wouldn't avoid that unless it's
You know just making you miserable and you just need to give your body a chance to make energy properly
David Walker thank you for the super chat
75 of carnivore day 15 of the line diet
If my second fasted blood tests still shows triglycerides of
Should I then continue the diet 21 year old male 180 pounds so I believe this is what this was the gentleman from
From the last live where we talked about
He said triglycerides were like a 1900 something I've never seen that in my entire life
I've never seen anybody with that and that's what's saying you need to get multiple data points
So meet does not raise triglycerides fact does not raise triglycerides dietary fat does not raise triglycerides
Eating carbohydrates eating sugar drinking alcohol potentially seed oils
Ray triglycerides so distress and so does poor sleep
I still never seen anybody with a 1900 on their on their triglycerides and absolutely
Chaffee: Never seen it go go like that because of a meat diet
I've seen a couple people that have gotten worse not really only one
That has gotten worse triglycerides when on a carnivore diet
But that was because they were an extraordinarily stressful situation at their work and when they
Came you know got out of that situation just all all came right down
Chaffee: So that that just normalize itself so stress is a major factor sleep is a major factor
Food is of course the main factor
Chaffee: But it's it's carbohydrates and the sugar and the alcohol that are going to raise your triglycerides and not meet
Chaffee: So yes, I would continue that I've just tried to figure out what the hell is going on with your blood tests and try to
Maximize your sleep
Chaffee: Optimize your stress levels and and make sure there's nothing else that sort of sneaking in
That might be complicating things
You know the 1900 I mean that sounds like it's it's not a fasted
Chaffee: Test they're saying hey right if my second fasted blood tests still shows this so that
Chaffee: Sort of suggest that the first one was a fasted test when you get an average test like this
Chaffee: It's just way off the scale you need to check it again in just basically straight away because it could just be a lab error
If you're if you're fasted and you're doing everything
In the correct way person in the morning no exercise no sex no stress or poor sleep
Leading up to the test
By a couple days
Then and you get some crazy number like that you check it again and you see okay, was that an accurate reading and
And then you try to figure out what the hell's going on there if it is an accurate reading
Chaffee: I would still continue the diet because the diet's not going to cause that is something else is going to cause that and you know going off
You you'd still be eating me right but you're adding in sugar and carbs and all these other sorts of things which will
Chaffee: Generally make your triglycerides worse so that's sort of adding to the problem as opposed to helping the problem
Chaffee: Even if you just went off and eat all together
Chaffee: That's not going to lower your triglycerides
You're going to be replacing that with carbs and sugar and seed oils which is going to
Raise your triglycerides so that's that's going to be the last thing you want to do
You're going to want to figure out why your triglycerides are crazy high like that
But again like that's that's a very average number that is very likely a lab error if you had actually if you actually done that fast. So just check it again
And then see how you go picture sleep picture stress make sure there's nothing else sneaking in and
Get more data points, you know, it could be some sort of
Genetic issue that I've never heard of that will slam your triglycerides up to to nearly 2,000
But again, I've never heard of it and
But it doesn't mean it doesn't exist and
Could be other factors that are going in and but it wouldn't it it won't be for meat meat does not raise triglycerides
Fat does not animal fat does not raise triglycerides
So you need to find what else is doing that but first first things first check it again
Chaffee: Do it in all that the same way no stress no exercise no sex for two days leading up to it
Certainly not the morning of drink a lot of water
Fast from the net for 9 p.m. Get your test first in the morning between 8.9 a.m. Don't take any pills
Or medications and stop any multivitamins or
B vitamins containing biotin which is a B vitamins you just stop all
Vitamin supplements basically for three days before because that can change your results as well and
Yeah, just get more data points and then
Try to figure out what the hell is going on if it's an extra accurate number which is just
Really unlikely, but please do
Let us know how that goes
and
Yeah, and see how you do
Lena. Thank you for the super chat does the amount of dairy cause
Weight stallers it simply just the dairy itself. I only have one or two ounces a day. I even heard that can stall
Um
so
You know more
More is going to cause more of a problem more can make you gain weight
Some can make you stall the thing is choose that it's it can cause compulsive eating people just sort of
Go to town on cheese and dairy and
You know, there's you sure start removing the stop mechanism or
Down
Chaffee: Regulating the stop mechanism that your body automatically does
um the
When you're only eating meat if you're just eating fatty meat you can eat eat till stops facing could your body's going to regulate that and tell you hey
Stop now
If you're if you're eating other things even dairy that can
upset that and then you end up eating more than you may want and you end up eating the exact same amount of meat
But you're at also adding on cheese so it just make you overeat a bit one in two ounces a day
Not all that much so from an overeating point of view
Probably not an issue there are some it there are some things that can cause information
And that could potentially lead you a bit of a disruption in your
Your hormonal physiology and homestasis
Chaffee: You know we don't we don't have exact reasons why that could be but some people do find the dairy is a weight loss
So one of two ounces day not all that much using it as a as a condiment melting it onto meat or into eggs or something like that
Chaffee: That's fine for most people see how you go if you're not getting the results if you want if you're not losing weight
As quickly as you think you should or losing fat specifically as quickly as you should because if you're putting on muscle
And you're losing fat you're staying the same weight so just remember that so
if you
Don't think you're losing fat in the way that you should
Just drop the dairy. It's really easy so only one to two ounces so that much shouldn't be hard to give up and so
Chaffee: You just see give it up for 30 days give it to give yourself an honest chance to to see a difference and and see for yourself
Chaffee: But yeah, it's a classic weight loss stall
one to two ounces a day
For most people probably not that big of a deal to see how it affects you
Chaffee: Beth Ratamokker. Thank you very much for the super chat in general how long after starting carnivore with someone be fully adapted
Chaffee: Clearative toxins and experiencing the full benefits. Thank you
Well full benefits is a bit different
majority of benefits within a few weeks
You're gonna get a lot of these toxins out of your body a lot of them seem a lot of people seem to feel a lot better after about two weeks
Chaffee: Alcohol generally takes around three to four weeks to get fully out of your system but it's almost it's better every every week every day
Chaffee: And so that's why I tell people you know give yourself a full 30 days because then you'll get most of the stuff out of your system
Chaffee: Then you'll start feeling really really good by the end of that time and you can give yourself
You know an accurate depiction of what you might feel like with all the stuff out of your system
Something's take longer so make a six is seed oils these sorts of things have a longer half life
It's like a couple of years half life so it can take years to clear this garbage out of your system and
Chaffee: After three four months you end up radically increasing amount of mitochondria
You're going throughout top of you this whole time you're turning over cells
Turn over cell lines you're turning over organelles and so we usually about six months on you sort of recycled and turned over all of your shows
You feel a lot better, but you can continue to stimulate more growth and
Increase the number of mitochondria and their efficacy going on to you know two three years, right?
So you're just going to keep getting benefits. You're going to feel
Chaffee: Fantastic after a few weeks you're going to get tons of things out of your system if you have any sort of medical issues
Chaffee: They can take
longer or shorter to go away a lot of them clear up quite quickly
Chaffee: Which is remarkable because people live with these things their whole life and they're just taking medications and medications
Chaffee: They're just getting worse and worse and worse and now all of a sudden just pull
You know a month or two in and these these serious medical issues are
Improving dramatically or even going away others take longer so Hashimoto's can take a year or two
Chaffee: Before you really get your antibodies down to zero depending on how high they were
And and then allow your thyroid a chance to repair which and may not do all the way
There is such a thing as damage done if we if we permanently damage ourselves
Chaffee: Due to exposure to the wrong food and causing autoimmunity or just direct toxic damage
Chaffee: You know from eating
cyanide containing things like almonds and cassava and
Chaffee: Flaxseed and these sorts of things that that can permanently damage your thyroid that can permanently damage your neurological system so
You know that that that can leave
Lasting damage that's not going to heal
fully but you'll get as you'll heal as much as your body is able to heal
So you'll feel a lot better most people feel a lot better after a few weeks
Two to three weeks if you'll dramatically better and I mean, I thought like a different breed of human
Chaffee: Just a super hero after two weeks and most people report that as well
Chaffee: Some people take some longer like I said to get that energy level and all that sort of stuff
But if
If you are
If you're
If you're coming to like a very strict carnivore diet and you're only eating meat and only drinking water most people and getting enough fat getting enough food
Most people will feel a lot better after two to three weeks but you get continuing benefits
Chaffee: You just keep feeling better and better and better and then you start having more energy you want to start working out
Chaffee: And that's going to obviously improve your health even more
So you get a vast amount of benefit within a few weeks and
Then you keep getting more benefits after that that makes sense so full maximum benefits
That's a lifelong expression right
But you keep getting it you get a lot of benefit just right away getting this garbage out of your system and
That can make you feel dramatically better within a couple weeks
Another question from Lena. Thank you very much Lena
Carnivore for about four months still no weight loss how much longer do you think till it comes off still facing brain fog
Am I not fat adapted yet?
Chaffee: So this was this was a question about
Chaffee: Dairy so look you're in that situation where you're not necessarily
Chaffee: Losing much weight remember that if you put on muscle and you lose fat you will stay the same weight
So the scale is really not what's important a lot it's really important for people to really focus on their health
As opposed to the scale the vast majority of people will lose weight and fat
Chaffee: Early on but other people will be you know everyone comes from a different situation metabolically and
hormonally and so you just need to look at things from where you are and focus on your health
This is about being healthy first and foremost. This is not a weight loss and gimmick
This is a health
Chaffee: Optimization technique this is this is eating to our biological design and being as health
Chaffee: We can possibly be that's the main thing weight generally comes along with that that loss generally comes along with that
But it's that it's important to focus on the health aspects
So think about how this is helping you think about how this is benefiting you and and and go from there and let the other things come as well
brain fog
Is rare but again there's there are some people that
It takes months before they really start seeing the full benefits
I don't exactly know why I haven't
Figured that one out yet
Chaffee: Because it's very rare. We just don't see it every now and then and then just all of a sudden just something just ticked over and just people feel
Massively better and their weight starts coming up. There are a lot of reasons for for weight loss
Stalls could be dairy could be other things that you're including in your diet like artificial sweeteners
That's a common one people including a rethought all monk fruit sugar
Chaffee: Stevia these sorts of things because they think well, it's natural sweet normal sugars and natural sweeteners, right?
And so you're we're avoiding that too. So, you know, you just want it just just eat fatty meat
Until it stops tasting good just cut out everything else just keep it simple
Chaffee: Have you know a bit of organs things like that the higher nutrient density
Chaffee: More saturated you're going to be earlier on your body's chasing nutrients. It's not chasing calories
So you don't want to eat the ton of of organs because that can be overwhelming to your system. You can get too much of a good thing
and
Have a hypervotaminosis or
Chaffee: Increased especially the fat soluble vitamins like vitamin A or things like copper and then different metals. They build up
And take a longer to clear out of your system than say like water soluble vitamins like b vitamins, right?
So just be mindful of that
But having a bit of organs especially early on when you're transitioning it's great idea
You know, it's nature's multivitamin, right? And so
And so you can try that there are other reasons different hormonal reasons things that people have leptin resistance LEPTIN
Chaffee: That's elevated. It's generally very difficult to lose weight from most people and
Chaffee: Some people still can but a lot of people don't a lot of people when they have high leptin. It's very stubborn weight loss
And that can be an indicative of a slowed and damaged metabolism and so you need to coaxial metabolism to increase
You don't want to starve it and suppress your metabolism more and that's what happens if you can if you chronically limit the amount of nutrients and
Energy available through your diet
Chaffee: Your body's just going to shut things down and you're going to feel really tired. You're going to have horrible brain fog
Chaffee: You're going to feel wretched and you're not going to really lose weight because your body's saying no, no, we have to store everything
Chaffee: Coming in is going into fat because we need to survive a famine and so just hold energy levels are down because less coming in less is going out
As you want to do the opposite you want to coax your system you want to coax your metabolism and speed it up
So you want to do things like exercise and aerobic exercise
So resistance training
Sprinting those sorts of things even though you feel tired you do it you'll get something done you
Start encouraging your system to work but you need to eat enough as well
You don't just want to exercise and not eat enough because then you're doing the opposite as well
Chaffee: Your body's like well now we really need to save everything because you know we're having a high demand output and
You know we're not getting enough in so we really need to hang on to this tightly
So they'll do that
Eat enough and eat fatty meat until it stops tasting good and you'll try that twice a day if you need to especially if you're working out
And see how that goes you can check test your blood you can test your thyroid you can test your
Leptin you can test your fasting insulin these are signs these are different things that if they're out of balance that can
Cause slow weight loss and and slow metabolism
Chaffee: You can also check your your nutrient status your B12 your vitamin D your zinc and your magnesium these are very important things
You get them with meat but
Chaffee: People when you're starting on this thing most people are a very deficient diet and not taking supplements
And so they're gonna be quite deficient in these things too to extend that the reference ranges have actually slid down and gotten
Chaffee: Lower because they're just an average for the community since everybody's deficient in magnesium
Chaffee: B12 zinc and vitamin D
Chaffee: They're just like just move that reference range. Yeah, well, this is normal now
Chaffee: It's like that's the new norm deficiencies the new normal apparently and
No, it's not normal and so if you're in the reference range for these sorts of things
Chaffee: You're not on the really upper end of that reference range or above that reference range you're low
That's all there is to it. I'm never seen
Any country or any any lab that
Had a reference range for B12 that's actually made it into what I would consider an optimal reference range for B12
So the other ones
You know sometimes they sort of lip into the right range but not always
So you want to be on the upper end of their reference range if you're sort of low normal for them you're really low
If you're low low for them
Really low
So you can check those things as well
But just be patient get out everything except fatty meat and water
Chaffee: And make sure you're eating enough make sure you're sleeping well because that can be a major stall as well if you're stressed out
You're not sleeping well that raises cortisol and that will stall your way loss and
There are a lot of different things it food is
The main factor here, but these other factors really matter as well so just keep that in mind as well and and then just just keep giving it time
Chaffee: You know it can take longer for some people than others even when they're doing it right the vast majority of people
Don't have as much of a delay as this
But you know it will happen for you too. I've never seen anyone not get there and some people
Chaffee: I see that their leptins massively elevated and it just takes time and they're not really losing weight
Chaffee: Not really losing weight not really losing weight and then all of a sudden their leptins coming down the whole time
And then also just hits that tipping point and the rest of their metabolism other sorts of factors coming to play and just well then they start losing weight
I just had a lady actually
I've been following since last year
She
Has been doing this and you explain that to her and and she'd been over way to whole life nothing had ever worked and
And she came around around this and she said okay, I'm just gonna give it a try
Chaffee: You know, I knew it can take longer and and she's doing this for her health and she just really enjoyed it
Chaffee: She was eating well and things would and you know, it wasn't hard for her to do so just like okay, you know
Chaffee: She wasn't really losing much weight but her leptin was sky high and her fasting insulin was very elevated as well
Chaffee: She had other other markers that you know, this was gonna take a while and
You know, so we we corrected things and added a bit of liver and all these sorts of things
She was able to eat and we just sort of tractor every month and she's usually losing a bit
But not all that much and
You know really just very slow, but she's like, yeah, I'm just I'm in this for the long haul
You know, I feel good
I'm just gonna focus on my health and just give it time
That was back in August, right? So it was a long time ago, right and just last month
She came in hadn't seen it for sort of a month before that and every month
She was just sort of like losing just a little bit a little bit a little bit and then all of a sudden bam
16 kilos
Which is
Significant right I mean, that's like 35 pounds right so
Chaffee: That was in a month month six weeks, you know, and so that just that just happened to hit just that was it or
Chaffee: Or left him was coming down down down and then bang
Just dropping all this weight so
Chaffee: You know that that is generally what happened as you're body needs to just get to a point where it's happy and it's saying
Chaffee: Okay, we're not in a family anymore. We can release this so
Fix all those other things and
Then after that just give it time and I think it'll do fine
I'm sure you'll do fine
Akin thank you for the super chat
question
Chaffee: I've just got my first A1c after starting carnivore serum sugar
From eight to seven point two A1c from six point eight to six point four
Triangle stretch one point one HCl one
I'm disappointed my HBA one C isn't lower what might be the next step I need to take well first of all it came down and that's good
Doesn't doesn't do that any other way, right? I mean what what
You know have you what have you done so far that has given you
Even that much of the drop in your A1c
Right so you know, I mean this is we need to be
Appreciative of this as well you know count your blessings some people have have more of a drop than that but
You know who cares you know like some of some people have you know when you're coming from the very higher
Levels of A1c that can have a more dramatic drop
So I mean I've seen people with a HBA one C of you know 13 14
Drop down to you know five or six after three four months. That's that's incredible, right?
So that doesn't happen but that doesn't happen either
Sounds what was it go from six point eight to six point four only just goes up and just goes up it goes up and you try to slow it down with the medication and life style
But it only goes up that that was the previous thought and teaching was it?
This is a progressive disease and it only gets worse, right?
Not anymore so you're already improving and that's that's you're already
Breaking the norm breaking the standard so that's great. You should be really happy with that also how long was it between tests
Right, you know was it one month two months three months five months six months a year
Right, obviously that's kind of matter two so the point the the main thing is is the trend
You're trending in the right direction also if you're on
Blood sugar medications for your diabetes you should not stop them until
Your blood sugar indicates that it's appropriate to if you're if you're you're fasting blood sugar
You really should be between four and five that's what you want to keep it and so if you need medications to keep it there
Take medication is to keep it there, right
Going from eight to seven point two and dropping from six point eight to six point four that
That seems about right, you know you want to be you want your fasting steer
Fasting blood sugar to be between four and five really so you still have insulin resistance
You still have diabetes. You still need to take medication if you're on it
Chaffee: You should probably be on it
Chaffee: In this case that can help you bring that blood sugar down and reduce the insulin resistance or give you an up insulin if you're not producing it
For now, but it's
Most people can come off insulin
But it takes time
Right, so it can take you know people
Chaffee: You know people get you're very excited that that this can help reverse their diabetes
Chaffee: So they go, okay, if I just stop eating carbs, I don't have diabetes anymore
No, not yet, you know you have you have lead poisoning, right? And so you stop drinking
Chaffee: Let it water great. There's still lead in your body. There's still poison in your body
Chaffee: Your body still has to recover from that and if you need medications to get that lead for their out of your system and heal and repair the damage from that lead
Chaffee: Great, you know, then so be it. Thank goodness. They have medications for those things
I don't think we use that as a crutch to justify eating a whole bunch of carbs and sugar
Definitely not but if you need it
Because you have damage and you're you're using it as a bridge when you're transitioning to a
Great, that's very useful and so that's what medication is supposed to be for it's this temporary bridge to get you to where you need to go
not just a lifelong
You know, lifelong condition that you have to chronically be taking even though that's what they are
Build for and design for because
That's what makes them the most money is if you take this to rest of your life
You don't need to take it to rest of your life, but you may need to take it right now
Chaffee: So if you if you're on medication, I continue taking your medication
Chaffee: I would try to get your blood sugar down between four and five when you're especially when you're fasting
And and if you need you know that form in or whatever you're taking to achieve that
So be it. Don't come off your medication until it's actually appropriate to what you know what
Whatever you're doing is working. So that's good. You know, it's all about the trend. You're going in the right direction and so
Why would we be upset about that it's going in the right direction? You know, we can all want in instant results
But this is amazing that doesn't happen normally right and so doing anything else that doesn't happen
This is the only thing that has ever done that right there
Right and so you'd be very happy about that be very proud of that and just look forward to the rest look forward to
Continuing get better, you know, if you know, if you're if you're not pure pure pure fatty meat and water get there
Chaffee: And and get rid of all artificial sweeteners everything I don't care if they don't have carbs and then
I don't care if Aliulos has a much lower glycemic index just don't eat it
Just don't have it just eat fatty meat
Chaffee: Only drink water you'd do your full stay on meds when you need them come off when it's appropriate and you will do you will do just fine
Chaffee: And you will reverse your diabetes as what people all around the world are doing
Of by the millions now. It's absolutely incredible. So
You know, just keep it up keep going get as pure as you can and
Chaffee: Just be patient. It is going in the right direction and you're doing great. So just keep it up
Chaffee: Beth Rathamocker. Thank you for the super chat. I heard that ground beef is higher in histamines than other meat
How do you know if you're sensitive to histamines? Sorry
Some requests is now. That's perfectly fine. So you know the thing is is that
Whether or not there are histamines in there
Doesn't matter if you react to it that that's that's the thing so some people
Get some sort of a reaction that they that is unpleasant to them when they have brown beef or when they have
Leftovers they put in the refrigerator to have it the next day and give them some sort of weird reaction
Chaffee: Is that histamines? Is that something else who knows? I mean I talked to people all the time
They swear by it being his means. I talked to other people. They're like there's no chance in hell
That that's the case. It's I think it's something else
Doesn't matter what matters is that you're reacting to it right and so that's the only thing that matters
so it's not a matter of of
Knowing if your sensitive to histamines are not
If that's even a thing, would you maybe? I don't know. I don't really care
I'm looking at this more from a practical standpoint
Do you eat ground beef is that?
Giving you a reaction that's negative?
Chaffee: Yes, eat something else. No go to town. That's the only thing that matters
Chaffee: So it doesn't matter why you're getting a reaction or you're not getting a reaction
If it's just can you eat it? Do you enjoy it? Is it making you feel good? Yes? Keep eating it? No
Find something else. It doesn't give you the same reaction and so that's the main thing so just try it out
Try some ground beef if you don't have any problems with ground meats and no problem
Beth Rathamocker. Thank you for the super chat
Chaffee: Hunger changes from day to day. So it seems like I eat it different times every day. Is it okay?
Chaffee: Not to have any kind of schedule. Thank you is always that's fine. Just eat fatty meat until it stops tasting good
If you're doing that in the morning or during the day, you're gonna get a bit more tired especially if you're eating
Maximally and so you're just may
Bung up your day
So if you're doing that during the day, maybe try to eat less than your body wants just sort of half as much take the edge off
So you can keep going and still have good energy levels. I
And to eat my bigger meals later in the day later at night because that
Automatically just makes me a bit more tired and I want to go to sleep and that's a good time to go to sleep is at night
So
But yeah, just the fatty meat until it stops tasting good and and do so in a way that's logistically feasible for you
So you're not getting tired or work on things like that
Carnavoir says not a question just want to thank you
For doing a stocked shape you we need more people like you. Well, thank you very much Tom. I appreciate that
Reabell. Thank you for the super chat
Is there any type? Is there any hope for someone on the carnivore diet
Chaffee: Who had to stop carnivore due to alpha gals syndrome? Carma hydrates mess me up so bad as well
And I don't know what to eat anymore. Yeah, no, you absolutely can it's just you have to avoid red meat
So the other meats are fine. So like chicken and fish
Possibly pork don't look that up though um and
And and take a look, but yeah, so
Yes, you can it's it's really just like the red meats that you that you need to avoid
And from what I have
What I have been told by other doctors is that it is it's basically temporary and so after
You know after a couple months or you know six months or a year or something like that
Chaffee: You lose that sensitivity and you can start eating red meat again. So yes, there's definitely hope
Not even hope you can just keep doing this right now you just need to avoid the red meats and so it
On deck chicken fish eggs and things like that. I mean you can you can find online which meets will have the alpha clock toast
What about how it is that you you react to
from that tick bite
It is thankfully still pretty rare
Who knows how much more prevalent that's gonna get pretty
Is this you know coincidental this is this is happening?
Chaffee: We'll be able to try to get us to the less red meat and all of a sudden people developing allergies towards a red meat
Chaffee: When that's what people were saying. Well, this is what we should do just to make people allergic to red meat
So that they they don't eat as much so we force them to not eat as much
I think that's that's kind of funny that this is coming out exactly exactly the same time that you said that that's
a way that we should
Way we can control people to eat less red meat
Not saying that that's what it is, but it's a bit odd that they're saying that I don't know how hell they would do that
They're does seem to be a tick bite, you know the low-star tick that's that's causing this or at least that's what's being reported
and we all
You know have our opinions on how accurate and
authentic and honest the reporting is these days either way
Seems that red meat's a problem there and so you just eat chicken fish eggs things like that and
You'll look up the different sorts of things that that are safe to eat on alpha gal and
and you know then six months or so
You know try some beef again see how you go with it and hopefully
That goes away, but yeah, you can absolutely still just eat meat now. You don't have to eat carbs or any of the other garbage
So yeah, you can still definitely just eat carnivore
Joe comic thank you for the super chat
ever seen carnivore for prostitutes 58 years old
dealing with prostitutes after stream injections or steam injections for
20 months ago PSA 2.5 paying information pelvic tightness sex issues all post procedure. I'm really sorry to hear that
Chaffee: You know it really just depends on what's what's causing these things if you have a of a sort of post-operative
complication
It's at least going to give you a body a chance to heal as much as that as it can it can help with BPH and you know just reducing insulin can help reduce BPH
so
You know the actual damage and pain and dysfunction from that procedure
I don't know I just have to sort of see but you know being on on an optimal diet like a carnivore diet or
The carnivore diet of the carnivore diet is at least going to put your body into a position that it can heal as well as possible
and and be as healthy as it's possible to be and recover and heal from as much as you're able to heal from
I don't think that you're going to be able
to heal as well if you're on anything else anyway
So it's definitely worth a shot hopefully it does help you
But um, there's really no way to tell you know, I mean there's things there there is again such thing such a thing is damaged
Chaffee: Done and if you have permanent damage due to injury from a procedure
It may not recover but a lot of things do recover and this will at least give you the best chance to
To recover that you can you can get and good luck with that. I hope it works
George story. Thank you for the super chat
How did the micro nutrients and bacon and eggs compare to room minute meat?
Our bacon and eggs sustainable long-term as a primary food store so on carnivore. Yeah, you know, I mean it's it's probably better with the red meat the room minute meat
They're also going to be able to filter out more of the plant toxins especially when they're being fed
Things that they're not designed to eat pigs and chicken being fed corn and so are they're not designed to eat that stuff
They're not going to be able to detoxify as much. They're not going to get as much nutrients from it
They're not going to be as nutritious. They're not going to have
Be able to filter out more of those new those toxins
Whereas a you know a room minute animal like a cow they ferment this stuff and break it down make it much more nutrient rich
Even if it's not their natural diet and
Detoxify more of these things through that fermentation process and so it's safer
Chaffee: But we're toxic load higher nutritional about nutrient density, but
There's a difference again between
Grass fed and finish regeneratively raised beef and
Feet lot beef, right?
Chaffee: There's only you know a couple months in the feed lot of three months in the feed lot and that can significantly reduce the amount of nutrients that are in there
Chaffee: And doing it on a regenerative pattern where you're moving the animals around and you regenerating the land
Chaffee: You're actually regenerating the nutrients you building up more nutrients. It's pretty crazy to think about you think of it
Chaffee: You just keep it sort of stable, but no actually increases the nutrients in the soil in the grass in the cow
And then more nutrients going around just more more more more more more so doing in that process makes that makes the cow more
Nutritious makes the land more more more viable and fertile
It's pretty amazing. It's absolutely amazing amazing
The ecology of it all
so
Bacon and eggs
You know, are you getting pasture raised pork or are you getting pasture raised chicken and eggs?
That's going to make a big difference too
Chaffee: Massive difference. You have a massive difference in the amount of micronutrients available as well
Yes, you could eat bacon and eggs rest of your life. If they're pasture raised bacon and eggs, it's going to be a lot better a lot better
Chaffee: And
Chaffee: Some people just can't do that some people thought I'm going to use your other issues
Can't really do
Or eggs or even chicken or farm deficient particular so but you know if you do good do well on
Chaffee: Bacon and eggs and you feel fine just make sure you get bacon. It doesn't have much of sugar in it
Try to get like no sugar cure bacon and
You know and you should be fine if you feel good you feel good. I feel best on beef
Hands down. I feel great on bacon and eggs
Certainly taste good, but I always feel the best on beef red meat in particular red meat in general anyway
So just see how you go, but yeah, you could you could eat bacon and eggs rest of your life
Tebo, thank you for the for the question. I'd like to ask Dr. Chafe to address my sick feeling after
Just eating meat ten days in a carnivore, please
Yeah, often this is this is that psychosomatic sort of
Condition response where we're like, well meet bad for me. That's bad for me. I'm gonna avoid this
That's your your brain is telling you. Oh, this is bad. This is bad
You need avoid that but also
You if you're getting a negative feeling you're short of feeling sick and it doesn't really taste good
Chaffee: You brought it your body is telling you no uncertain terms that you are not hungry anymore
So you eat fatty meat until it stops tasting good
Chaffee: If you if it's if it's the fat is making you a bit queasy and nauseous you need to ease and do it
Chaffee: Just have smaller amounts of fat cut off a piece of fat put it with only a piece of meat
Chaffee: Eat it together say like, oh, okay, that actually tastes nice together and you go on from there
Any sort of build up it can take months before you undo that conditioning that we've all had
Chaffee: For entire lives about how horrible that is for you. So we actually get a visceral
Response that we're feel sick
So you can ease into it that way but also if you're eating fatty meat and it tastes good eventually
It's gonna not taste good and that's your body telling you to stop and if you keep going
He's oh, well, I have to finish my plate. I haven't eaten that much and but oh, I feel sick
I'm feeling all that your body telling you to stop it doesn't matter how much is on your plate
Stop just putting in the fridge right your body knows what it's doing as long as you're just eating
fatty meat and water
Chaffee: Let your body handle it so if you're if you're not feeling well feeling sick or queasy and you don't really want to eat meat don't eat
Right
Chaffee: But if your body selling you not to eat meat. It's telling you just not to eat. It's not just telling you not to eat meat. It's telling you
Not to eat okay, so that would be that would be my advice
Question from Charles Ben Dari. Hi. I have been following you from Ghana very cool. Can you explain further to me?
That we don't really
We don't really like vegetables is it because of the chemicals applied to them or
Naturally not good for humans. Yeah, they're just naturally not good for humans think about it this way
You get lost in the in the woods or the jungles of Ghana and you run out of food
Chaffee: You know, can you eat any random plant in the forest? No, most of them will make you very very sick or even kill you
The vast majority of plants will kill
You and every other animal on earth, right
So all plants are poisonous. It's just that certain animals evolve the ability to eat certain plants and detoxify them safely
And they can eat that plant
Chaffee: But if they go outside of that they get very sick and this is why animals in the wild they eat very specific plants
Then they venture outside of that they can get very very sick or they can even die
So the plant itself is bad for us and then we add insult to injury and we dump a bunch of
Chemical toxins and pesticides on them
Make them even more poisonous. So
Chaffee: There's definitely a combination there. You know the pesticides are definitely not good for you
The plants worse so I would I would avoid that if you if you watch on
Chaffee: YouTube there's a there's a lecture I gave it a medical conference that I just
Chaffee: You know, just went from big air and just named it plants are trying to kill you and I made this argument in front of
Chaffee: Not be recommending these things to your patients and
Very skeptical crowd at first by the end of it. You know, I it was very well received and I had a lot of people coming out to me after that
You know, you know, just like you know white hair professors of medicine, you know very
All steer and suits coming out to me saying like I never want to eat a goddamn vegetable again in my life
I'm sorry
You know job done so
It's you know what's that it's on the low carb down under YouTube channel and
I have I have one called by the same name
Chaffee: Plant your trying to kill you on my channel is more of a discussion we talk about very similar points
But I like the one on low carb down under because it's just
You know it's a it's a presentation, you know, it's not a discussion. I'm just you know
hitting points and and there's you know these visuals because I have a PowerPoint as
presentation as well so it's
That's the one to watch and that tells you exactly
you know why
Chaffee: It's a plant themselves that we have to worry about more than the pesticides and and actually we looked at the comparison of this and found that
The natural plant toxins are actually worse than the pesticides at least the ones that they've studied
Back in the the late 80s really 90s. So yeah, check that out
But yeah, it's the plant itself and the and the chemical to reply to that just make it worse
These thank you very much for the generous super chat
The Valkorn of War for seven months plus
Chaffee: Dealing with Tartar buildup which I understand is more calcium and saliva
Chaffee: I don't hear a lot of people mention this is this normal. Yeah, can be you know if you look back at the fossil record you know a pre-agrarian
People that big wide jaws perfect teeth all 32 of rupted and perfect and
And there's buildup there's there's um
You know there's
Calcifications or or whatever the hell of some sort of sort of harder buildup in between the teeth so you know there goes
Flossing you don't need to floss and probably protects those the teeth and the gums and things like that as this little little layer
So they had that excellent teeth excellent teeth health and you see that sort of patina
of buildup in there and actually you know survived in the fossil record so
You know when when you have the normal
Oral biome that's probably very normal, you know, we like having clean teeth with all that stuff scraped off so we do
fine
But it seemed in the in the wild and nature
I was a very normal thing to have that buildup in between the teeth and protecting the gums and things like that
Chaffee: So if you're eating car or maybe other sorts of things you're going to get the wrong kind of bacteria
Chaffee: You're going to get a different oral biome and you are going to have
Rodding and nasty sort of things you get that buildup
You're going to have a whole bunch of
Bad bacteria in there and that's going to cause other problems the other thing too is that people find that
Chaffee: Oxilates can do that as well so you have sort of oxidative by sort of getting rid of oxilates can get more
Tarder buildup in your mouth and you can you can get pretty dramatic and so you might have to get more cleanings or
You know scrape that off more regularly and that can be from
From the oxilates as well and some people don't have much of an issue as well so it can be normal
You know long before we had dentists, you know, we had teeth and they didn't run out of our heads and animals
No, I don't have dentists and their teeth don't run out of their head
Chaffee: So and what we we noticed what in the fossil record was that you did get that sort of buildup so that can be normal
But also it can be
Buildup of you know from from dumping out oxilates and
Building up sort of calcium oxilate deposits around your teeth as well because you might just try to get this stuff to hell out because it's just poison
And you know, but if you if you you don't want to get that stuff scraped off get it scraped off, you know, that's fine and
If it's oxilates that will slow down eventually and and just
Chaffee: Get just a bit more normal, but you shouldn't get cavities anyway as long as you're not eating
Anything else besides me
Carnivorous plant. Thank you for the super chat
Chaffee: Does carnivore help with her pseudism? Her pseudism is inappropriate hair growth
On women so body and facial hair that would be in more typically male pattern
Due to high testosterone typically so it depends on what's causing it
But the leading cause of PCOS which is elevated testosterone and women and
Lowered estrogen levels
Leading to infertility and and polycystical variance syndrome is PCOS
That
The leading cause of that and that's the leading cause of infertility and women is
Chaffee: Insulin resistance so high insulin having high insulin
Chaffee: Chronically high insulin because women make estrogen or testosterone first and that conversion to estrogen in the ovaries
And so elevated
Insulin will block the conversion testosterone into estrogen so you get too much testosterone
And you get her pseudism because you get you're getting too much too much testosterone
So it can help with that
Chaffee: Are there other cause of her pseudism or there other causes of having excess testosterone? Yes, absolutely
But it can certainly help with the some of the more common causes
Which is what I just described there that the insulin resistance
Any ketogenic time should do that especially when you're getting rid of lectins
Different plant toxins that can actually bind on to the insulin receptors
By the times more tightly than insulin shouldn't get even though you're not even carbohydrates
And your insulin is normal you still get an insulin like a fact and insulin affects
Over a hundred different processes in your body including the conversion of testosterone and estrogen and so
Even just the lectins can do that as well and so yes, it can definitely help that
But again it depends on what's causing the her pseudism
I mean medications that can do that to
Gunther SB thank you for the super chat
If oh also
Which probably stop super chats now because I got a
lot load of them and
So
I need to leave I had around 11 because I have I have
appointment
Shortly after that
Chaffee: So if rabbis have a wonderful on a faculty protein ratio
Chaffee: What are some good non-rendered sources of roommate fat?
I can add to boost to a two to one
Fat protein ratio non-rendered the not only non-render would be just getting
cuts of
Fat the fat trimmings from the butcher and just frying those up in a pan and even those together
Just have a little
Palo fat next year your meat as well
You know if you wanted the other floor would be like melted butter
Palo those sorts of things but really just the the fat trimmings
That's the best way to do that especially in a non-rendered form
K&N can thank you for the super chat
Chaffee: Hi doc. I have a family member with type two diabetes and stage three colon cancer
Chaffee: They are on a lot of meds. I tell them to try keto or corn or more please help
Well look I mean, you know that's that's very good of you to to recommend that. I think it will help both
We know we that that died two diabetes is reversible clinically by putting people on a high fat meat-based ketogenic diet
Like a corn or more diet so we know that
So that'll help but also that high blood sugar from the diabetes is feeding the colon cancer
So ask them if they ever got a pet scan and you get that pet scan you see where these hotspots are
So that's a cancer
Light up like a Christmas tree. Why does it light up because we give them an injection of glucose
That's radio labeled and then we see where that glucose goes where that sugar goes
Right where those carbs go and it goes right to that cancer in a pool and I can't you just sucks at all
up right
Every time they have carbs
They need to remember that pet scan that their cancer is now lighting up
And all those cancer cells are whole flush with energy
That's what happens every time you eat carbs and you have cancer
so
Chaffee: Colon cancer is not caused by red meat that's an insanity that's just it's liable really and slander and
I wish red meat could sue the people and doctors that that push out that slider because it's a complete bullshit
There are a lot of people treating colon cancer by going on a pure red meat and water diet only and it's
pushing back their disease
Look up ketogenic metabolic therapy
Chaffee: Work with professor Thomas C3 look up Thomas C3 S. E. Y. F. R. I. E. D
Check out my interview with him on this channel and and you'll see what I mean. This is this is
You know this this is you know if you understand the biology of cancer
It's it's very straightforward and you would treat this very differently than we're treating it now
Chaffee: I also gave a lecture at another medical conference called ketogenic metabolic therapy as an adjunct to
as a novel adjunct to
Standard care and cancer and and sort of goes through this but there are dozens and dozens and dozens of studies in
Multiple different kinds of cancers like dozens in each type of cancer
Showing efficacy and benefit and and hundreds and animals showing benefit of ketogenic diets in
Cancer so you know, it's just and it's just remember the warberg effect
Novel prize winner auto warberg showed that cancer cells require
400 times the amount of glucose is normal cells and they can't run on ketones
So you limit the supply of glucose you limit the energy to those cells and your cells are all fine because your your cells primarily run on ketones
anyway
so
Watch those things. I have a playlist on YouTube on my YouTube channel just
Chaffee: Cancer as a lot of videos on cancer and so I would just go through those and
Try to get your family member to watch those because they
Will reverse their diabetes and by doing that it will
Significantly help their their fight with cancer and help help manage it much better
Good luck with that. I hope they do well
Tyler Durant has resurfaced and
Thank you for the super chat not seeing a question attached for maybe down the road
You wills Anderson thank you very much for the very generous super chat
Chaffee: Following your advice Dr. C days six of no coffee previous only one organic coffee in the morning
Head pain fatigue light sensitivity woke up during the night with reflux never had that before
Had camel mild tea sorry and set up for hours any tips. I mean it's just withdraws you know
It's like it's this this is a drug withdrawal and so you know that
That does go away your your day six. That's usually the the sort of the tail end of it
Chaffee: You know early on if you're if you're really getting really bad headaches if you take like a no dose like a
caffeine cap tablet and take like a quarter of that so like 25 milligrams that can take the edge off the headaches in the
And the
And the different sorts of withdrawal side effects and sort of you know when you off of it
quickly
But you know
Chaffee: You're sort of through most of that at this point most people feel a lot better after the first week the first week is usually the toughest so drink a lot of water
Eat me until you're satisfied if you know and and you're almost there. I wouldn't even
I wouldn't even recommend taking a tiny amount of caffeine unless you're having just a massive
Splitting headache, but most of the time at at this point you're pretty much through it. So we'll why start that up again? Why start the addiction process up again?
You know, I would just I would just
You you weathered it this far
Generally this is the tail end of it. I think you'll do
Chaffee: Much better very soon in the next sort of week or so you should be you should be
Through the worst of it and feeling a lot better so good luck with that
The real Carolina guy. Thank you for the super chat
Chaffee: I'm about to start carnivore and do not want to lose a lot of weight
As I am an optimal for my fitness. I just want to shed body fat any suggestions
Chaffee: Well if you're going to shed body fat you're going to lose weight if you're not putting on muscle
Chaffee: But if you're working out and you're and you're doing fitness then the body fat you lose
You'll put on muscle mass as well. But if you have excess body fat then you have
Unhealthy weight that you don't really want on your body
Chaffee: You know the number on the scale doesn't matter what matters is your health and your and your your composition your body composition
That's what really matters and so
If you just eat fatty meat till it stops tasting good and you lift weights, you know you should be fine
and
And you should actually put on muscle as opposed to
Losing it and
You should be fine. So just work out lift weights
Eat meat be happy eat until it stops tasting good. You want to get enough nutrients or else yeah, you could you could lose
Chaffee: More lean body mass and you want you won't be able to maintain more lean body mass
You're going to lose inflammation you're going to lose water weight you're going to lose some unhealthy fat
Those all have weight to them and so you're going to lose some weight
But that's not lean body mass. That's not healthy weight. That's weight that you didn't want
And if you're working out if you're exercising if you're lifting weights if you're doing sprinting
You'll put on muscle and
You'll gain muscle and you'll probably gain weight in the long run. So good luck with that
Venetros. Thank you for the super chat
Hi, J.V. Have you had an experience with patients who have Lyme disease and how
Carnivore has helped affected them or come across any studies before well
Chaffee: You know treating Lyme disease and things like that since the 1800s with red meat and water diet and yes a lot of people have
Come to a carnivore die because of their chronic Lyme disease
I've had a number of people on my podcast who have put their Lyme disease into remission
by using a carnivore die and you you can find them on their Angela
I'm blanking over last name, but
She did I think Rebecca Heishman did as well and a number of others
But yeah, if you go to so you can watch those those videos and and you know, they they dramatically improved their
Their hell, I mean massively. I mean these these poor ladies were
Nearly dead at a certain point and
Chaffee: It's completely reversed and have horrible Lyme disease for a long time
Chaffee: Gone now or at least so
Chaffee: Reduce that they they don't really notice it anymore and
You can watch those for inspiration. You can also go to the older
Better
The better older
Chaffee: Baseball groups such as zero carb health and zeroing in on health that you know like 15
Plus years of data
Chaffee: Just go and just join those and go into the search function and just say Lyme disease you'll get tons of threads of people
Asking the same questions that you have and getting getting answers from people that have gone through this and
But the answer is yes, it does help
Dark sky. Thank you for the super chat
Chaffee: Have you heard any testimonies of people improving from MS or CIDP with carnivore?
Chaffee: Yes, absolutely. I mean MS at like any autoimmune disease improves dramatically
On a carnivore diet, but you really have to be very strict is red meat and water very high fat
the brain and the
And the the nervous system
The myelination this is made out of fat the myelin is is specifically
Made out of fat so when you have a you know chronic you know demelination process such as MS or CIDP
Chaffee: Then you know you need the building blocks. You need the cholesterol
Chaffee: You need the saturated fat need the B12 as well. B12 is required for
Milinating your your axons almost everyone is deficient in B12
If you're in the range for B12 you're low on B12
Chaffee: That's a fact in America if you're under 540 that's critically low and just that level can cause demelination in it up itself
So if you have a demelination disorder
Chaffee: You really need to make sure that your your B12 is above that really way above that because that's a
Critical deficiency you need to be a lot higher than that you need to be double that basically
Critical deficiency in Australia is different units Australia Europe
England things like that
It's under 400 that's a critical deficiency that you can get demelination of your of your axons, right?
And so you want to be between 12 on 800 and 1200 and those countries in America you want to be between 1100 and
1600 right so the reference range is never make it up that high never
And then the UK the reference range goes up like 540 right you know 550 something like that is this like no nope
That's not good enough and
You know you even Oxford showed that you get get levels below through you know three three 50 something like that
After five years people's brains were shrinking by five percent
How are we how are we pretending that that's in the normal range right and it does it goes down like one 30 and a lot of places so it's like clearly that's ridiculous so
Make sure your your B12 is up
Make sure you're just eating fatty meat
Make sure you're just eating red meat because that reduce that's going to be the best thing to do to reduce your antibodies
And then there's protocols using vitamin D most people are low and vitamin D too it's very important normal so
You know
Add in liver for the B12 and vitamin D they even some folate in there although B12's
You depend on what you talk to
There's people to think that it's really not about the folate. It's just about the B12 as long as you have enough B12
Folates isn't as much of an issue
Chaffee: But then vitamin D all these things exist in abundance in liver so you know just you hit cover all your bases with that
Even taking a B12 shot if you're if you're below that
Critical level. I mean just don't mess around just get it get a shot get it taken care of
Chaffee: And and you know we might have a nutritional deficiency or an absorption issue you may have a
Chaffee: Pernishes inemia where you're just not going to be able to absorb B12 properly
You need to find that out and you need to make sure that you're
Either through injection or under the tongue supplement
Getting enough B12 if you're not able to absorb it properly and
Of course B12 doesn't exist in plants or fungus so you need to get it from meat in your diet
But look with that
Those are main take home points though. I have a lady that I interviewed who did recover from MS
Very severe case of MS
Dr. Sarah and it's sort of the that so it's called from wheelchair to walking
She actually was wheelchair bound and in early 30s she's basically dying and
Six months later on a corner board diet on a lion diet with
High dose vitamin D she was not only out of her wheelchair, but she was back doing ballet
Which is amazing and so that's what she did. She did high dose vitamin D and a lot of red meat and nothing else
Make sure your B12 is up
Jump start that with an injection if you need to and then then maintain it and build on that with your diet and make
And but check it again because if you have an absorption issue or pernicious anemia
Which is if you have one autoimmune disease you almost certainly have another autoimmune disease
And pernicious anemia is an autoimmune disease that attacks apart of your stomach that releases intrinsic factor
You have to have intrinsic factor to bind to B12 to absorb that complex without intrinsic factor you don't absorb B12
Right so if you
Attacked and damaged that part of your stomach. It makes intrinsic factor because of this autoimmune disease
You know that's just something you need to know about you need to get in regular injections or
under the tongue sub-lingual
Supplementations so you can absorb it in another way because you're not going to absorb it through your gut because
You know you've got permanent damage there. Okay, so keep that in mind and check
Everyone should check. This applies to a lot of people
Chaffee: The the deficiency side of things in the mountain absorption side of things
Chaffee: Steven Wells. Thank you for the super chat try general neurology type two
Chaffee: Have you heard of anyone with this condition being cured by this diet so it can certainly improve I have seen people improve dramatically
so it's
There are different different causes and there's different sorts of
Chaffee: There's different sorts of ideologies for trigeminal neurology
Chaffee: But either way whatever's inflaming that trigeminal nerve
can be relaxed and calmed and the
Information can go down and that can reduce the signal up that nerve and get applying that pain response
So yes it can it can definitely help
Chaffee: It depends you know, I mean sometimes you get like an aberrant vessel that can sort of like move and shift around in your brain
And sort of like press on the trigeminal nerve and every time it
Be to just don't don't don't just hits that trigeminal nerve and you get pain pain pain pain
And so sometimes you need surgery you need to go in there and just put a little
Teflon pad
Chaffee: In between the the artery and the nerve and then that can
That can sort of block that off but yes it can
It can
Reduce the inflammation it can reduce the the pain sensation just like it does with a lot of other neurological pain
Pathologies
If you've got something pushing on that nerve though, is that going to reduce it all the way hard to say
Chaffee: Just have to see but it it almost certainly will reduce the pain if you're just getting rid of all this other
Information because that information increases the pain expression and so whatever pain you have in your body is going to be worse
Because of the things that you eat and so if you just cut all those things out then then that will almost always
Reduce the pain but keep in mind that can be
Physical reasons why that could that pain can be there
Sue W. Thank you for the super check can Venus stasis and autoimmune neuropathy heal on carnivore three months in having oxillate dumping lots of pain suggestions
Chaffee: autoimmune yes absolutely I mean you're damaging the nerves if the nerves are damaged then
They could be permanently damaged and and that pain can still be there
But it it should reduce the amount of pain that you have or by reducing the information expression of that pain
Giving your ketones up by eating a lot of fat that can further reduce and suppress inflammation
Because high ketones directly suppress
Implamation as well
Oxillate dumping can cause pain oxillate double can cause nerve pain cause joint pain can cause
Edics and other sorts of things as well so you might have to sort of get through that if it's
Too much of a bother you can try saline orton's
Protocols about a very low amount of oxillates like a bit of lemon in your water or a bit of
You know weak tea
Chaffee: Where you will have to just a bit of oxillates, you know less than a hundred milligrams a day you can look these up and how much these things have
You know about 50 to a hundred milligrams tops and
per day and then
That can sort of suppress the oxillate dumping if that's actually indeed what's happening
Chaffee: Part of tests for that. We don't we don't have a test to show that your oxillate dumping is just sort of
us
It's a clinical diagnosis sort of things, you know, and
So
Chaffee: But it can help these sorts of things Venus stages depend on what's causing that
But it can help with a lot of
Issues with circulation certainly help with auto immunity
Then the neuropathy and the damage that's happened from that
I have to see how much of that heals, but you're at least give your body a chance to heal
And then keep that in mind for the oxillate dumping
Hopefully things have gotten better though. Hopefully the pain even though it's severe is it at least better than it was before
You switch to this way of eating all to there are other benefits as well focus on those good things and that can help you
You know weather things until your body heals and nothing gets the rest of the problems out as much as they can
So good luck with that. I hope it gets better soon
Jason Warley. Thank you for the super chat
How about healing neurological disorders for example
adrenal lukodisc
Chaffee: Trophy uh with spasticity and build up of long chain fatty acids in the in the body symptoms
Very good question neurological disorders in general can
Be helped. I mean we have studies showing that
High fat meat-based ketogenic diets like a carnivore diet. Remember ketogenic diets are all animal-based high fat animal-based diets
And a carnivore diet is a high fat animal-based ketogenic diet so anything any studies that talking about the
Benefits of a ketogenic diet apply to a carnivore diet that is ketogenic so you're not having
fruit or honey or those sorts of a lot of milk things like that
So I don't know specifically for that
Chaffee: I haven't really seen that
Chaffee: I have seen pretty remarkable things with people that have had old strokes or even spinal cord
severe spinal cord damage and
Paraplegia or quadruplegia
Chaffee: with spasticity or cerebral palsy with spasticity improve their spasticity improve some
neurological findings is absolutely incredible so how much of that don't know but it can
It can it can seriously
Improve a lot of these sorts of things so it just depends
A lot of these sort of
Chaffee: Issues they they've caused damage to the body damage the neurological system and it's just a matter of
You know how how much healing the body can do and so it's um it just sort of some of those things that you just have to sort of
wait and see but a lot of things yeah it does help with a lot of a lot of neurological issues absolutely
I mean look at look at my interview with Dave Mack he wrote he improved his symptoms from a stroke from a
30-year-old stroke after two months on a carnivore diet right he'd done ketone icons before that it didn't
change anything just going carnivore
Two months he was walking normally and didn't have as much weakness nearly as much as weakness there's just sort of normal
Wasn't quite as strong as the left side
But it was you know right right side of weakness previously but
He it is basically functionally normal now
Excuse me and
And so you know that that's remarkable so
We don't know everything that it can do but
We're still learning and definitely it can heal a lot of
neurological issues so
Chaffee: It'll at least put you in a position that your body can heal from as much of it as it can
And hopefully stop it from getting worse
Chaffee: Robby Waller thank you for the super chat my sister's 46 was diagnosed with early onset Alzheimer's Jesus
Chaffee: I mean what this was this never existed even in the elderly population and we're saying no no no
Chaffee: It's totally normal blah blah blah
Explained 46 rules then
These these people piss me off by by dismissing this oh yeah, yeah, it just happens know it
damn well doesn't it's not supposed to and
You know now we're now we're getting people in their 40s getting Alzheimer's this is just
infuriating to me and
Chaffee: I normally swear a lot so I hope you people will realize just how much self control that I exert in these videos because I normally
Chaffee: So we're a lot I've rugby players on my team that would be like K. O. Chay, if you can you just
Chaffee: Tone down the swearing a bit. I mean that's like having a long short amount of telling you you swear too much
So I hope you guys appreciate that because
normally I'd I'd be
There'd be a lot of expletives involved in in reading something like this
However, she chose to do the Mediterranean diet what are your thoughts on our recommendations
Chaffee: Well look I mean she's making conscious decisions to improve her her diet and and make up you know positive impact on her health
So that's already great and so you know doing Mediterranean diet as long as she's doing
I mean look at the sardinians like they almost essentially all meet with a bit of olives and tomatoes and that's it
Look at my video on the blue zones with
Dr. Bill Shimler he did a research trip out to sardinia to the epicenter of the first blue zone and actually saw no
They're not plant-based. They're not vegetarian. They don't eat meat once a week. They eat meat all day every day with a lot of dairy and
So you know that's just a flat out lie by damn mutner. He's a liar. I'll say that publicly. He's a liar
Please try to sue me. I'll sue you back your a liar. You made this shit up
You know because he went there and and Bill Shimler talked spoke to the same people that that butner spoke to and they said
Chaffee: Why does everyone say we're vegetarian? What the hell? Where the hell did they get that from we meet every day?
So he's a liar and
And he's a seven-day dentist. He's got a he's got a ideological
bone to pick with the way everybody eats
Chaffee: But Saturday that just church bought the blue zone rights for like something like 68 million dollars
This is a con these are liars and con artists and they are they are doing things that hurt people and so that bothers me
So she's doing a real Mediterranean diet. You know the way that sardinians actually
Great
But look the main thing is she's making a conscious effort to improve her health
Like the hood, she's going to be cutting out a bunch of processed foods and garbage
Seedles and sugars and buying carbs. So that's already really good
Chaffee: If you can get her to go key to genic that's even better. I have videos on Alzheimer's
Dimension living to past 120 I think it's called and where I talk about this there are studies again
These these studies with ketogenic diets are thousands of high-level randomized control trials in ketogenic diets
Showing specific with specific health outcomes showing improvement
A high-fat meat-based ketogenic diet
Like the real Mediterranean diet the sardinians
That has been shown to be a better treatment for Alzheimer's than every medication ever trial
Right so you really want to get rid of the carbs. So eat meat. The fatty meat the brain is made out of that
Chaffee: And so it's made out of cholesterol as well right and we're we're working as hard as we can to lower our cholesterol and
Chaffee: Your brains made out of cholesterol and there are studies showing that people have had and certainly case reports of
People that had Alzheimer's and they were on statins
Chaffee: Stats can cross the blood brain barrier and and stop your brain for making the cholesterol that it uses to build your brain
Right are we insane
Chaffee: Right, that doesn't get into your blood stream. That doesn't cross the blood brain barrier back the other way
It's just being used for the for the building materials of your brain most likely
There may be mechanisms they can cross back and forth
But it makes it in your brain so your brain can use it in your brain for your brain
And we're giving drugs that reduce that stop your brain for me able to make cholesterol
Which is how you violate your axons and your nerves and so you can get brain shrinkage
You can get damage and you can get insulin resistance so glucose count can't feed the brain
Chaffee: Properly and you see this on pet scans where the glucose is is reduced the signal is reduced in the cortex of the brain with people with all
timer so you go into ketosis ketones don't have that problem
Brain brain wakes up right and then those ketones can actually reform in a fatty acids
Which can then be used to rebuild the structures of the brain the cholesterol can rebuild the structures of the brain as well
needs to has to be there
And so there's these these in the published literature
Chaffee: They found these people that had Alzheimer's on these statins. They removed the statins six weeks later
Chaffee: Wouldn't you know they didn't have Alzheimer's anymore?
Put them back on the statins
Funny enough they got Alzheimer's again
Isn't that funny you know it's almost as if they're related so
Sorry for the bit of the rant, but I mean this is this is that doesn't need that should never have happened to your sister
That should this is not be something that we're dealing with at all no one should have to deal with this right now
We have been tricked and controlled and fooled in eating things that are horrible for us because we think they're good for us
And it is causing serious disease and harm and it never existed in any in any real form in humans before
You know 100 years ago 120 years ago. This is
This is a man-made disease and it is devastating so
But
Is is if we're causing it we can also
Undo the cause and and hopefully
You can get a lot of improvement from your sister and I would expect she will get a lot of improvement if she's able to go
High-fat keto even if it's not full of carnivore just get rid of the carbs had in meat and fat and
You know
Keep cholesterol in the brain because the brain needs cholesterol. Okay good luck with that good luck to her
And damn butner's a liar
Dark sky. Thank you for the super chat
Could caffeine make autoimmune diseases worse
potentially
It is a neurotoxin. It's an insecticide that plants makes it to to fry the brains of insects
They're trying to eat it so it's not it's not there to help you it is there to hurt you if it
If you like the effects that's that's a
You know that's that's not the original intention so
You know
To see how you go I mean I if with any autoimmune disease I would just cut out absolutely everything from plants
I would cut out everything except red meat really
Chaffee: I would I wouldn't be surprised if caffeine did but I don't know specifically if it does one way or the other
You can always try caffeine coffee will coffee definitely will tea definitely will
Make autoimmune diseases worse but if you take this a caffeine pill
Maybe you can you try it out and see for yourself but I would just sort of avoid it on principle really
Pete thank you very much for the super chat
Hi Dr. Chafi. I lost
Something so maybe there's something else here Pete
Okay, so I think I think I think I may have lost some of your of your message
Chaffee: But say life's otherwise good. I do line diet on mad 99% with occasional cheese
And cream only one socializing how do I stop the weight or belly fat gain? Thank you for all that you do is in another one here
Not that I'm seeing so sorry Pete. I'm not seeing your other part of that question
But
Sounds like you're doing good doing line diet
occasional cheese and cream fair enough
And you're saying you're sort of building up belly fat or maybe not losing it as much
It's hard to know but it looks like stop belly fat
Weight gain
So you need your dress things like sleep and stress those are major months, especially with a belly
You know the the interbdominal fat is is is is a very
Sensitive to cortisol so you raise your cortisol because you're stressed out because you're not sleeping well
You're you're going to not only retain belly fat, but you're going to grow your belly fat
And so you need to you need to address that as well. Um, if you
If you get four to five hours on average of sleep a night for for a week
Seven days you'll actually give yourself diabetes, right? So not good because of how how much that cortisol affects you stress will do that too
If you average seven to eight hours of sleep for the next seven days, you can reverse that
So really optimize and prioritize your sleep
I try to prioritize your and optimize your stress levels and de-stressing as well very important things
Stress is stress, you know, we we all sort of face it, but you have to try to do things that just make you happy
And de-stress every day and try to get yourself into a situation that's that's more conducive to your your stress levels
And mental health being being benefit of that so and then just give a time
You know, there are reasons hormonally and otherwise that that can be a problem if you're on medications that can also be a problem
occasional dairy
You know
Probably not that big of a deal, but you know, you're just
Get rid of everything and you're going to be better off
And
Exercise as well lifting weights
Doing sprints if you can even on a stationary bicycle
That can be very very beneficial and I think can stimulate fat loss and especially belly fat loss
Chronic cardio the other way around that can actually raise your cortisol
So doing like just long-term stuff on the treadmill or going for long jogs or whatever
That can actually raise your cortisol and make it make this
That loss a bit more stubborn
Sprinting does the opposite just melts away belly fat and interagomal fat in particular
So that's what I would do. I'd add in those sorts of exercises the resistance training the anaerobic training
Chaffee: And high intensity really try to work you know work yourself
very hard within you know safety
reasonable
amount so that you're not hurting yourself
Chaffee: But you know challenge yourself make yourself work really hard and you know you'll get there just keep going with it and
Chaffee: Cut out everything all artificial sweeteners everything like that sounds like you are but just some of these things sneak in
You know stevia month root sugar even things like on the electrolytes of people supplement with they have artificial sweeteners in a lot of them
So just don't take those ones and
And just keep going with it. You'll do fine again some people just take a bit longer
Because of their hormones and other sorts of reasons to lose weight, but you'll get there just optimize all those things and keep going you'll do great
Chaffee: Superfluity of
Chaffee: Notiness whatever that means so
Chaffee: Thank you for the super chat. Can you give a refresher on the efficacy of alleged health benefits of fiber
Chaffee: Also, you will insoluble
Chaffee: Manicated carnivore
beautifies food in your gut. Yeah, so the thing is is that
Chaffee: Can't put you to find your gut if it doesn't get to your lower gut right because you're absorbing 98 to 99 to even a hundred percent of the meat that you're eating
If you cut out the gristle of the of the meat and you just eat the fat
Soft fat and the soft muscle
None of it none of it's getting down to your lower intestine and to where the bacteria are in the first place, right?
So
Camp future five what does future five is the fiber because you can't break down fiber
You can't absorb fiber. It has to go out the other end
Chaffee: So it necessarily has to go to your lower intestine because it's a one-way one-way tube and
Chaffee: And that's where the fiber goes and then the bacteria work on it and future flies it and and
You know, and that that's what that's what's getting future five now if you're eating fiber and you're eating food
Plants that have anti-nutrients that block the absorption and digestion of meat
Chaffee: Okay, yeah, then that can get down to your lower intestine and then the bacteria can work on that
Chaffee: But that's the plants fault that's fibers fault fiber causes that it doesn't help that
meat you absorb all of it nearly and
As long as you're not eating it with fiber and other anti-nutrients that that delay or block absorption
So yeah, and
But yeah, fiber you don't need it. You don't want it. No animal on earth
Each fiber unless they can break it down and get something out of it. We can't
70% of all animal species are carnivores none of them eat fiber in order to be able to defecate or for any other health benefits
It's not necessary it can cause harm and delay up to 30% absorption of the food you're eating
If you're eating high to octane crap, then that might be good
Chaffee: You're going to absorb less carbs. You're going to absorb less sugar. You're going to absorb less of the other garbage because it's a physical barrier and and disrupts your absorption
That's not good if you're eating things that are just good for you, right? So yeah, so that's a short answer
Chaffee: I have a video on fiber conservation and diet the people can watch also Zoey Harkham's
Video what about fiber is excellent as is Dr. Paul Mason's
Video from fiber to the microbiome excellent. They're both excellent and they don't even
Chaffee: They have they're both very complementary to each other. They don't just say the same things all all three of those don't say the same things
Chaffee: They're all sort of looking at it from slightly different angles and talking about it in different ways
Minds more practical on how to you know avoid constipation and all that sort of stuff on carnivore eat more fat and
And how you don't have to have fiber and all these other sorts of things
Those are excellent Zoey Harkham and Paul Mason's especially the fantastic so I will watch those
Chaffee: Richard Bishop. Thank you for the super chat is a carnivore diet safe for an older person who has damaged
Chaffee: liver from Advil and Tylenol
Thank you for being so generous with your time. Oh 100% and it and first won't get the hell off those things
Second of all, you know, this can reduce your pain so you don't need to take those things anymore
Advil tends to damage the kidneys Tylenol tends to damage the little will damage the liver
The combination will really damage your kidneys. So you number one to take those together for more than five days in a row ever and
But you body can heal from a lot of these things
If you have cirrhosis and permanent damage, that's permanent but the rest of the liver
And the kidneys that are that are not permanently damaged can
Certainly heal and get better and
Yes, it's actually most important for people that are that are having a health issues because you just don't have as much of a threshold to get
To fix yourself
You know, so you have to be very careful with that. So yes, the optimal diet
is important
Chaffee: And so hello Ellie Millie and she says that hugs help reduce his stress as well. That's very good point
And yeah, it was some of the was saying that the other day that we watched it like a 20 second hug
Release his oxytocin a six second or longer kiss
Reduce
Send the oxytocin and presumably help stress levels as well. So that's that's nice too
Chaffee: And and and she sent a very nice super sticker. You don't have to keep doing that. That's very nice of you
Very very sweet of you. Thank you. Nice to see you
Um, okay
Steve
573v3
Chaffee: Thank you for the super chat. Some say Dr. JP is making stuff up by saying Brussels sprouts have 130 plus known human carcinogens
Chaffee: What other sources? Yeah, that's just for my my class in
Cancer biology. So that was that was direct from
the professor of cancer biology and and I say that and I preface that
And everything I say like this is what we were taught in that in that class in cancer biology
So that's that's the source who take it take it or leave it
You know there are there are always a finest out it's super hard. It's just it's just
Chaffee: Drenched in the
Chaffee: You know and and buried in the literature in a lot of places you can see like the Bruce Aims
Paper they found 42 different toxins
Chaffee: 20 of which were shown to be carcinogenic. So what I mean, this is a fact
You know, they do have carcinogens in them you look on the WHO website. They just
Flat out say these different plant toxins can be mutagenic carcinogenic lethal
And and these are in the foods that we eat and so we have to be careful about that
So it's not me making that up the 136 specific
Carcinogens that was from my class in cancer biology
So you know
Take it or leave it, but you know, there are other places that that do a numerate out different sorts of things
And that's just but I always I always preface that you know by saying this is what was taught to me in class
Chaffee: You say the same thing you know you learn something in anthropology class and this and that and or whatever
You know that's just what you know people learn things in school and I learned that in school
So that's that's my was the source was my professor of cancer biology at the University of Washington in Seattle in the early 2000s
And so there may be even more than 136 identified now
But you know a lot of books on botany and biology they they they cover the sort of stuff
You know, so you can take a look at that as well
Jill kitchen thank you for the super chat question. I am only five feet tall
But obviously in a amount of weight to lose do I need to pay attention to calories
No weight loss yet so I'm a bit worried
No, I don't think so I think you just need to just focus on just pure meat and water
You need the fat you know you don't want to if you're chronically under eating your body's going to actually lower your metabolism
Check your leptin check your fasting insulin check these sorts of things your your metabolism can be
Pretty botched up and that can make you very difficult and slow to lose weight
Check your thyroid as well there are reasons that these this can happen slowly a lot of people
We'll lose weight right away not everybody does so just just be mindful of that. It's a process you focus on your health
First
Chaffee: Watch my interview with Kelli Hogan watch a lot of interviews with Kelli Hogan
She had this too. She didn't she let she gained weight for six months
But her health was improving. She felt better and then her weight started coming off so it does take time for some people
And watch watch Kelli Hogan stuff for that. She did a video with Charles Washington about people that are
Slow to lose weight and they talked about that on her channel so take a look at that as well
Low carb low drama. Thank you very much for the generous super chat. I appreciate it
Hi Dr. Chaffee was the best diet for one year old
New treatment requirements et cetera. Thank you for all you do well. It's the same
Chaffee: Neutron requirements for the rest of us mammals drink their mothers milk and then they're weined on to their mothers diet and they eat that diet
For the rest of their life and then they wind their children off to that diet as well for us that's fatty meat
So you can start off by by giving them just the meat juices from like a roast or a steak or something like that
Give them a little spoonfuls of that you'll see their eyes go. Oh, that's good because it wants those nutrients a lot of iron and
And he might earn a lot of other really good nutrients in there
That they'll that they'll want and they'll they'll desire
So fatty bread meat
That's that's what they should eat you know
There's different there's different
discussions on how to do that whether you give them a much bigger piece
Then they could ever choke on and so they're just sort of knowing things off and got a couple teeth
They're just going to be able to scrape off just a bit of that meat that's enough that's appropriate for them
And they can eat that that's going to help their jaw work and their teeth form and their and their jaws form as well
And that's going to be better for their
Facial structure a little development or jaw development or teeth development as well and certainly get the nutrients you want so fatty meat
Chaffee: Same thing that we all need is just fatty meat and you can sort of you know puree it if you want but you know they need to chew you know that chewing action helps
Develop the jaw and the palate as well and they'll have
much stronger a much broader airways and they won't have
All the breathing issues that that we have as a mainstay now. I think that's what's the same stuff
Chaffee: So it's the same thing that you eat, you know, they can eat too and they're they're much more sensitive
Chaffee: You try to give them a piece of broccoli. They will just just be horrified and so don't just give them give them something that
It's good for them, you know, fatty meat and they need a lot of fat and the meat as well because they their brains are growing
They need to be in ketosis
Because your brain grows optimally in ketosis because of the ketones are better for your brain
And they also reconstitute in the fatty acids help grow your brain
fetuses are in ketosis nursing babies are in ketosis even though there's lactose
And so it's only when we don't be in a bunch of sugary crap when they they are
Chaffee: Formally low or baby food that they kick out of ketosis and they're eating super soft
Chaffee: Mushy crap their jaw don't develop their their teeth don't develop properly their airways don't develop properly. It's really bad for them
so
Don't do that and
They'll do great
Jewels and just and thank you very much for the super chat
Passing A1 C is 5.3 glucose 4.9 insulin is 10 deficient vitamin C dizzy in in the morning causing cortisol rush
Well vitamin C supplement help insulin cortisol and sleep
B flam butter eggs and water. Thank you for being a great teacher
You know my vitamin C was undetectable and
That don't have scurvy. So the amount of vitamin C that you need is
Radically reduced when you're on a cardamor diet
And you won't get scurvy because you scurvy is a misdevelopment of collagen and so
it
It's it's it's required when you don't have
But the appropriate building blocks for collagen. You need to make them to know what you need to make them from scratch
By hydrolyzing proline and lysine and so vitamin C is necessary to
Hydrolyze proline and lysine you get the pre-hydrolyzed forms when you eat meat
It's just when you're eating plants
That you need that you need and you're not getting enough from the meat that you need
Vitamin C to make that stuff
So
You don't need that now the caveat being with my vitamin C being
Undetectable is that I was drinking milk for like three days leading up to the test and
Carbohydrates even in from lactose will block that out and will block out the absorption of vitamin C
So
Chaffee: You know there is vitamin C in meat. There's actually more vitamin C in a gram of and program of liver
Chaffee: Then there is a program of apples
Right so there's plenty of vitamin C
You don't need it if you want to take some vitamin C. I wouldn't take too much you know like you know
500 milligrams max the day you just don't need as much
I don't think that it's gonna
necessarily change much to do with your cortisol or anything else but
Chaffee: If you want to try it and you want to see if it makes you feel better and you don't go for it
Chaffee: As long as you're not taking too much you're excessive vitamin C actually turns into oxillates in your body and you can actually get oxillite problem
So just be mindful of that as well
Chaffee: Westfield. Thank you very much for the super sticker. I appreciate that
Chaffee: Low carb low drama. Thank you for the super chat watching your live Q&A on my iPad while walking around Singapore airport
Earlier this week was exhilarating. Thank you for making a possible well. Thank you very much. I appreciate that and that's and that's fun
That's your well the people are really care or what I have to say
And that they're finding it useful and helpful. So thank you very much for that
Chaffee: Jason Moreley. Thank you very much for the the very generous super chat. I appreciate that
What your thoughts on carnivore healing exhale D
adrenal ducodot
dystrophia with symptoms such as
Chaffee: Fastestity low cortisol and
Chaffee: very long chain fatty acid build up too high of fat like 80% makes me dizzy
Chaffee: So I think he's going back to the other one just just remember everybody that there is a bit of a delay between when I
Get a question when I can answer a question
Because it takes me longer to answer a question than it takes people to write them and so there's a there's a backlog
But I do I do get to all the super chats especially and I try to do the other ones too
Chaffee: So I sort of answered this before but also just add on to that you know if you are
Chaffee: If you're getting a certain amount of fat and that's making you dizzy or giving you some sort of symptoms
Chaffee: You're just don't eat that much. That's fine
Generally eating more fat than your body can absorb you just
Excreate it and you can get diarrhea
It usually doesn't affect you physically otherwise except for the the loose stools
So that's interesting that that makes you dizzy. That's that's something I haven't heard of before
Chaffee: Generally you just physically can't absorb it so it's not gonna get in your body unless you're taking things like oxbile and then you'll force it to go in your body
So don't do that
Just eat the amount of fat that's right for your body. So you think the amount of fat that that gets you
soft stools but not loose stools and
and enough
Meet as well being any sort of state of ketosis and carnivore can actually
Chaffee: Optimize your cortisol as well as your other hormones so people with metabolic syndrome
Chaffee: Actually tend to have low cortisol two low of cortisol and
Not can reverse by putting people on a carnivore diet. He degenerate that because that reverses the metabolic syndrome
And their cortisol comes up slightly
Chaffee: But then people say oh my god is coming up too hot? No, no, no, it comes up but it doesn't come up to
Cushing's disease levels. It comes up to normal physiological levels and so and then it stays there it doesn't just keep keep keep keep going up
So it can't help with that
Could potentially help with the spasticity as well
As I mentioned with people with stroke and and all of that
Um
Chaffee: And then we have a couple of superstakers from Oz Gal very very nice of you. Thank you very much for that
And Nick Johnson who's
Very kind to to send the superstakers as well
And
So I think I just done then of course my little Ellie Milley
We send very nice super sticker. Thank you very very much for that
Chaffee: All right everyone. I think I have to stop there that that's all the super chat. So I'm glad I got through all those
But it's 1115 and I was supposed to stop at 11. So I need to I need to hop off
And get to my appointment and get to work and
And then I've got a seminar actually tomorrow here in Perth
Where I'm giving another top revenue
Intake for patients a new patient intake seminar
Tomorrow so for people going to that
We'll see you there and
Otherwise I will see you all next week for my premiere of the new episode on
Sunday Monday Sunday in America Monday here and then the the next live which will be my Wednesday
America's Tuesday
So
Chaffee: Thank you all very much. Thank you very much Al for for watching as usual. Thank you very much
Melissa and Rick and Darvett and all the other mods for helping out
Always great to have you guys help out and certainly better than it was before when
There's a bit of chaos and weirdness on the jazz and we didn't have mods
So thank you very much is very very nice of you to help out. I really appreciate you all and
Big round of applause for the moderator. Thank you
So thank you very much
We'll see you again soon. I'm also releasing another video tomorrow with my friend
Tyler from the the big the
Roddevoo city round up so the beef beef round up in Wyoming that I went to last year
Chaffee: Which was awesome. I had a great time there. I just just Wyoming was gorgeous for people
You know this is where yellowstone is where the T-tons are it's absolutely stunning country
You know it's it's a very large state in America and it has like 300,000 people
It's like things like the third largest state something something massive. They big state and it's
It's it's one of the least populous. So it is just gorgeous pristine wilderness and
Chaffee: So Ellen I went there last year. We're going again this year in end of August. It's like August
24th I think is that is that weekend
It's amazing and so it's trying to make it like a big carnivore event and
And they've sort of they're actually officially renaming their town
They're not renaming it, but they're so their town motto is going to be officially
Set as the most carnivore friendly city in the world
Which has got a cool so that's riverton
Wyoming that's going to be so I was staying more towards we were staying more towards the T-tons in the national parks by
Sort of like an hour or so outside of of Jackson Hole
Which cool little town and that's like sort of an hour or two
Sort of yeah probably around two hours to riverton
Sort of drove over there stayed there for a bit and then went back
And stayed out by the
Chaffee: The national parks and then then drove around and and just saw a lot of really cool stuff
Chaffee: The national parks which was really really amazing so people want to go to that
It's fantastic go to
beefroundup.com
And I think that the website's being built, but you know just you know
What we'll talk about it more in that that video is going to be released tomorrow
And the Rosalind stop talking and go play for your appointment. I'll be fine. Thank you
But thank you good to see you Rosalind. That's my sister for people that it don't know
some areas in very sweet sister very nice sister. So thank you. I appreciate it
But yes, so that'll come out tomorrow and people can check that out
But it'll be a lot of fun and people like Dr. Sean Omar
Courtney Luna
from Life like Jake and my friend Simon Lewis who does the how to carnivore with me
and Dr. Lisa Weidman who's been a you know carnivore
Chaffee: ophthalmologist for 15 years or so and
Chaffee: So be there as well and I'll be having her on my podcast too. I was just on hers and I'll have her on as well. She's great. So
Yeah, so be a lot of fun and
And they're trying to make it like a big
Carnivore event every year and it's worth going
Because it's a awesome part of the country and Rosalind if you're still here
Talk to mom and dad about this. I'm trying to get them out last year and it's just sort of a bit to last minute
But maybe we can fly them out there and and have and go for a
Drive through Yellowstone because that's that's always fun. That's something that my parents have wanted to do
Okay, thank you all very much. It's been a pleasure
Love you all see you later