Okay, hi, everybody, we're live here.
Jeff, the prosperous from blessings on my journey.
And it's an absolute honor to have Dr. Anthony Shafi.
Good day, Dr. Shafi.
Hey, thanks for having me, man.
I'm good to see you.
Yeah, you too.
And I want to apologize to you to all your subscribers,
to my subscribers.
I had huge technical difficulty this morning.
It's like eight, 45 now,
and we were supposed to start 45 minutes ago.
So I'm really sorry to everybody,
so I just want to start with that.
I just want to say, Dr. Shafi,
this is my fourth time on with you.
So I want to thank you again for making time for me.
I think, actually, to be honest with you, Dr. Shafi,
I think it's been about five times,
because if I include the 24 hour live event
we're a carry band showed my video and you addressed me.
That was the first time really.
And then we did one with carry.
We did one with you and me just recently.
It came out on your podcast.
And we did one with, I believe, JT from Polka Moonshine.
It was the one about youth in carnivore.
So we've done a few.
So thank you very much.
Yeah, no problem, man.
So it was a pleasure.
And it's always great to see you and carry everything
that you guys are doing and getting the word out there.
It's just growing and growing and growing.
And getting more people excited about it, which is great.
And my subscribers were all tuning in now.
They're all saying hi.
So thank you.
I just wanted to say to everybody that's tuned in.
I just want to introduce myself and Dr. Shafi's going
to introduce himself.
And I want to also introduce talk about us as athletes
our little history, just a brief one.
And then we'll start fielding questions kind of.
Is that sound good?
Dr. Shafi?
Yeah, yeah, sounds good.
OK, and I just want to do one quick thing,
because I kind of had this plan.
My two sons, Peter, and Dante, let me see here.
They were going to be on with us today,
because it's about athletes.
But anyone can see in the background there,
there is the footy pitch and Peter and Dante are on there
right now.
And they're training from 8 a.m. till 10 a.m.
Chaffee: And they do that every Saturday and Sunday,
Chaffee: with this trainer, Ian McClerg, here in Ontario.
He's from the UK.
And my sons have been training with him for about five, six years.
So they are kind of part of this today.
So I just wanted to show them and show the audience
and everybody that.
Today's topic, everyone, is carnivore for athletes and youth.
And I'm just going to quickly introduce myself.
And then I'll pass on you, Dr. Shafi,
to introduce yourself to my audience.
And to everybody.
My name is Jeff, everybody.
And I started a YouTube channel back in September,
because I've been on a journey.
And my new journey, my new mantra is to be cancer-free.
But today, I'm not going to be talking about how I have
stage four cool and cancer, because I've done many calls on that.
I want today to be different with Dr. Shafi.
I want to talk about carnivore, because I've had a lot of success.
I've been a carnivore for 20 months now.
And I've had a lot of success in terms of my own health
getting better.
And I am a high school phys ed teacher.
I have been for 21 years in my hometown
in Brantford, Ontario.
And I coach many, many sports.
I played varsity soccer for two universities here
in Ontario, Wilford, Laurier, and Brock University.
I had a lot of success as an athlete.
And I'm enjoying working with youth for the past 21 years,
coaching them and teaching them when it comes to phys ed sports
and nutrition.
So that's just a quick brief introduction
about myself, Dr. Shafi.
If you don't mind taking over and introducing
and telling me, tell everybody your credentials,
because it's pretty awesome.
Yeah, well, thanks.
Yeah, so my name's Dr. Anthony Chafi.
I'm an American physician.
I work in Australia at the moment.
Currently, in my residency for neurosurgery,
I also have a private practice in functional medicine,
metabolic health, sometimes called preventative medicine.
But same things you can do to prevent diseases,
you can do to reverse them.
And so we have a lot of patients with formally
Chaffee: with diabetes and obesity and autoimmune issues
Chaffee: and all sorts of other weird, wild and wonderful things
that are doing much better now,
because we address things at a root cause level,
which sort of ties into all my work online
in the carnivore diet, because something I've realized
as a physician, one of the most powerful tools
Chaffee: that we can use are dietary interventions.
Chaffee: You're eating the way we're supposed to eat
Chaffee: and design eat biologically,
is one of the strongest things you can do
to heal disease.
As Hapakridi said, 2,500 years ago,
Chaffee: before you heal anyone, first ask them
Chaffee: if they're willing to give up what is making them sick.
And that is so true today,
because everything that we're doing is what
is making us sick.
We're not sick because our bodies are just failing
and they're just cracking out and they're just breaking down
because we're deep, flunked species
and that's just how we're designed and made,
that's completely false.
We're designed to be extremely healthy
and we're built to be a very healthy
and animals are all very healthy.
Humans are supposed to be healthy.
So that's the idea is getting people back
to their natural state of health
and that's why I use the carnivore diet for it.
So I've been studying diet nutrition
for over 25 years.
I've been practicing as a doctor for 11 years
taking some breaks, doing humanitarian work here and there
and back at it, seeing patients full of time now.
And I played sports since I was a kid.
I trained in MMA at one of the top gyms in America.
They MCK boxing in Washington State with Matt Hume.
Since I was 14, I was there sort of every day
until I was 18 or so and I started playing rugby.
I was an all-American.
I started focusing mainly on that.
I played professionally for 10 years before medical school
and then kept playing throughout medical school
and beyond as well.
And so that has been a huge benefit to me as well,
especially because five years of those,
10 years I was on a carnivore diet
and I felt like I absolutely super hero.
And then the latter five years more experience
of older, I'm bigger, I'm stronger.
I should be better, but I wasn't anything close
to how dynamic and explosive and athletic that I was
in my first five years in my 20s.
So it's massive difference.
And now that I'm in my 40s,
I feel like I'm in my 20s again.
I feel like I'm in my early 20s
because I'm eating the way I did my early 20s.
I feel better now at 44 than I did at 28
playing professional rugby or 26, 27.
Chaffee: I just felt better than from 25 to 38.
Chaffee: I feel better now than I did that whole chunk of time.
So just trying to pass it along to people
and you know, show them the science behind it
that this works, it's not just a one-off
Chaffee: or a two-off or a one million off.
Chaffee: There's millions of people doing this now
Chaffee: and finding the same results.
But there's a reason for that
because it actually works.
Awesome.
Thank you, Dr. Shafi.
And I just want to say that all my subscribers
and Dr. Shafi subscribers,
if you could just hold off another about five to 10 minutes
for the questions because there are a few things
I want to talk to Dr. Shafi about.
And when we do start field in questions,
if you can put QQQ,
Dr. Shafi is that what you have your subscribers do?
Yeah, yeah, that's just make it obvious
that it's a question and we'll try to catch it.
Great. So thank you for the interaction, Dr. Shafi.
I just want you spoke about your credentials.
You spoke about your professional rugby,
your MMA training, everything that's great.
You have such an athletic history.
I want to make sure everybody understands that.
This gentleman that I'm honored to be on here with today.
He does brain surgeries during the day.
He works out, he's an athlete.
We're going to learn a lot here today.
And I'm hoping, Dr. Shafi,
because we start a late, do we still have an hour?
Can we go to about, I would say, 945 East, Eastern, is that okay?
Sure, that's fine.
Okay, that's great.
So before we get going and talk in a more questions,
I just want to say a little bit about my past.
I did talk about me playing University soccer,
but I grew up playing all sports.
From a young age, my dad got me in soccer at five years old.
And I ventured into also playing a lot of competitive basketball.
I wasn't, I didn't have the stature, the height for it.
Maybe if I was carnivore as a kid, I might have grown a few more inches.
But I got to about 5, 9, 5, 10.
And I was a point guard in high school.
I was running back in high school for football.
I played rugby actually as well.
I had an opportunity to go over to Ireland when I was in my last year high school.
And we did a little tour over there.
So, and then I went off the university medical university soccer.
So, I have quite a bit of experience.
And I just want to say, I always knew the power of meat
when it comes to giving you strength and energy
and repairing your muscles as well.
Especially growing up in an Italian culture household.
My mom always cooked very Mediterranean style,
but good fresh meat all the time.
And she knew the importance of it.
I grew up being a little bit obsessed with athletes, professional athletes.
Just like I am obsessed with you, Dr. Shafi, and all the doctors on YouTube right now,
because I'm on a different journey right now in my life.
But I grew up being obsessed with someone like Michael Jordan.
Michael Jordan was my biggest hero.
And obviously, from my hometown,
Bramford, Ontario, Wayne Gresky.
And now, in the soccer world, Lionel Messi and Cristiano Ronaldo.
So, I was watching something online a few days ago about Michael Jordan.
And I knew this about him.
His pre-game meal was always a steak.
Always a steak steak steak.
And I guess he had a side of potatoes.
Wayne Gresky did the exact same thing.
And Lionel Messi, every single big soccer competition,
he gets hundreds of pounds of meat delivered to wherever he is,
so that he's performing.
So, I just want to say, and driving here this morning to my son's soccer training,
we listen to motivational speakers all the time.
And this morning, we were listening to Kobe Bryant.
Because Kobe Bryant is quite motivational when it comes to improving oneself.
And he talks about the bamba mentality,
and he talks about how you want to be the best version of yourself,
and improving yourself day to day.
So, I just wanted to say, that's one way we can encourage our youth
and our athletes having role models and seeing what they've done,
especially when it comes to diet, when it comes to the carnivore diet,
Michael Jordan, always having a steak before every single meal.
Kobe Bryant saying that we need to improve day to day and be the best version of our self.
So, this is why I'm saying, this topic today, it's true to my heart
in terms of working with athletes, working with youth as an educator.
And, you know, I think that's where we're going to go with today,
Dr. Shafi, is that sound good? Sounds good? Awesome.
So, I just take a look at my agenda here quickly.
I've talked about my past, you talked about your past.
Athletes today, Dr. Shafi, can you explain
where they're getting their energy from? And,
I know there's three different macro nutrients, and maybe we can explain to the audience the options
that athletes have when it comes to energy and performing. Is that sound right?
Sure. Yeah. Well, so, I mean, one, a lot of people, most people,
are getting their energy from carbohydrates. We've been told for the last 40, 50 years that
Chaffee: we have to eat carbs in order to burn carbs. Even the, the golden era bodybuilders like
Chaffee: Vince Garanda, who's a steak and egg steak and egg steak and eggs are like that's what we're
supposed to be eating. That's what humans have been eating forever. That's what we're supposed to eat.
Even he thought that you needed to do a carb day once a week, because he said,
you need to replenish the glycogen in your liver and the only way to do that is eating carbs.
I saw that. That was a quote of his. That's not the case. You know, that's not the case.
They may have been what they understood at the time. That's not true. In fact, there have been
studies in athletes, in humans, showing that ketogenic athletes replenish their muscle and
liver glycogen faster than carb-fueled athletes drinking sugar water like gatorate, right?
So, you know, it's not only can you do it, you can do it better naturally on your own.
Chaffee: So, at the moment, everyone's just sucking down sugar and sugar water and sugar pills and
Chaffee: you know, gatorate became this whole big thing. The original gatorate was just electrolytes.
Chaffee: It didn't have just a ton of sugar. Now, it's all sugar. It's barely any electrolytes.
And that's what people, people run on. They think you have to have all these carbs,
Chaffee: all these carbs, all these sorts of things, which is not the case. I'm sure you experience this
Chaffee: in your athletic career, you know, that concept of hitting the wall. That was something that was
Chaffee: very familiar to us when I was growing up. You push yourself. You push yourself and then you hit
the wall. You just have nothing left in the tank. You just dead. Most people stop at that point.
Most people don't even get to that point. But if you hit that point and you keep going and you keep
going and you push yourself and push yourself, sometimes we'll talk about breaking through the wall
Chaffee: and you get your second wind and your runners high. You can just keep going and going and
Chaffee: going and going and going. What that is biologically or biochemically is you're running on
carbohydrate rates. Your insulin is up and your fat cells are blocked. You cannot mobilize
an energy from your fat cells. And so you only run on the glucose and glycogen that you have
in your body from your last few meals. And that's finite. That's going to run out. And there's
not that much of it. You have 10, 20, 30 times as much energy stored in your adipose tissue,
even in very slender people. Then you can maximally store in glycogen in your muscles and
liver. So it's massive, massive, energy stores there. They're just going to waste if you don't tap
Chaffee: into them. So what breaking through the wall is that you've run out of glycogen, you feel like
garbage. Your blood sugar is dropping and you can't get it up and you feel horrible. So you can't
get your blood sugar up. You can't mobilize glycogen. You can't mobilize blood sugar. You can't
Chaffee: make key tones. You keep pushing. Normally, insulin takes about 24 hours to come down to a
Chaffee: reasonable amount that you can start. You're getting your key tones up and your blood sugar up.
Chaffee: But if you force the issue instead of letting you die, your body shifts gears and starts mobilizing
your fat source. And obviously, you have all this energy again because now you're tapped into your
fat stores. And now you can just go and go and go. So a key to genic athlete is always in their second
they're always in their runner side. They're always past the wall. They're never going to run
into the wall because they started after the wall and they can just go. And that's what I experienced
as an athlete in my early 20s from 20 to 25 where they're about. And I could not get tired.
I could not run out of energy. I just could go and go and go. Now there's a limit. I mean,
your muscles have a specific limit, your lung capacity and all these sorts of things. But if you're
yourself maximum, you will have energy. You know, your your body may not be able to go with you,
but you'll have the energy to do what everything that your body can handle. And then when you're
pushing yourself that hard and you're doing so much more and you're going so much harder,
Chaffee: you get in much more fit. And you recover much better when you're just eating me. And your body
Chaffee: heals better and you build muscle better and you build strength and endurance better. And so
Chaffee: your performance and your athleticism just goes up at an astounding exponential sort of pace.
Chaffee: And so you can get very, very good shape. And eventually I got in such a good shape that I
simply could not push myself to the point that that I would wear myself out. I could not. I was
sprinting a quid moons little marathon. I just sprint for a mile, dead sprint for a mile.
And then I just run hard for my I could just keep going. I just figured, you know, I just like
all right, and I was just, I said, I do this much so I did that much. It wasn't like I was like,
oh, it was just, it was fine. It was no issue. And then I was running hard. And then it was a dead sprint
for another mile. And then running hard for a mile. And then dead and I just did this. I just kept doing this.
And eventually I would just stop after I did, you know, 10, 15 miles. I would just be like,
okay, I've just gone up and down the bowl of order in the on Lake Washington bowl of order
in Kirk and Washington, I've run up and down by the by the lake front there in the summer, especially
and I just do, it was three miles up, three miles back. And so I do that, you know, two times,
Chaffee: three times. And then just be, I just was already bored. I'm like, I get, do I just stop now? I could have
Chaffee: just kept going forever just sprinting a mile running hard for a mile, sprinting a mile running hard
Chaffee: for just sprinting the whole time. And I would just get bored because running stupid.
You know, I'm going to agree with you right there, Dr. Sheffey. And I'm going to say this to
all of everybody at listening. I've been a high school physician for 21 years and I've told my
students many times, I hate running. I can't stand it, right? I like to run on the pitch,
on the soccer pitch, the rugby pitch, the basketball court, whatever. I need to be motivated
in that sense to be running. So that's that's that's amazing, Dr. Sheffey. You from your experience,
because I haven't really had a chance to really experience being in the state of ketosis and
being in athlete the way you have, because you did it twice. You did it when you're in your 20s
correct, and then for five years, and then you did it kind of later on in life, right? Like,
just recently, right now. So the next thing I want to, I want to say Dr. Sheffey is from my experience
from the last 20 months, myself and even with my sons as carnivores, because they are too,
and I'm looking at them on the pitch right now. And I'm really proud of them because
and many parents that are listening to this, my son, Peter, he won't eat a vegetable ever again
in his life. And I used to, five years ago, I used to, it was a struggle. We would make him,
he always liked me, and we would make my wife would make broccoli, and he would sit there for an
hour, two hours. You're not leaving the table until you finish those five broccoli. And to me,
that was abuse. We were abusing him. So anyways, he will never eat broccoli.
Chaffee: Being that kid, and it felt like abuse. Absolutely. We're going to talk later on about parents
and what they're doing to their children later on. But I wanted to just expand on what you're talking
about a little bit from my experience. Last summer, I was hitting a gym quite hard. As a stage
for cancer patient, with my sons, we joined a gym, and just recently built a gym in our basement.
And the one thing that I've noticed, Dr. Sheffey, and I speak about this, because I actually
caught a weightlifting course for the past 10 years at my high school. And it's very basic. And I teach
the kids about hypertrophy in terms of your muscle fibers growing and getting bigger and stronger.
And I talk about Dom's delayed onset muscle soreness. And basically, when I was working out with
my teenagers that I teach, and I went really hard in terms of heavy weights, like squats,
or bench, or back, I would have Dom's delayed onset muscle soreness, either 24 hours later,
or 48 hours later. And it would last, sometimes when I did squats, I couldn't even put my socks
on the next day, because it was so bad. And I was carved dependent this time. Like, this is a big
time carved dependent. So in the past summer, I was working out the boys, and I was getting the
weights quite up there again. And I noticed, I didn't, I haven't had any soreness. I don't have any
soreness anymore. I don't have that same delayed onset muscle soreness. And is it because I'm
using fat as fuel, and I'm having adequate amounts of protein in me, that I'm repairing my
muscles very quickly? Can you expand on that a little more in terms of the muscle soreness in the recovery?
Yeah, it's really just from plant toxins. Right? These are inflammatory factors that are in the
Chaffee: lads that are trying to deter you. So the plants trying to make you sick is trying to make
Chaffee: sore. It's trying to screw up your hormones. It's trying to poison you. So you stop eating it.
You know, it's just trying to tell you, no one's certain terms back the hell off. You know,
I'm going to hurt you. I'm going to be bad for you. And so if you're around in the wild, and you
just feel like a superhero all the time, and you're really hungry, and you're like, well, I'll just
I'll just try this instead of going to hunting. I'll try chewing on this, you know, sort of taste
bitter, but yeah, whatever. And all of a sudden, you're just sore and miserable, and you're like,
never again, I'm never touching that thing again. If it doesn't kill you, right? Because a lot of them
do kill you. Most of them will kill you if you try that. So don't try that. And so that's the thing.
You have these inflammatory factors that are causing inflammation, pain, stiffness swelling,
and soreness, and they can act on other parts of your body that are healing as well. So you have
areas of some sort of nightess for a damage like arthritis, you have damage of the cartilage,
your bones are scraping together, which is always an unpleasant image. You have an injury,
you have sciatica, you have compression on a nerve, you have all these different sorts of things
Chaffee: that are a bit of a problem, but now they're exacerbated. You have all this inflammation that
Chaffee: is making that pain signal 10 times worse. And so when you just get rid of that, it just goes away.
Chaffee: Do an experiment. You have all the same protein, all the same ketones, and fat, and all that
sort of stuff. You'll be in ketosis. You'll be running on fat. Have all this protein,
drink one cup of coffee. Let me know how you feel. You'll be sore for two days. So it's not the
lack of protein in fat. It's not the lack of being in ketosis. ketosis does help because
when the ketones are higher, they directly suppress inflame zones, and that will reduce the pain
swelling, and all that sort of stuff all on its own. But if you drink coffee that shouldn't
kick you out of ketosis, it's not going to stop you from having the protein that you just ate,
and the fat, and everything like that, but it will make you sore. So there are inflammatory
factors and chemicals that are harmful that we experience that as pain. And that's part of
that's part of that experience. So we know that there's these toxins that are in there,
and they say, oh, but is there dose makes the poison? Well, look, the dose is pretty damn small
because one cup of coffee will have you sore for two days. It's just that no one stops eating these
things. So they don't realize that they are being poisoned, that they actually have a much greater
effect on their body than they take for granted, or they take that for granted. And so I'm
Chaffee: just going to write a note for myself. But like, so that's the thing. So it's inflammatory
Chaffee: factors. So, you know, not being in ketosis, you know, sure that that will have you'll have higher
information then. But they're they're due seem to be just actual toxins in the plants that will
mess you up. I certainly find that the grains and beans and legumes and seeds, they make that
Chaffee: pain come back far worse. So, you know, when I was sort of experimenting early on, I was at a restaurant
Chaffee: and I had had some beans and rice sort of mixed in with some of the meat that it was like chopped
Chaffee: meat. And so I was like trying to scrape it off and it's just a little bit of rice and a little bit
Chaffee: of meat. But it was like a little smear on it. It wasn't even like big chunks of it. I was thinking,
I'm like, I'm getting a little bit of this in me. Like, well, maybe I'll just take a spoonful of the
Chaffee: rice and a spoonful of beans and just see what it does to me. Right. And then I said, no, I'm not going
Chaffee: to do that because if I make an excuse to do that, even for an experiment, I'll make excuse to
for other things. I'm just not going to do it. So I just did that. Thank God, I didn't do that.
Because just a little residue of beans and rice on this, it felt like someone was stabbing me
in the spine in my lower back for the next four days. And it, when did this happen? Dr. Sheffey?
How long ago? Six years ago. Six years ago. Six years ago. Yeah. Yeah, I actually went to dinner
with a pro soccer player in Seattle funny enough. And then we sort of went, they got this like,
yeah, it was like a Mexican place and just had this little beans and rice on an
ass and proud without the beans and rice. And of course, it came on the beans and rice,
like shit. I'm like scraping this stuff off. And, you know, I felt, you know, as a bit funny that
day, not a big deal. The next day I woke up and I could not get out of bed. I tried to get out
like, oh, it was just like something just stabbing the back. I was like, whoa, what's wrong? What's
going on? It was, it was debilitating pain. That I could not sit up out of bed. I was in so much pain.
It took, I don't know, how many minutes to sort of like shimmy over. I tried to like,
sort of move over and roll over with so painful. And I was able to sort of finally get on my,
on my front and then I sort of was able to push myself up on all fours, slide over to the side
and get into a sitting position on the side of the bed and just sit there and breathe and
catch my breath and then slowly sort of work my way up and stand up. And I'm like, oh my god,
what a hell happened in my back. And I just had to be, I had to be locked rigid, straight and stand
up because I couldn't, I couldn't let being bent forward or anything like that. And it was very
difficult to get in and out of chairs and then lying down. If I moved in the middle of the night,
like, in my sleep, it would wake me up. It would shock me awake from the pain four days. That
wow. That's crazy. Yeah. Dr. Shafi, you know, I'm listening to you,
speak about that experience. That's, it's mind blowing or what you had experienced just by a little bit
of that, of that poison that you ate. But I look at, I look at there, are you today, and what I've
been experiencing as a teacher, a coach, an educator, and the youth I'm dealing with. I'm constantly
hearing kids complain about them being sore, being tired, over, over, over, they, they worked at
over, did it. And you know, even with my, and it's a reflection, it's got to be a reflection of
their diets and what they're eating because carbohydrates is through the roof. You can barely
go into any restaurant, any grocery store where they're pushing it in our face, right? Carbohydrates,
refined sugars, GMOs, all that stuff. And you know, I'm looking at Peter and Dante on the pitch right
now and Peter's constantly talking to me about because they both actually have fitness once a week
and they work out hard with, with, with the fitness instructor. And Peter says all his teammates
complain about being sore after and he does, he's not feeling that. So it's really, it's, I'm
really proud to hear him say that. And I just, you know, I just want to, I just wanted to add that
in, Dr. Shafi. And I'm looking at my, I'm getting tons of comments. My, my feed, a lot of people
are talking and communicating. And this is great. And the conversations that they're having in,
my, on my channel is great. I'm sure there's a lot of stuff happening on your channel right now
to Dr. Shafi. So I, I just want to say to everybody, we're going to start taking some questions.
Q, I, I, I, I just got my first Q, Q, Q come in. But it will start with Dr. Shafi. But even before
you pull up your first question, I just want to give a huge shout out because I'm super excited,
Dr. Shafi. I'm wearing this brand new t-shirt. Okay, that carry man sent me in the mail. I just got it.
It's healing humanity. It's the documentary he's making. It's about the power of the proper
human diet. So I'm really proud. And I'm also wearing my Dr. Shafi hat today. Okay, I bought this.
Like, I bought this a few months ago. And I, I, I have to wear every time I'm on with Dr. Shafi.
And I, I am a big, as, as athletes, you know, I'm, I'm, I'm big into Nike because of Michael Jordan.
And, and Adidas is more of a soccer brand, which I was, I was into back in, when I was playing
university soccer. Some of my favorite players like Alessandro Delpiro, David Beckham, they were,
they were Adidas. So I do like that brand as well. So I just want to say, I'm representing
Carrie Mann. I'm representing Dr. Shafi today. And I'm super excited as this, as this,
this live podcast continues on. So Dr. Shafi, do you want to pop up your first question?
If you got one there, um, yeah, see, see, I didn't actually, let me see, see if I have some of these,
so I don't have them start. I got one right. I don't want to go. Why don't you go for, I'll take a look
through. I guess this is one of my favorite subscribers. Her name is Sandra, one hole for all,
so high Sandra. And I just want to say she, she's got a question here. If the young man who's not
overweight is working out and wants to build muscle, should he have more protein than fat? I used
the babysit this guy six years old and tell him he should be a carnivore. So should they have more
Chaffee: protein than fat working out, not overweight? No, you know, you generally need to, I mean,
Chaffee: you'll need enough fat, you'll need enough protein. Even if you're working out,
you actually tend to need a lot of fat for the, for the energy that you'll, that you'll be
Chaffee: spending. So that's where a lot of your energy comes from. It's fat. If you don't have enough fat,
Chaffee: you'll start converting more protein into energy. And you won't be using that for a building block
Chaffee: anyway, you'll be using it for energy. So really, what you want to do, you want to a lot of fat,
you want a lot of meat. You still want it about the same proportions. And so you just, you just eat
fatty meat until it stops tasting good. You eat enough fat so that you don't get constipated.
And do you body takes care of the rest? You know, it's usually about one to two grams of
fat for one gram of protein. That's usually how that works out. But your people's bodies will change
on their demand. They'll need a bit more protein. Sometimes we'll need a bit more fat. Sometimes
but you can, you can tend to, you'll tend to figure that out intuitively. Your body will just sort
Chaffee: of tell you. And so to go by taste and more lean meat will start tasting really, really good.
Chaffee: You'll sort of be a bit over the fat, but it's only in taste, really good. Those sorts of things,
you know, will, will kick you off and give you a hint of what your body wants. And so
Chaffee: you just listen to that, really. Here's another one. Can I go body building with only meat?
I think we kind of touched on that. We definitely, the energy source we can use is definitely fat.
And I've had no, I've had no problem using it when I've been working out.
Chaffee: Yeah. Well, and specifically for body builders, all the professional body builders in the
Chaffee: golden era of body building, Vince Garonda, Serge New Gray, those guys, they were steak and
steak and steak and steak and steak and steak and steak. Serge New Gray would eat six pounds of
horse meat a day. Right. The guy was just like a, like a Mongol warrior. He was just an absolute beast.
And he was Arnold Schwarzenegger's body in a body idol. That's who Arnold Schwarzenegger grew up saying,
Chaffee: I want to look like that guy. Right. And then Arnold Schwarzenegger, what did he do? He didn't do the
Chaffee: game changer bullshit that he's, that he's trying to push now because he's selling it on trying
to help his, his buddy James Cameron, make a mint on his P protein company. And that's what
that is. I was just a giant commercial because James Cameron, who was the EP on that,
Chaffee: he owns like $140 million worth of a P protein company. So it's just, oh, hey, you know,
Chaffee: you don't want to eat meat all so bad, but you need protein. Hey, we've judged. I'm going to have
Chaffee: some right here. Yeah. Why do you buy it? Arnold Schwarzenegger is a vegetarian vegan now, right?
Chaffee: My ass. You know, like he's just now. Of course, he's not. I don't know. He's aging quite quickly.
Chaffee: Well, he doesn't look good anyway. I mean, it's not, it's not a, it's not a, you know, if he's,
if he is vegan vegetarian, it's not, it's not working well for him. I mean, he's older anyway, but,
you know, Maggie's older than him. Maggie's an over a decade older than him. She looks better than him.
But, you know, although all the old school guys, including Arnold were steak and eggs,
steak and eggs, steak and eggs, steak and eggs. Sometimes they include carbs once a week,
because they thought that you needed to store glycogen that way. That's wrong. You don't need to do that.
There are professional bodybuilders right now who only eat meat. Ronnie Coleman, apparently,
hated vegetables. He thought they were bad for him, so he wouldn't eat them. I know a guy here who
helped like, how's the company that helped like make Ronnie Coleman supplements his line of supplements.
Chaffee: And, and he was telling me that he's told me that Ronnie Coleman was like, yeah, he's like,
Chaffee: telling us, like, oh, hey, here's the guy saying that vegetables. I told you, I told you vegetables
were bad those things are awful. And so, yeah, that's the thing. So, I did a, specifically on bodybuilding.
I've done posts on that. I've done videos on that. And I've interviewed a lot of professional
bodybuilders who have just done keto or even just carnivore. And, and been like European
pro champion natural in a, in a non-tested competition. So, this was with pros that were on the juice
and he was natural. And, and he won the whole European pro championship. That was Richard Smith
who goes by keto pro on Instagram. And, we have a, a couple YouTube videos together where we talk
Chaffee: about all this stuff. And we go on through the science. I've been talking to his, his experiences.
Chaffee: And, and he got absolutely jacked and shredded. He said it was just cheating. It was so easy to get
complete, so shredded on a carnivore diet. It was even easier than doing it on keto. So, yes,
you can definitely do bodybuilding on on a carnivore diet. In fact, you'll be better off
Chaffee: because if you're eating a whole bunch of carbs like, yeah, you'll put on bulk. Oh, I got a bulk. I
put on fat if you're going to put on muscle, bullshit. You only put on fat if you're eating carbs.
If you only eating meat, you will not put on fat. You will only put on muscle. And, you'll,
so everything you put on is just lean body, body mess. It's lean muscle mess. I said,
well, you have to have a chloric surplus. No, if you have a chloric surplus, you'll put on fat.
You'll put on muscle. You know, so, you know, like the, for the stand effort is out there.
It's just like, learn some goddamn biology, you know, and math. You know, it's chloric surplus
equals storing fat. That's the whole idea, even though calories are a bit of a nonsense. But,
Chaffee: the whole idea is you eat more food than your body has demand for. You're going to store it as
energy, right? It's not just going to just like, well, I guess we got it all, I guess we'll just put it
in the muscle. You know, that's not what happened. Your body of a stimulus to build a certain amount of
put into fat. So you need to eat enough. And that's the same thing you can do. You just eat
until you're, until meat stops tasting good fatty meat stops tasting good. Your body will tell
you how much it needs. And so you don't need to calculate that out. And you'll only put on lean
Chaffee: muscle. So the, the golden era body builder guys, like Garanda and Serge New Gray, even Arnold,
you know, you look at him. Arnold was never in this puffy fat stage. He was always jacked. And he
got more shredded coming up to competition. But he was already pretty damn shredded. And so
his Serge New Gray and Vince Garanda, they were just always ripped your round. And then they just get a
little more lean just for competition. And that's it. So that's, that's, that's, it's a huge advantage
to be on a corner for one of all your builder. Absolutely. Thanks, Dr. Shafi. I, I, I, I, I love the passion
that you get into answer in these questions. So the, the subscriber is keep, keep asking these
good questions. And I apologize if I'm missing anything. I, I got some questions popping up. Here's
another one. My dad is two months on carnivore and his triglycerides went up from mid 80s to 130
and his hdl, hdl dropped from 90s to 65. Is there any reason for concern?
Chaffee: Well, so it's, it's, it's, it's, you have to, sort of ask, you know, wonder, are, are there,
Chaffee: is he really doing carnivores, he having other things, is he eating other things, having
Chaffee: his sugar drinking alcohol, artificial sweeteners, any of these other sorts of things. Because,
Chaffee: you know, you typically, you would see sort of the other way around. You see triglycerides come
down, hdl go up, things like that. Um, however, things like stress, people can really stress
down, not sleeping really well. That can negatively affect both of those numbers. I don't even
test those things anymore. It was a fun, they were useless. I think that testing,
it's cholesterol was just a con in the first place. Why are we even testing anymore? I just
say we ignored it and let it, like, nor did let it go away because it was a con from the beginning.
And so why are we paying attention to it now? I think it's a waste of time and money to get,
to get your cholesterol checked. However, um, thing that we should realize, hey, stress can
make this worse, poor sleep can make that worse. And lower hdl and higher triglycerides probably
the only useful thing in your cholesterol panel, except for higher LDL and total cholesterol,
I mean, you're statistically more likely to live longer. So that's good. Um, but it's not where
we think it is anyway. And if you have low hdl and higher triglycerides, it can show metabolic
dysfunction. And so, and that can come about from stress and from poor sleep, as well as a bad
Chaffee: diet and drinking alcohol and things like that. Um, one thing to remember too, is that if you take
Chaffee: cholesterol 10 times in the same day, you'll get 10 different results. And so, oh my god, what's happening?
If you work out the day before, you'll have different results. If you have sex before you go
and get your cholesterol tests, you'll have different results or the day before. Right? If you're
stressed out leading up to it, you're going to have different results. So you need to, you need to get
first of all, you need to get multiple data points, right? See, I mean, one of those could have just
Chaffee: been an aberrant test, could have just been something off. It's not actually indicative of
Chaffee: regular trend. And so, you need multiple tests to see what's going on. Um, so, you want to do the same
in the same way every time. It can assist in pattern. You want to do it the same time in the morning,
every morning, you know, usually between 8.9 a.m., you want to fast for the exact same period of time.
If you fast for 10 hours, and then you fast for 12 hours, you'll get two different results.
And so, and you can try that. Take your bloods, take it at 8 in the morning, take it at 10 in the
right? You will get two different results. You know, take your tests, work out, go take it again,
you'll get two different results. This is such a volatile test. It's so useless. So you take it
in the same time of the morning between 8.9 a.m., fasting from 9.p.m. the night before, only water
after that, only water in the morning, no coffee, tea, supplements, medications, until after your
test. You take at least two glasses of water, no more than four glasses of water, same hydration
instead of. If you're taking any B vitamins or anything that contains biotin, which is a B vitamin,
that can disrupt your hormones, that can disrupt your blood tests, that can change your
Chaffee: results as well. So stop those for three days before you take your blood test and then be very calm
Chaffee: and relax and no stress for the certainly the morning of in a couple of days leading up to it.
Don't get pissed off and traffic on your way in to getting the blood test,
you know, don't get it in a fight with someone in your family or get pissed off.
I'm getting kids out of the house and go to school, just be chill. And no stress exercise or
sexual activity the morning over the day before your test. You do it all those things consistently,
you'll get much more consistent results. And then, you need a few more data points.
You know, I wouldn't worry too much about it. You know, check it again in three months and then
three months, six months, whatever, cholesterol was never the problem. You know, as metabolic health
could be impacted and that could change his HGL and then triglycerides. A carnivore diet is only
going to improve that. Saturated fat is known to raise your HDL and eating carbohydrates and sugar
and alcohol and seed oils, raise your triglycerides. You're not eating any of that and you're eating,
you know, so your triglycerides are going to come down. You're all eating saturated fat things
are good for you. So your HDL is going to go up and you're in the right metabolic state and that's
going to help you as well. So then you optimize sleep and stress and you'll be fine. I wouldn't
worry too much about it. Just try to make things consistent in that pattern so you get reliable
test results and reduce stress, prioritize sleep, get out on the sun and chill out. Maybe
fine. Absolutely. The whole stress thing and keep in your cells calm, keep in your mitochondria
and healthy is a huge thing that I'm learning about quite often. So I make a lot of sense. There's
a lot of variables that definitely affect things and we're always quick to blaming the carnivore
diet or only eating meat and the people don't really understand there's a lot of other things.
You're like you're right, especially sleep, Dr. Shaky, that's something that we need to pay attention
to a little more. Just looking, I got so many questions. If you ever want to pop a question out,
let me know Dr. Shaky, but I have this, I've had this one up for a bit. Jeff, did your boys decide
to adopt the carnivore diet on their own? Obviously, not on their own. Obviously, parents
do and they should influence their kids on how to be successful in life. And Mike, my two boys,
I can only imagine the life they're living with their father, myself having stage 4 cancer,
but they've been amazing teammates for me along my journey and we've been watching people like Dr.
Shaky, Dr. Baker, Dr. Kilt's talk about all their success they've been having on the carnivore diet.
Chaffee: We're listening to it all the time, so my sons have realized and they're pretty smart boys
that they want to be as optimal as possible in life. And I'm really proud of my son Peter. He's in grade
10. Last year in grade nine, he had a 96% average. He actually participated in six different
school sports. Wow, still participating in his club soccer and the soccer that he's doing right now.
He's go-go-go all the time and he's really focused and for a teenager,
not saying all teenagers are bad, teenagers are great, they're the best people ever,
but he's a little more focused than your normal teenager. And I think the diet has helped a lot.
I think his mental clarity is through the roof. He's focused. He's a wild plan, especially as a boy,
as a teenager, and I'm really proud of him. So they didn't do it on their own.
I definitely being involved in my life, it's motivated them to be as optimal as possible.
So that's that. Do you have any questions you want to pop up? Dr. Shaky,
I think we're both seeing the same, was that both from both our feeds will pop up there?
Is it? Oh, is it? Okay, okay, that's good. I didn't know. I'm new to disguise. I apologize. My technical
skills aren't the greatest. Here I'll pop this one up here. Taking away the taste aspect,
how many grains of protein would you recommend per pound for the average person?
And for someone building muscle, I understand to start with equal parts fat and adjust.
Yeah, it's a difficult one to answer. I mean, you think about how complex or biochemistry is
in our metabolic demands, especially when people in different states or everything like that.
Like you have tens of trillions of cells, they have tens of trillions of chemical reactions,
you have every few seconds. So this is so much more complex than we could ever calculate.
Chaffee: There is no equation that's complex enough to figure out exactly what our dailyins and
Chaffee: else need to be. We simply don't have the variables, all the different things that we're doing
on that day-to-day basis. So there's really no way to calculate that. Just like one gram of
protein per kilo, that's sort of nonsense. I guess it's sort of a rough guide, but it's not going
Chaffee: to be a fantasy. But it doesn't matter because you don't have to. You don't have to figure it out.
Chaffee: Your body figures it out. I've never seen a koala pull out a calculator to figure out their
macros, right? And yet they know how much they're supposed to eat because they just eat it.
And so if you're eating what you're supposed to eat, your hunger and your taste signals will
Chaffee: tell you how much to eat. So it's hard to say, if someone is trying to build muscle,
Chaffee: you're going to need more than you did before. If you're static and you're environment,
and you're just sort of sedentary just having normal life, you're going to, you remind me
the X. When I start working out and I start lifting weights a lot, I need to eat 2X. So I'll
literally twice as much during the day, but it's purely driven by my hunger. I'm not saying,
I'm not, you know, this stand-up or things going on. I have to force myself to do that. No,
my body doesn't form me and I naturally will be more hungry and my body will want more.
If I'm not able to get it as much as my body wants, I'm not able to eat twice a day or something
like that or get enough when I do. I simply won't put on the muscle mass that I would have
Chaffee: otherwise. If I'm able to eat as much as my body's telling me to, I will put on muscle extraordinarily
Chaffee: easy. It's easier and more easily than I've ever experienced in my entire life. So it's pretty, it's
going to be different. It's going to be different for your size certainly, but it's also going to be
different for your metabolic demand. You know, if people, you know, I've worked with anorexics,
Chaffee: recovered, recovered anorexic who actually go carnivore and recover from anorexia. And
Chaffee: little small women that are like a BMI of nine at one point. And now they're eating meat again
Chaffee: and they're doing amazing and they're putting on weight. They're eating 3, 4 times as much as
Chaffee: you know, sometimes, right? It's like it's insane how much they'll eat. You know, one lady was
putting it more maybe not four times as much as me. But you know, good like twice as much as I would,
you know, and I'm not a small man, you know, I'm like at the moment I'm like 6, 3, 2, 3, you know. So
this little tiny little slender woman was even like 8,000 calories a day in rib eye. And that's
what she needed because her body was at such a deficit of of nutrients that she just needed this.
And she was putting on weight, but she wasn't like a massive bodybuilder. She didn't get
fat or anything like that. She was still very skinny at the end of the year, but she was eating like
Chaffee: 8,000 calories a day. And then that sort of tapered off when her body caught up. So unfortunately,
Chaffee: it's not, it's not like I can't give you a straight cramage amount. Your body will figure it out for
you. And you'll end up getting a couple hundred grams of protein a day. It's going to,
it's going to be well in excess of of what anyone would say. Oh, Graham, 1.2 grams, 2 grams
per kilo. Any of these sorts of things like you'll, you'll exceed that. Your body will definitely
exceed that, especially if you're working out a lot. Okay. I pops up this next question, Dr.
Shafin. I think it kind of, it goes along the same topic. If a person eats higher protein than fat
and is in ketosis when working out with the body prioritize using fat stores versus the protein
being converted to sugar. When they say protein being converted to sugar, I think that's a process
Chaffee: called gluconeogenesis. Yeah, it's not just your protein, though. You'll do that from fat too. So
Chaffee: it's not just, it's not just from protein in that. And the idea that if you have excess protein that
automatically get turned into carbs is not true. It's demand driven. It's not substrate driven.
It's not, you know, because there's, oh, it was just like that. Oh, yeah, that's just excess,
you know, food your all. We're just turning it in the muscle. No, no, that's not how it worked.
Your body does what it wants to do. And then if it has stuff left over, puts it in storage,
that's basically what's going to happen. You know, it's, it's hard to say, you know, your body's
your body's going to, yes, use some fat. But if you're eating far less fat than your body wants,
Chaffee: you will start converting protein into energy. And it's not, it's not, you're not going to
Chaffee: trick your body into losing fat. In fact, a lot of times when you start doing that, you try
Chaffee: restricting the amount of fat that you're trying to, that you're eating. If your body's telling
Chaffee: you to eat the fat, it means eat the fat. You know, you're not going to trick your body into doing
Chaffee: this. Yeah, you can starve yourself into a smaller, you know, dress-off. Like everyone knows that.
But it will depress your metabolism and you'll plateau and you won't, you won't get any further
than that. And so you won't get like the ultimate gains. You know, it's sort of like, you know,
like that, taking a short cut and then you like you get there, but you didn't actually get
Chaffee: all the way there. You know, it's just, it's just, you know, it's like a deal with the devil.
Chaffee: You know, it looks like you're getting something good, but then actually it pulls you up short to a dead end.
Chaffee: So you can, you can slow down your metabolism and then all of a sudden you're not doing as
Chaffee: well, then when you start eating again, your body goes, like, okay, you know, we're going to store
Chaffee: this because you're telling your body that you don't have resources available. You know, what animal
when resources are available, when food's available, when their primary optimal food is available,
Chaffee: and they're hungry, they don't eat. When does that ever happen? It doesn't happen. So your
Chaffee: body doesn't know what you're doing. Your body doesn't know that you're trying to lose fat.
Chaffee: No, I know what he's doing. I'll help him out. It just sees, we're telling him to eat fat. He's
not eating fat. That means there's no fat available. We need to shut down. We need to store and
Chaffee: save resources. So you don't want to think about fat as a calorie source. You want to think of
Chaffee: fat as a nutrient. It is an essential nutrient. There are essential fatty acids that you have
Chaffee: to have or you get sick and you can die. There are essential fats available in nutrients that you
Chaffee: have to have or you can get sick and you'll die. Also, if you want to lose weight, you want to
actually prioritize fat as well. Think about it this way. Calories don't have weight.
Calories is a measure of heat energy. This is why I say they use less metric.
So when you eat things, you're eating matter, you're eating master eating atoms. That has weight.
They weigh in grams. So what's that equation? It's nine calories per one gram of fat, right?
And then four calories per one gram of carbs and protein. So people think, well, this is less
calories. So I'm eating less calories and all of these. My calories, no, it's not really how that works.
You'll end up eating similar amount and your body will tell you to eat this amount.
Chaffee: You could starve yourself but you're going to crash your metabolism. So if you're eating
Chaffee: fat and protein or don't eat carbs, think about it this way. If you flip that equation around,
Chaffee: now you look at it's one gram per nine calories or 2.2 grams per nine calories for protein or
carbs. So you're actually taking in less matter, less mass to get that energy. So in fact,
you're much more efficient getting your energy from fat than you would be from protein and things
like that. You're not just going to prioritize your fat stores. If you're eating enough fat,
if you're eating a protein, then you prioritize your fat stores. And your body says, hey, we're not
in a family. We don't have to store on to this. Let's raise your metabolism. Let's see what we can do here.
So, you know, another way to look at this or test this in yourself. And if you're burning
more protein than you want for energy and turning that into glucose, as you check your urea,
your urea and your B1, B1 and creatinine. But that starts going up. That means you're
converting a lot more amino acids into glucose and energy. Because you have to, you have to
leave off that amino group. That's that nitrogen group. You turn that into ammonia that turns into
urea. So urea starts creeping up. That means you're eating too much protein on a fat. And you're
using the protein as energy instead of the fat. And you can do that if you're overweight. It doesn't
Chaffee: matter. You know, if you have a lot of excess fat and you're eating weight too much protein,
Chaffee: you're about to use that protein as energy. You know, it doesn't need it, right? And so,
and it needs energy. And you're telling it you're in a famine and you're starving. So it's going
to say, well, we don't want to use our savings. We want to use that as little as possible. And we want
to use other sorts of means. So you're not going to outtrick your biology. You're not going to
trick millions of years of evolution. You know, just eat fatty meat until it stops tasting good.
Chaffee: Lift weights, sprint if you can. And, um, and just give it time. You know, if this is, you're
Chaffee: not in a rush. You know, there are people that that lose hundreds of pounds in a year. And there's
other people that lose 40 pounds in a year. Or as people that don't lose any weight for six months or
a year. And then they start losing weight. Everyone's at different places. You don't want to force
this. Just eat fatty meat until it stops tasting good. Don't eat anything else. Let your body do
Chaffee: this thing. And you'll be fine, you know. And just be patient. Let your body do its thing.
Chaffee: And like you'll get good results. The most important thing is your health. And then you're eating
the right things and give your body the proper nutrition for for optimal health. That's what you need
Chaffee: to do. So, you know, like you can trick yourself and take drugs and do it and take a
Chaffee: ejectal zempic and do all sorts of, you know, things to try to lose weight. And you'll lose weight.
But you'll really hurt yourself in the process. And you'll end up gaining more weight
Chaffee: than you lost at once you stop. So it's not the right way to do it. You know, slow and steady
Chaffee: wins the race. And the fact that matter is the most people doing carnivore eating more fat,
lose it, shit ton of weight. More quickly than anything else they've ever tried and it's consistent
and you can maintain it and you can keep doing this for the rest of your life.
Absolutely. Thanks Dr. Shafi. I'm going to have to rewatch this live a few times because your
answers are amazing and they're very scientific and there's been a lot of research and you've been
studying quite a bit. So I think these answers are awesome and I just want to pull this up because
I know what you do this all the time and you say thank you. We got about like five more minutes but I
appreciate the detailed answers. Dr. I'm on day 14 feeling amazing. This is double nickels and
keto $20. Thank you Dr. Shafi for all of you. You're a rock star. I appreciate all you do. He
absolutely is a rock star. He's like superman. He's Michael Jordan to me. Read a $5 super sticker. Thank you
very much. He says he could keep for the earlier question on protein fat and other $5. Just coming
back here will take a few more questions. I had one ready. The next time I do this I'm going to be
a lot better at this everybody. I learned a lot from Dr. Shafi even when it comes to technology
sometimes. Just learned by doing I had to struggle through this the way you know what I was
Chaffee: starting out to. So here we go. When the samurai were hunting meat for their own consumption
Chaffee: and the imperial court tried to discourage rice growing peasants from eating it. You think something
similar is happening today. 100% there was the same thing everywhere in the world. The elites ate meat
in the peasants ate grains. That is what happened. That was in England. That was in India. That was
in everywhere. When the British colonized India they pulled them out of the forest. They stopped them
hunting because those were now the king's woods. The king's deer and they put them on
on fields. They had them growing grains and they paid them in grains and so they come overnight
changed their diet. They were always always Hinduism. No. Most people still ate meat.
In fact the original Brahman text was all about eating cows. It was all about how important
it was to eat cows. That sort of sacred, you know, colding the cow is sacred. It's probably
a holdover from that. It was such an important animal. But there's an important animal to
sacrifice and eat and share and feast and things like that and someone important came to visit.
Chaffee: You were required by the religious text to sacrifice a bull and your best bull and have a feast and
Chaffee: these sorts of things. That's exactly what's happening. They're trying to make this
the food of the elite again and they're trying to make people sick and dependent on the food
supply. If you have animals, if you raise animals, if you hunt in the woods, you're independent.
They don't want people being independent. They want people being deep-ended.
Chaffee: There's some weird stuff going on with hunting. There's some weird zombie plague going on with
deer. I think like Mark Zuckerberg went around and did a campaign and
inoculated a hundred thousand deer with what? For why? Well, for what reason?
But the hell do they need to be inoculated for against what? And all of a sudden you have this
zombie deer apocalypse where they have these are crazy neurological problems. And what's that
Chaffee: doing? Is that going to spread? Is that because of the inoculations? Is that what they were
Chaffee: going on here? Is that going to be transferable to humans? Is that transferable to other
deer or other animals? This is some scary stuff. And you know, people are desperately trying
to vilify me and they're desperately trying to stick the masses on just plant-based garbage that
we know is toxic to us. We're getting sicker and sicker than we've ever been in human history.
And and it is a direct result of the crap that we're eating. Absolutely.
One more quick thing. That was one of the major things. I was one of the major ways of keeping
the surf class, the peasant class suppressed and oppressed was you would you limited the meat supply.
Everyone knew how important that was and you just you kept it limited and that kept them
weak and subservient. In ancient in ancient Rome, they said, you know, when the plebians,
you know, which were the peasant class, when they would get, when they would get up and they
started getting ready to revolt. They didn't like how things were going. They would start handing
Chaffee: out bread and they'd put on a bunch of circuses and just distract them. Oh, look at these shining
Chaffee: lights. Same thing we're doing is like, hey, here's a free, happy meal. Here's a free Sunday and
Chaffee: come down here and oh, it's free, you know, going to have a free festival in the conference and
Chaffee: a carnival and all this sort of stuff. Same thing. But what people, so they said bread and circuses.
That's what people talk about. You know, just distract the plebians, the surfs, just bread and
Chaffee: circuses, bread and circuses, give them junk food, put them on Netflix and just just distract them
Chaffee: with shiny lights, right? That's what they do. That's been doing for thousands of years. What they
don't tell you is the other side of that equation of bread and circuses was they cut off the meat
supply and then they hand out a bunch of bread and then distract people with, you know, flashing
lights and lines, eating Christians and things like that. But that was part of it. They cut off
the meat supply. They know exactly what they're doing. People know this stuff for thousands of years.
And so, yeah, that's exactly what they're doing. Wow, crazy. Everyone, we're going to start
up and we're going to wrap this up because I've taken 45 minutes of Dr. Shafi staring at nothing
because I was a technology dummy this morning. And then we've been on, we've been on now for just
over an hour. So this has been phenomenal. I just want to, I'm just going to end with this one,
you can get all the nutrition from ribeye too. If you want to feel more better, have liver,
you can be in test science. I know Dr. Shafi, you don't eat any organs and you don't really
need to, I guess, being a lion diet carnivore diet. But I just wanted to pull that up because I was,
I was actually talking to my mother the other day and my mother's in her 70s. And, you know,
she's even fascinated by the diet that I've been doing, obviously. But I remember as an athlete
when I was in high school, especially as a basketball player, my calves would cramp up a lot.
And we had this thing we were taught to eat bananas, right, which to eat bananas for potassium.
So I'm sure my muscle cramps were a combination of, you know, inflammation, maybe not having
enough electrolytes, magnesium and potassium levels for the right muscle contractions. But everything
I'm learning about the ribeye steak and all the essential vitamins and minerals and nutrients
that are in a ribeye steak. I don't know what the actual number is, Dr. Shafi, but it's
something around like there's 10 times the amount of potassium in a ribeye steak versus a banana.
And I'd have to eat like 20 bananas a day to get my calves behaving the way I wanted them to behave.
Chaffee: So I think, is that somewhat correct? What I'm saying there? Yeah, I know me is way more nutrient
Chaffee: dense than all of this nonsense. I mean, it's just it's just all marketing, really. I mean,
Chaffee: and or just based in just flat out lies and propaganda, it's funny how many of these things are,
you know, I mean, did you grow up being told just eat carrots because it's good for your eyesight?
I did. Yeah, yeah, because it's old. There's a lot of care routine and that turns into vitamin A,
retinol. And that's really good for your eyes. And that's crap. That was, there's there's barely any
retinol at the end of the day. There's no retinol. It doesn't exist in plants. Beta care routine can
be converted, but it's like 120th of the beta care routine turns into retinol. It's very inefficient.
So you're really not going to get enough vitamin A. You'd have to eat about six pounds of
carrots a day to get enough vitamin A. And some people don't even convert retinol to or
from World War II, because we had like radar technology. We didn't want the Germans to know
Chaffee: that we had some new technology where we could spot planes before they were visible. And so we
Chaffee: we let it go out there that, oh, we're our pilots are eating a lot of carrots. So they get like a
Chaffee: lot of beta care routine and vitamin A. So they have better vision than they can see these guys way
Chaffee: far off. And it worked. People bought it. And then they didn't actually say that we were joking,
you know, because they, you know, they just they just left it, right? And you're just like the
food pyramid, you know, the government bought up all this grain because they guaranteed the
price of grain because they had to deal with the USSR to sell them grain and they have way too much.
And they just said, wow, we want to get this off our hands. And so they came out with recommendations
saying, hey, you need to eat 9 to 12 servings of grain. And they made the food pyramid. And that
was it that was not based on any of those recommendations. Even the recommendations at the time
were like, yeah, 3 to 4 servings a day. That's that's optimal. They're like, great, 9 to 12 it is.
And that's what they came out with, right? And um, and that was just to sell off the excess
surplus of grain that they had. And then they never walked it back. They just said, well, we're not
going to, we're not going to tell them that's what it was. So they just walked it, they just let it go.
Chaffee: There's been like that since the 50s, you know? So, you know, or 60s, 70s, you know? But anyway,
Chaffee: long, long time, you know, decades. And, um, you know, and it was, it was just total crap. So,
you know, a stake is the most nutrient dense thing in the world besides, you know, liver and organs,
organs are really, really chock full of these stuff. Uh, I tend not to eat organs, but I do
Chaffee: have to do sometimes. There's, um, there's a South African dish or psych basically like minced up
liver with a bit of beef in it and it's wrapped with a suit, like fat and things like that.
I actually find I really like those. So I found a butcher here that would do without all the spices
and seasonings that they use. It's just the meat and the liver. And so I have those every now and then,
and that's fun. I don't think you need to do go crazy on it. There are a lot of people living
Chaffee: 20 years, 30 years. These guys, the Anderson's that have been, um, you know, for the last 25 years,
just eating rib eyes every single day, just rib eyes. And, um, raised, you know, handful of kids,
Chaffee: on the same thing, and they're just, they're all doing great. They look, you know, they look
Chaffee: younger now than they did 25 years ago when they started, you know, and, um, and like, actually,
I've shown their picture to, to people and they were like, they were like, yeah, well, that's obviously,
they're younger here, sort of put on weight here. It doesn't look as, as, uh, as fresh and
or faces, obviously, whether it is like, yeah, that's her 26, uh, when you're saying she looks older,
that's her 46 when you say she looks younger. It's crazy. It's crazy. The difference. Um, so you can get
almost everyone can get all they need from rib eye. Um, some people will have things like
MTHFR, they won't be able to methylate folate as well. And, uh, so just check your folate. You know,
if you're on a corner where I died, I think that's probably the only blood that you should check
is, uh, is your folate and, and potentially be 12 because if you're not methylating these
properly and you're not processing these properly, then, uh, you may just need a bit of extra
liver. And that's it, really. You just add in a bit of organs every now and then, but, you know,
you know, it doesn't have to be much keeping a proportion. You got to be able to cow, you're going
to eat that thing for the next year. It's got one liver, you know, so, you know, space it out. It's not that
big of a deal. And, um, and that's fine. So I still have a little bit of it, but, um, uh,
really only in the, uh, in the, uh, in the version of that, those, that little South African dish.
Sounds good. Uh, Dr. Shafi, um, I'm going to close this off, but I have this other question up here.
And I want this to maybe be answered on my, on our next live because I'm hoping you'll do another
one with me, Dr. Shafi. And what I'm hoping is I can maybe really try to encourage Peter and
Dante to be on with us because I think it's good to hear things from teenagers. I also understand,
I, I'm going to have to build up the courage for them to come on because, uh, when we're on
social media, I get it. All the other teenagers, uh, maybe judging them, right? So it's, it, they
need a lot of courage to get on here, but I, I would like to do my next live. And this question here,
like, can I continue taking, creating something while adapting the carnivore diet,
creating a something I know teenagers, even when I was in high school, um, and this is something
we could touch upon. I know, I kind of know the answer to this. You don't get enough
creating in rib eye snakes and in meat. You don't need to be taken this process garbage that
they're selling teenagers, um, especially how they're, where they're getting the creatine, um,
from, right, and how they're, how they're making that creatine in the supplement. So we could talk
probably more about that and how it, you know, it retains, it retains water in your body.
We could talk about more about that when we, when we're on with my sons, when we get some more,
this, this is what my wish was for today, Dr. Shafi, is that I really hope a lot of parents
of youth were watching this, a lot of parents of athletes were watching this. I'm looking at this,
there's 437 people watching right now. So I'm really blown away. It's pretty awesome. I thank all
my subscribers, all of my, all Dr. Shafi subscribers. It's really the parents and the adults in the
world. My number one passion is youth and we, and I think a lot of us are, as our passion is
our youth and we want to change the world because we're kind of living in a cynical world where
we judge people a lot and we're being brainwashed by the wrong powers in terms of what we
need to be doing to improve ourselves. So I, you know, I, I started today with talking about
Michael Jordan and then I had people say in the chat here, Wayne Greski to stake every day,
every day, every day, every game to use to messy. There's actually someone right now in the soccer
world. His name is Irling Holland and Holland is the number nine striker. He's the Norwegian striker
place where Manchester State, he's in his early 20s. This, this young lad is constantly as an athlete,
trying to improve himself. And he is pretty much in, he pretty much emits to being about 80 to 90
percent carnivore. And he's grown. And I think I believe an inch or an inch and a half in his 20s.
Okay. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. That's Holland. And he wears, and he wears blue light glasses three hours
before bed every single night. So he gets a good sleep because he knows the importance of sleep.
Stuff like that, these are the types of people that we need, our, our children, our athletes,
are you looking up to. And um, Dr. Shafi, you're one of them too. So I just want to say thank
you from the bottom of my heart for being on with me today. And I'm sorry about all the technical
difficulties. Yeah. That's all good, man. That was a pleasure. And yeah, well, hopefully,
yeah, hopefully more parents get onto this and more kids are encouraged to try this because it's,
it's the best thing for them. They'll, they'll develop better than, then they would otherwise,
their brains will be bigger and stronger. Their bodies will be bigger and stronger. They'll be more
athletic. They'll be happier. They'll be less, um, agitated, have less mental health issues. All these
things that you want for your kid, you know, this can be, they won't have major problems with acne
and skin issues and, and, you know, depression and all, you know, kids will get sad, you know,
being teenagers sucks in a lot of ways, you know, when you're dealing with a bunch of teenage drama,
but you can handle it so much better. Everything's just so much more chill. And so it's something
that that I think every parent would love the results of in their kids. Absolutely. Um, yeah,
thank you, Dr. Shafi, uh, for everything and thank all of subscribers and I wish everybody has a great
Sunday. Um, I know you're probably going to bed soon. Hey, Dr. Shafi. Yeah, it's 11 o'clock. So probably
I am so sorry. You need to go back. Yeah, that's all good, man. Take care. Thanks, everyone.